<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: interpersonal | Justin Murphy]]></title>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/categories/interpersonal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-10-02T15:07:01+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[j.murphy@soton.ac.uk]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What trust is not]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/22/what-trust-is-not/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-22T16:50:34+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/22/what-trust-is-not</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Trust is not the absence of fear or insecurity regarding the possibility of betrayal. The very structure of our society wounds us so badly from the very beginning of our lives that perhaps such fears and insecurities are doomed to persist. Rather, trust is the feeling of peaceful confidence in a particular relationship <em>despite</em> whatever fears or insecurities one nonetheless continues to feel. Trust is only meaningful as an <em>earned relief</em> from fear and insecurity; as such, it not only implies the continued presence of fear and insecurity outside of the trust relation, it even requires a practiced awareness of the default fear and insecurity which has typically persisted as a fact throughout the greater part of the whole, global human network. We find negative evidence of this in the observation that partners in an honest trust relation often become so absorbed in their own mutual security that they lose awareness of the frightful insecurity against which they have built that trust with great labors and against great odds. When this happens, the storehouse of trust quickly begins to deplete. In colloquial terms, we often refer to exactly this process when we object to being &ldquo;taken for granted.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Historically, the bourgeois defenses against this tendency are typically strategies of locking-into and locking-up the trust relation as soon as it is sufficiently established: make commitments backed by the wrath of God and the law (marriage); construct a physical space that is at once a fortress against external threats and a prison to contain internal threats of flight (the &ldquo;home&rdquo;); then whither until death in the empty husk of a trust that dies six months after it is locked-in.  Trust in the absence of fear and insecurity is not trust; it is merely a glorified emotional comatose which accomplishes nothing more than self-protection and the <em>forgetting</em> of the real omnipresence of fear and insecurity that persists between nearly everyone else.</p>

<p>Furthermore, this bourgeois illusion of trust is not simply pathetic, which would at least be harmless. This false trust of the bourgeois family is <em>productive</em> of more human fear and insecurity than existed before it was &ldquo;locked-in.&rdquo; It produces net fear and insecurity because the little and tawdry security gained by the bourgeois couple is more than offset by all the lonely, isolated peers who are objectively less secure after each and every exclusive, excluding, and acquisitive bourgeois coupling. Finally, the bourgeois techniques of politically organizing trust not only tend to destroy the true and emancipating reality of any real trust they seek to hoard, but additionally, by their exclusive and excluding nature they hardly permit any honest understanding (in private or public) about how this political organization of trust ultimately fails everyone. The basic political form of the bourgeois couple necessarily brings with it a strategically dishonest public ideology because its very strategy is simulative and dissimulative: what is most characteristic of the bourgeois organization of trust relations is the creation of a political edifice that props-up merely an idea of trust, using privatized and therefore rarified social resources. The real production of real trust <em>has nothing to do with it. </em>In fact, the whole bourgeois organization and conception of trust seems almost expressly designed to excise the necessity and anxiety of having to build trust.</p>

<p>In other words, because the bourgeois organization of trust relations is chiefly a system for simulating trust and dissimulating its precariousness, it is especially damning for the overall social trust because it not only fails itself and denies others, it also requires and sustains public allegiance to its honor and continuation at all costs. After all, that is the bourgeois couple&rsquo;s original intention: to sustain a privatized &ldquo;trust&rdquo; at all costs, to hide from the insecurities that have always plagued humans everywhere, to pretend that fear has been abolished, at least until death do it part.  The truth is that people cannot know trust when fear and insecurity have merely been excluded and forgotten. Today, real trust can only be known when real fears and insecurities are so honestly recognized, shared, and accepted as a common problem and common responsibility. When this really truly occurs, the release from bourgeois fakery is so vertiginous and empowering that it cannot be mistaken. It is often named &ldquo;falling in love.&rdquo; Indeed, there is no reason to believe its uncommon and it is almost certainly the once-truly-lived kernel of truth within the dead husk of most bourgeois relationships.</p>

<p>We, on the other hand, do not seek to lock-in or lock-up the truth that together we have glimpsed, because for us, the truth we have shared is the hardest and rarest truth that can be shared: that there is nothing whatsoever to lock-in or lock-up. Recall that <em>to betray</em> means <em>to reveal</em> as much as it means <em>to deceive</em>. We do not betray each other because we neither hide nor reveal anything, but rather we produce shared truths that did not exist before of us. We are not therefore free of insecurities and hardly a day goes by that we do not tremble with some mundane everyday fear; we simply love each other but we truly love each other, and we trust each other <em>despite</em> that real love is a real cause for very real fears.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A thought on jealousy]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/14/a-thought-on-jealousy/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-14T15:10:04+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/14/a-thought-on-jealousy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When one person is jealous of another, that jealousy can be oppressive for the other, of course, but it can also be perversely comforting: Jealousy <em>is</em> flattering. And in the most dangerous cases, rather than balance each other, the oppressiveness and the comfort fuel each other. If the oppression of jealousy is intolerable and even debilitating, the comfort that is supplied by its flattering component can begin to feel all the more needed. This perverse need or desire for the flattering insecurity of the other can lead the coveted person to continue in behaviors that effectively encourage the covetousness under which they are oppressed, rather than simply confront the jealous person and defuse these obviously unhealthy dynamics. In fact, this dynamic is so dangerous because of its final step: this process tends independently to <em>create</em> and <em>drive</em> jealousy because the person who is oppressed but unable to speak about it makes the jealous person fear—this time <em>rightfully</em>—that the other is hiding something. And, to boot, because there is a flattering component in jealousy, the jealous person is unfortunately and unconsciously encouraged to maintain their jealousy insofar as they observe how the other takes solace in it, however perverse and subtle that solace may be.</p>

<p>By starting this illustration with the jealousy of a jealous person, it might seem that I have set out to describe the perverse effects of jealousy. Although this is true, it is far too easy as it simply flatters our prejudices against a naive conception of the jealous persona, and would merely encourage the scapegoating of individuals for what are inherently social and political problems. The most radical implication of the process I&rsquo;m describing has not so much to do with the effects of jealous people, but the conditions for the very possibility of jealousy itself. That is, if one person is sufficiently oppressed by even the perception of someone else&rsquo;s insecure covetousness, or if the projection of a jealous other is ever simply a defensive mechanism for pushing one&rsquo;s own fears and insecurities onto an other, then at work here could very well be a very base-level mechanism for the possibility and <em>production</em> of jealousy in the first place.</p>

<p>For what is most interesting about the process discussed above is that, strictly speaking, it does not require the original jealous person to be jealous. The jealous person might not even be jealous or their jealousy could be quite mild and they could be quite willing to change if confronted, but the process could still launch from understandably defensive strategies on the part of the other seeking only to deal with their own essential and perhaps even primordial insecurities. Still, this process would tend to produce real jealousy even if there was none to begin with.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A note on masculinity and self-expression]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/17/a-note-on-masculinity-and-self-expression/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-17T19:25:11+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/17/a-note-on-masculinity-and-self-expression</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One characteristically masculine technique of expression is to translate feelings of fear and insecurity into verbal and gestural forms of aggression and bids for power. In other words: not expression at all, but rather the opaque, instrumental action of concretely attempting to remove an irritation by subduing its real or imagined sources. Not depleting or reducing fear and insecurity but simply displacing them onto others. What the average man expects from women, and indeed requires from them, in order to exist with the fears and insecurities he knows no other way to deal with, is the woman&rsquo;s passive compliance with this masculinist formula of translating felt fears and insecurities into aggression, and many popular tropes about male-female romance only catalog the most traditional and well-known ways in which women have figured out how to cope with these strategic ruses of masculine dissimulation which are intended to pass for expression. Women who are no longer willing to shoulder all of this displaced insecurity and fear are, for obvious reasons, an extremely fearful threat to the traditional man. If such traditional men were simply backward, hopeless fools with whom it&rsquo;s not even worth bothering, then perhaps we could simply write them off as too far gone. Then those of us with radical interests would have no real reason to be too concerned with the difficulties these men face in coming to terms with the truth of feminism. But it is not so easy because it must be admitted that even we men who are absolutely committed to learning and understanding the nature of patriarchy and are actually committed to changing our practices in a way consistent with the liberation of all people, the truth is that we don&rsquo;t currently have alternative ways of dealing with the fears and insecurities we all suffer from. And it cannot be treated as a matter of heroism: &ldquo;I will just deal with it, I have no right to complain, because I&rsquo;m just a privileged man in a patriarchal society,&rdquo; without this, too, being itself a patriarchal and masculinist recourse.</p>

<p>In other words, those interested in a radical collective resistance against patriarchy have to develop practices that allow men to deal with their insecurities and fears in a way that does not revert to partaking in ultimately masculinist stances. An opposite strategy is to forego all masculinist techniques, to sort of submit or offer oneself unconditionally, to say &ldquo;here I am, relinquishing myself of the only techniques I know for dealing with my securities and fears, here I am, nothing but insecurities and fears, and, in my refusal to displace these fears and insecurities onto others but having no other techniques for dealing with them, I will simply show them and reveal them in honesty.&rdquo; The difficulty here, again, is that the emotional difficulties of such a horrific ordeal of revelation and self-flagellation typically fall onto the shoulders of those who care. Historically, of course, it is on women that the burden of such care labor typically falls, making this strategy of absolutely candid surrender likely to backfire. Another way it backfires is that this sort of practice is truly quite grotesque, monstrous; it is literally inhuman insofar as it is basically the act of relinquishing all of the characteristically human, that is to say dissimulative and instrumental techniques for being in the world and presenting ourselves in the world as subjects. Needless to say, this inhumanity, although perhaps commendable on some ultimate scale, is quite exactly the opposite of what is attractive to humans, and it&rsquo;s nearly impossible to actually live with. The point worth stressing is that alternatives to the dead-ends of masculine self-expression are not readily available; it&rsquo;s not clear that anyone knows how to resist and replace them in a way that does not take recourse to some sort of instrumentalism and exploitation at some level.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sensitivity is a scarce resource]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/01/05/sensitivity-a-scarce-resource/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-05T18:57:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/01/05/sensitivity-a-scarce-resource</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most people are sensitive in their relations with loved ones but insensitive to the far greater suffering of others. This is disastrous for the loved ones as well as humanity in general. The real challenge for loved ones must be to treat each other with loving <em>insensitivity</em>, a mutual respect so deep that it is impossible to silently indulge the other’s flaws and weaknesses. This is not only a truer and more mutually empowering path for the loved ones, but perhaps even more importantly, it reserves one’s limited resources of sensitivity for maintaining the highest possible degree of awareness and protest toward the rest of the world’s deepest and most urgent varieties of human suffering.</p>

<br><br><br><br><br><br>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
