<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: privilege | Justin Murphy]]></title>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/categories/privilege/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-03T23:11:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[j.murphy@soton.ac.uk]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On oppression and insurrection (1)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2015/05/12/oppression-insurrection-1/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-12T23:50:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2015/05/12/oppression-insurrection-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A diversity of inequalities will always make revolutionary politics difficult. Of course, many previous revolutionary projects tried to solve this problem by simply ignoring some types of inequality and prioritizing the equalization of certain, select inequalities. Clearly, in the most infamous revolutionary projects of the twentieth century, class or economic inequalities were typically prioritized over other types of inequality, such as those related to race and gender. This is one of the reasons why, today, the very idea of large-scale collective insurrection is widely and quite reasonably mistrusted.</p>

<p>As consciousness of race and gender oppression displaces the failed history of class-centric revolutionary projects, to even express interest in large-scale insurrection against inequality and domination <em>as such</em>—rather than framing one’s opposition in terms of specific vectors of oppression—is often seen as suspicious and sometimes explicitly accused of erasing differences between people. The result is that we are increasingly aware of diverse vectors of institutionalized oppression which increase our felt need to overthrow all of them, at the same time we have become deeply suspicious, to the point of preemptively dismissive, of anyone too passionate about overthrowing all of them. Precisely as a generalized insurrection appears more and more necessary, activists are less and less able to speak of, let alone believe in, the very idea.</p>

<p>My argument is that the diverse types of inequality we see today, the complicated distributions of privilege and oppression which characterize modernity, actually <em>increase our collective leverage</em> against the dominant institutions and the small elite which benefit from them, while rendering elite control increasingly brittle in comparison. The main problem is that the diversity which characterizes modern society poses extraordinary interpersonal challenges for which very, very few people have any training or patience, for the understandable reason that our identities today are precisely refractions of the very divisive institutions which dominate and oppress us all differentially.</p>

<p>The reason why almost all the revolutionary projects in history fail or end with terror is precisely because they have always tried to clean an open wound with a dirty hand, over-eager to fix some things but under-concerned with fixing others. Today, in our increasingly information-based existence in which it is possible to know any fact but nearly impossible to live, we have the opposite problem: we are so aware of the dirt on our hands that we don’t believe we can fundamentally heal this collective wound which masquerades as a society. It often seems that because people sincerely don’t want to hurt anybody else, nobody wants to even dream aloud about how one could exercise revolutionary agency in one’s own way, let alone possibly in conjunction with others’ autonomous agency at some point, somehow.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>I think that what we need are methods for identifying rigorously the emancipatory pathways available to different people in different situations at different times. It would seem to me that any vision for the possibility of social revolution in a society rife with diverse divisions and hierarchies would need to be composed of heterogenous battle maps for heterogenous situations. These maps should and must be made by different folks for different purposes and there does not need to be any overarching process of verification or legitimation for us to nonetheless wish, hope, and try to make them connect up to whatever degree that becomes possible. The mistake of previous revolutions has been to ask certain groups to wait for other groups; we can affirm everyone’s equal right to immediately do whatever they think most important, and we affirm our desires to attune ourselves to what others want to do, whether we understand it or not, then we can also affirm the dream of a massive and collective abolition of inequality and domination as such, without ever “prioritizing” anyone over anyone else.</p>

<p>What follows in this manuscript might be more immediately useful to those who already have certain privileges and resources which I’m lucky enough to have. I don’t know, one doesn’t know how limited is one’s perspective until one formulates it, until one takes its measure. That is probably an ineluctable condition of anyone thinking or writing anything in the contribution to collective social change. Still, I don’t know, I still believe in the possibility of individuals and groups contributing to the dream and, ultimately, the plan for concretely ushering in an era of real justice and real equality in this lifetime. I believe in at least trying to think through a process whereby diverse groups could aggregate effectively but justly into a massive insurrectionary force <em>toward</em> universal justice, understanding that a truly universal justice would have to be one that is absolutely consistent with all particular identities and desires.</p>

<p>To begin conceptually delimiting a philosophy of intersectional battle maps, of potentially infinite and absolutely autonomous units but facing only the <em>direction</em> of universal, insurrectional unity. We might begin by hypothesizing that wherever tactical opportunities open up in such a fashion that only a relatively small group of people are able to exploit them, that specific small group is a revolutionary <em>avant-garde</em> <em>of that specific front,</em> not by rights or necessity but by chance. No vanguard of “the revolution” or “the movement,” just one of many revolutionary vanguards growing from the logic that the emancipatory opportunities available today are extremely diverse and separated, and contingent on the different positions occupied by different individuals distributed across our hierarchical and divided societies.</p>

<p>And it is no criticism of the individuals first possessed of certain revolutionary perturbations that they are merely “privileged” or “bourgeois” as if that disqualifies them from the resistance. It is a conservative, bourgeois ideology to critique revolutionaries for having a bourgeois background, for not only is it a patently _ad hominem_ argument, it’s effect is to disqualify a faction of society which is sometimes the only faction with the material resources (time, education, technology, etc.), to undertake certain types of activity in certain times or places. Just as there will be crucial types of activity which, I imagine, could only be done by the less privileged. If someone is truly revolutionary, their only function is to spread freedom through contagion from <em>wherever they find themselves</em>, to embody a freedom whose specific nature and function is to proliferate and multiply itself through a process I’ve modeled elsewhere with respect to the political vanguard and according to which the avant-garde will expand just as well.
The simple reason why the avant-garde as well as the vanguard have been critical concepts in art and politics is not because there need to be leaders, as in the disastrously erroneous doctrines of someone like Lenin. The limited quantity of representatives in any emergent avant-garde or vanguard is simply a function of the evolutionary fact that everything has to start somewhere, with some minor perturbation in the system.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>In some sense this is good, because perhaps it means the pendulum has swung away from authoritarian tendencies, and perhaps it means that the next massive revolution to shake the world will be constitutionally incapable of lapsing into authoritarian terror. But in another sense, it is clearly a peculiar pathology for an allergy to authoritarianism to become a kind of authoritarian norm precluding the possibility of a generalized explosion of diverse freedoms.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA['Stand your ground' laws reinforce white supremacy in the streets and patriarchy in the home]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2015/02/05/new-evidence-stand-your-ground/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-05T09:02:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2015/02/05/new-evidence-stand-your-ground</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Because there are still many people who continue to doubt systematic racial and gender bias in law enforcement, I have been working on some new statistical tests of these claims. Earlier today I released <a href="http://figshare.com/articles/A_Statistical_Analysis_of_Racism_and_Sexism_in_Stand_Your_Ground_Cases_in_Florida_2006_2013/1301532">new statistical evidence of racism and sexism in the enforcement of &ldquo;stand your ground&rdquo; (SYG) laws</a>, using a sample of cases from Florida in the period from 2006 to 2013. A detailed explanation of the data, methods, and findings (including fully reproducible data and code) can be found in the full working paper linked above.</p>

<p>Below, I summarize:</p>

<ul>
<li>The two key findings</li>
<li>What if Trayvon Martin had been white? What if Marissa Alexander had been male?</li>
<li>What is new about these findings and why they matter</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<h3>The two key findings</h3>

<p>1) The probability of conviction for a white defendant against a white victim in a typical case is fairly high at around 90% but with a large margin of error, whereas <strong>the probability of conviction for a black defendant against a white victim approaches 100%, even after controlling for more than 10 different objective factors related to the circumstances of the incident.</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://figshare.com/articles/Expected_Probability_of_Conviction_by_Race_of_Victim_and_Defendant_in_Stand_Your_Ground_Cases_Florida_2006_2013_/1301534"><img src="http://previews.figshare.com/1880691/860/p_01.png" height="400" width="500" alt="Expected Probability of Conviction by Race of Victim and Defendant in &quot;Stand Your Ground&quot; Cases (Florida, 2006-2013)" /></a></p>

<p>2) The probability of conviction for a male defendant in a typical domestic case is found to be about 40%, but <strong>for a female defendant in an otherwise objectively equivalent case the probability of conviction increases dramatically to 80%</strong>.</p>

<p><a href="http://figshare.com/articles/Expected_Probability_of_Conviction_by_Gender_of_Defendant_in_Domestic_and_Non_Domestic_Stand_Your_Ground_Cases_in_Florida/1301535"><img src="http://previews.figshare.com/1880692/860/p_01.png" height="400" width="500" alt="Expected Probability of Conviction by Gender of Defendant in Domestic and Non-Domestic &quot;Stand Your Ground&quot; Cases (Florida, 2006-2013)" /></a></p>

<h3>What these models teach us about recent cases</h3>

<p>1) The probability George Zimmerman was going to be found guilty of murdering unarmed black teenager Trayvon Martin in 2012 was marginally greater than 50% but would have been about 98% if Trayvon Martin had been white.</p>

<p>2) Black female Marissa Alexander who fired a physically innocuous warning shot to deter her husband in 2010 faced a probability of conviction marginally greater than 50%, but the probability of conviction for a male defendant in an otherwise objectively equivalent situation would have been around only 12%.</p>

<h3>What is new about these findings and why they matter</h3>

<p>1) The only previous statistical analysis of racial bias in the enforcement of stand your grown laws at the level of individual cases concluded that there has been no racial bias. Conservative gun advocate John Lott analyzed the same data I analyzed and submitted his analysis as testimony to the US Senate Judiciary Committee. As I explain in the paper, his statistical modelswere very superficially reported and deeply flawed. Thus, <strong>my findings overturn the last most influential study which, I believe, incorrectly informed US policymakers.</strong></p>

<p>2) This analysis controls for a very large number of contextual factors which are frequently invoked to dismiss claims of racism and sexism. In other words, if anyone ever says the legal system is not racist or sexist but people of color and/or women are simply more likely to do/be some other thing which rightfully earns them convictions and just happens to be correlated with race or gender, <strong>my study provides evidence of racism and sexism in SYG enforcement even <em>after</em> subtracting out any effect which might come from race or gender correlating with a long list of common conservative excuses</strong>: whether the victim initiates, whether the defendant can retreat, whether the defendant pursues, whether the defendant has a gun, whether the incident takes place on the defendant’s property, whether the victim dies, age of victim and defendant, whether there is physical evidence, whether there is a witness, and whether the victim is committing a crime.</p>

<p><a href="http://figshare.com/articles/A_Statistical_Analysis_of_Racism_and_Sexism_in_Stand_Your_Ground_Cases_in_Florida_2006_2013/1301532"><strong>Murphy, Justin (2015): A Statistical Analysis of Racism and Sexism in &ldquo;Stand Your Ground&rdquo; Cases in Florida, 2006-2013.
http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.1301532</strong></a></p>

<br><br><br><br><br><br>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reactionary law and bourgeois desire]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/19/reactionary-law-and-bourgeois-desire/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-19T02:06:45+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/19/reactionary-law-and-bourgeois-desire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An unfortunate tendency of exceptionally repressive laws and draconian sentences is that, in middle-class eyes, they tend to justify themselves: to bourgeois stiffs, it begins to seem as if anyone who would risk such harsh punishments <em>must be</em> so crazy and dangerous that it feels appropriate and reassuring to be protected by such a vicious legal machine. Indeed, the self-justifying effect of a draconian legal system increases as punishments get more severe for less and less significant behaviors. As the punishments become larger and the crimes smaller, even more inclined is the average person to wonder with a mix of fear and envy why anyone would insist on actions that seem to them so trivial given such great costs.</p>

<p>Knowing already that countless people are jailed for years on simple, non-violent drug charges, we begin to read more and more absurd headlines: a black homeless woman is given a 12-year prison sentence for sending her son to a public school with an incorrect home address; even a white man is given a 2-year prison sentence <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_DeChristopher">for outbidding oil companies in a big land auction</a> and another white man is sentenced <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weev">three years in prison for accessing a publicly available website</a> simply because it wasn&rsquo;t intended for public view. In response to increasingly absurd and vicious applications of the law, the average fish-blooded citizen tends to think only that anyone who still insists on such unorthodox exercises of freedom must <em>lack all sense of proportion</em>. And this frightens them half to death, for good reason. Of course, in some sense, this view is technically correct (to maintain any integrity in a society such as ours requires a deep refusal of its ratios) but what is critical to grasp is that to the average and spineless citizen, those who display any kind of autonomy inconsistent with the police order <em>truly</em> appear <em>that</em> dangerous. And perhaps they really are. Not only because such behavior lacks the proportions of everyday middle-class order and therefore <em>generally</em> threatens it; because middle-class comforts and privileges could and would be re-distributed if it were not for a firm legal system, they are<em> especially</em> threatened when increasingly decent people are punished with increasing absurdity for breaking increasingly stupid laws for engaging in fairly reasonable actions. When there are individuals who insist on doing what they want despite the risk of increasingly insane legal punishment, the average citizen who marginally benefits from this legal system will only prefer more laws, more police, and more prisons.</p>

<p>It will never cease to astound us how impoverished the bottom ranks of the relatively privileged groups (in particular, white people, male-gendered people) can become without rebelling. But the present thesis might solve some portion of this classic puzzle. No matter how obvious it is that the contemporary political system has been destroying, and will continue destroying, even these historically privileged groups, they are paralyzed from resisting because they are wholly indebted to precisely this system and its tendencies of exclusion and oppression for whatever material and psychological possessions they still possess. The reason that rebellion is perhaps impossible for such souls, the reason they can see no other option than to double-down on their reactionary wagers, is because every advancement of capitalist exclusion and oppression is simply the advancement of what they once unconsciously but nonetheless gleefully assumed as the core of their beliefs and behaviors. Their refusal to rebel is suicide, but rebellion too would be suicide. Whichever path they choose, may they only choose quickly!<em> </em> 
Finally, this same thesis which helps us understand absurdly aggressive legal reaction also sheds light on why other types of crime are surprisingly under-punished relative to what we would expect. For example, as the recent and now notorious Steubenville rape case attests, young men who engage in brutal sexual violence against women often receive significantly shorter prison sentences than many non-violent, drug offenders. For the reasons already articulated, it is easy to see why property-related crimes are so grossly over-punished while crimes such as rape are relatively under-punished: crimes even vaguely related to property threaten relatively powerful (but increasingly fearful) groups invested in the status quo, while sexual violence against women—as one of the most basic substructures underwriting our political system built on domination—is the most basic kind of activity that constitutes the power of these relatively privileged but increasingly fearful groups invested in the status quo. From this perspective, it is not at all surprising that the former set of crimes is increasingly punished while the latter is punished less and less.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A note on masculinity and self-expression]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/17/a-note-on-masculinity-and-self-expression/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-17T19:25:11+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/17/a-note-on-masculinity-and-self-expression</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One characteristically masculine technique of expression is to translate feelings of fear and insecurity into verbal and gestural forms of aggression and bids for power. In other words: not expression at all, but rather the opaque, instrumental action of concretely attempting to remove an irritation by subduing its real or imagined sources. Not depleting or reducing fear and insecurity but simply displacing them onto others. What the average man expects from women, and indeed requires from them, in order to exist with the fears and insecurities he knows no other way to deal with, is the woman&rsquo;s passive compliance with this masculinist formula of translating felt fears and insecurities into aggression, and many popular tropes about male-female romance only catalog the most traditional and well-known ways in which women have figured out how to cope with these strategic ruses of masculine dissimulation which are intended to pass for expression. Women who are no longer willing to shoulder all of this displaced insecurity and fear are, for obvious reasons, an extremely fearful threat to the traditional man. If such traditional men were simply backward, hopeless fools with whom it&rsquo;s not even worth bothering, then perhaps we could simply write them off as too far gone. Then those of us with radical interests would have no real reason to be too concerned with the difficulties these men face in coming to terms with the truth of feminism. But it is not so easy because it must be admitted that even we men who are absolutely committed to learning and understanding the nature of patriarchy and are actually committed to changing our practices in a way consistent with the liberation of all people, the truth is that we don&rsquo;t currently have alternative ways of dealing with the fears and insecurities we all suffer from. And it cannot be treated as a matter of heroism: &ldquo;I will just deal with it, I have no right to complain, because I&rsquo;m just a privileged man in a patriarchal society,&rdquo; without this, too, being itself a patriarchal and masculinist recourse.</p>

<p>In other words, those interested in a radical collective resistance against patriarchy have to develop practices that allow men to deal with their insecurities and fears in a way that does not revert to partaking in ultimately masculinist stances. An opposite strategy is to forego all masculinist techniques, to sort of submit or offer oneself unconditionally, to say &ldquo;here I am, relinquishing myself of the only techniques I know for dealing with my securities and fears, here I am, nothing but insecurities and fears, and, in my refusal to displace these fears and insecurities onto others but having no other techniques for dealing with them, I will simply show them and reveal them in honesty.&rdquo; The difficulty here, again, is that the emotional difficulties of such a horrific ordeal of revelation and self-flagellation typically fall onto the shoulders of those who care. Historically, of course, it is on women that the burden of such care labor typically falls, making this strategy of absolutely candid surrender likely to backfire. Another way it backfires is that this sort of practice is truly quite grotesque, monstrous; it is literally inhuman insofar as it is basically the act of relinquishing all of the characteristically human, that is to say dissimulative and instrumental techniques for being in the world and presenting ourselves in the world as subjects. Needless to say, this inhumanity, although perhaps commendable on some ultimate scale, is quite exactly the opposite of what is attractive to humans, and it&rsquo;s nearly impossible to actually live with. The point worth stressing is that alternatives to the dead-ends of masculine self-expression are not readily available; it&rsquo;s not clear that anyone knows how to resist and replace them in a way that does not take recourse to some sort of instrumentalism and exploitation at some level.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The vertigo of social mobility]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/16/400-the-vertigo-of-social-mobility/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-16T18:10:32+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/16/400-the-vertigo-of-social-mobility</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Institutions lure you by flattering you, in a world where it is nearly impossible to find recognition outside of them; you begin to see yourself only in institutions that pre-exist you and over which you exercise no influence. If this is perfectly internalized, then you get typical neuroses, mid-life crises, etc. Alternatively, if it&rsquo;s not perfectly internalized, then you get perpetual, mini crises up front; you perpetually realize you&rsquo;re over-worked and over-working on things that are somehow sterilized in advance so as to make sure you cannot exercise freedom over them and you also realize that no matter how hard you work you will not overcome this impotence. The mythology of hard work is, for this reason, indispensable for the status quo; it&rsquo;s one of the only things that keeps people from realizing that they simply can&rsquo;t win, that nobody can win like that.</p>

<p>Furthermore, growing dependent on such an institution for the most essential and elemental psychological needs is a most deadly vulnerability because, when one steps back from the institution for one&rsquo;s own freedom, to the exact degree one is accustomed to the flattery of that institution, one will feel stupid and worthless and suffer all kinds of the most pathetic problems and embarrassments in trying to step back. This is why the businessman in mid-life crisis is one of the most pathetic figures. However, every downturn of self-esteem that comes from such a precarious and self-betraying identification with an institution, tends to produce an upturn in at least one thing: economic consumption. For, the one thing the institutions will give you is money. And they&rsquo;ll give it to you precisely to the degree you&rsquo;re capable of doing something intense outside of an institution; nothing gets a higher price than that and intellectual history is replete with examples. When the life of the mind faulters and there is money in the bank, an almost automatic transference of energy takes place in which the mind fixates on some new thing to buy. Most important in this respect are upper-class goods such as nice clothing and nice housing. &ldquo;Why am I so stressed and neurotic?&rdquo; they ask themselves. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s because I don&rsquo;t have the proper materials for such an important life.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Because money is the only thing the institutions ultimately offer you, there is an overwhelming tendency to spend it upwards so to speak&mdash;so as to alleviate the stresses incurred in earning it. This point is perhaps banal, but the less observed point here is not just the material compensation of purchased pleasures for working stress; it&rsquo;s that the things purchased actually come to convince people of the legitimacy of the social distribution of resources. &ldquo;I need a nice sunny loft apartment all to myself because I need to focus and that&rsquo;s when I&rsquo;m most creative, because I am an academic.&rdquo; In fact, the exact opposite is the truth: I need a nice sunny loft apartment precisely because I&rsquo;m not an academic, so that in trying to be one for money I get so stressed and distracted I can&rsquo;t even do it how most people live, so I have to spend this money on a new apartment, etc. Then, lo and behold, all of the material and psychological vertigo of upward mobility comes along. That vertigo is real, it is the <em>real movement</em> as the Marxists like to say, of being distributed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
