<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></title>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-15T17:26:12-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[There are more than enough hours in the day]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/09/15/there-are-more-than-enough-hours-in-the-day/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-15T16:46:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/09/15/there-are-more-than-enough-hours-in-the-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The popular refrain that &ldquo;there aren&rsquo;t enough hours in the day&rdquo; is an interesting departure from the long and storied political and rhetorical battle to <em>objectively</em> decrease the hours of the working day. It is an extraordinary gauge of our political pacification that when so many people have such a hard time meeting a pervasive social and economic expectation, we would sooner <em>ask for an extension</em> of the expectation than its abolition.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ego and revolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/08/31/ego-and-revolution/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-31T20:42:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/08/31/ego-and-revolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My ego often wrestles with itself: Obviously I want to avoid arrogance and self absorption and selfishness, but the project of revolution almost presupposes delusions of grandeur and extraordinary self-confidence (if only a confidence in the collectives of which one is a constituent). Capitalist individualism is highly egoistic but ironically it keeps egos small and frail under a herd mentality inclusive of exploitation and alienation. I would much prefer the opposite contradiction of wildly inflated egos demanding and creating revolutionary egalitarianism. Indeed, in such a truly egoistic society such as ours, a powerful and disruptive political project to truly force egalitarian movement might require not the altruistic ethos of shrunken egos but a proliferation of individuals sufficiently egoistic to see themselves as truly and immediately capable of changing the world.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The hatred of freedom]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/08/31/the-hatred-of-freedom/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-31T20:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/08/31/the-hatred-of-freedom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The truth is that most people do not want other people to flourish. We all support a general idea of everyone being freer but we tend to feel threatened whenever anyone <em>in particular</em> meets with an increase of freedom. Not long after, we begin to hate them for it if we are not welcome or able to enjoy in the proceeds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Resentment and vegetarianism]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/06/26/resentment-and-eating-animals/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-26T22:29:16-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/06/26/resentment-and-eating-animals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People only eat meat because their repressed rage makes them bloodthirsty. All forms of bloodthirst are driven by resentment and revenge; this is the only conceivable reason why smart and good-natured people insist on eating meat. Everyone is so oppressed by social institutions but unable to kill any of the <em>humans</em> responsible for those institutions, that the half-hearted laments of unapologetic animal-eaters often reduce to: “I must reserve at least this one right to exercise my insatiable need to <em>take life</em> for  myself.” I think this is why after great ventings of repressed rage, I find it impossible to eat the flesh of an animal. In such instances, one is free of the resentment which drives such a vicious appetite.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A mass media theory of the surveillance state]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/06/16/a-mass-media-theory-of-the-surveillance-state/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-16T14:57:30-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/06/16/a-mass-media-theory-of-the-surveillance-state</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://twitter.com/sarahljaffe/status/344555375170842624">Sarah Jaffe</a> asks for a political economy of the surveillance state. I felt especially behooved to send her something not just because I&rsquo;m a young academic roughly in political economy but also because, as one of thousands of young adults in the U.S. who were radicalized in through Occupy Wall Street—I strongly identify with independent intellectuals like Sarah and the class war of which she writes. I believe, contrary to many activists and radicals, that the tools of academic political economy can be extremely powerful in the struggle for truth and justice in the social war. So I really wanted to give Sarah a good link and say, &ldquo;Here you go, sure it&rsquo;s bourgeois but look this really can help us understand what&rsquo;s going on&hellip;&rdquo;</p>

<p>Surveying the political economy blogosphere, however, I&rsquo;m hard pressed to find anything worth sending her. Tyler Cowen <a href="http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2013/06/a-simple-public-choice-theory-of-universal-surveillance.html?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%253A+marginalrevolution%252Ffeed+%2528Marginal+Revolution%2529&amp;utm_content=Google+Reader">takes a stab</a>, which Kindred Winecoff <a href="http://ipeatunc.blogspot.com/2013/06/tree-dont-care-what-little-bird-sings.html">finds unconvincing</a>. Winecoff, though, is admittedly unable to do much better, offering only a smattering of thoughts and links. A little discussion on <a href="http://crookedtimber.org/2013/06/13/insubordination-and-the-surveillance-state/">Crooked Timber</a>, a very interesting and link-rich <a href="http://www.cnas.org/blogs/abumuqawama/2013/06/through-murky-prism.html">story from Adam Elkus</a>, but no especially compelling model.</p>

<p><strong>I&rsquo;d like to offer a model of the US surveillance state as a natural outgrowth of any militarized democracy with a corporate mass media. </strong>I&rsquo;ll summarize the argument succinctly up front, and develop an informal model below.</p>

<p><strong>Abstract:</strong></p>

<p>Basically, in an ideally functioning democracy, anti-colonial terrorism is an effective check on colonial tendencies of democratic states. In an ideally functioning democracy with a healthy communication/information environment, 9-11 would have elicited a massive domestic uproar against the US militarism which incited 9-11, that militarism abroad would have been withdrawn, and terrorism would have stopped.</p>

<p>When a capitalist democracy is overrun with rampant inequality and the media are captured by wealthy elites, terrorism does not produce a check against colonialism because the wealthy have incentives to stifle the message attached to anti-colonial terrorism. This leads to a bad equilibrium of colonial terror abroad and retaliatory terror at home. At the same time, wealthy elites who already have a monopoly on information production also already have economies of scale in information monitoring and surveillance. Because the system is increasingly suboptimal for everyone but the wealthy of the colonial regime, and because it is increasingly leveraged on distorted information, it is therefore increasingly <em>vulnerable</em> to the very nature of information <em>anywhere</em>.</p>

<p>The communication/information of domestic citizens becomes as threatening to the elite as terrorism from abroad, because the increasingly suboptimal system was built on a fundamentally manipulative basis of a corporate-captured media culture. Thus, once the system crosses some threshold of suboptimality, a surveillance state is rapidly and easily turned on populations at home and abroad—the bureacratic and technological resources easily spillover and an already pacified population even happily accepts it.</p>

<h2>1. A Baseline Model of Colonialism and Anti-Colonial Terrorism with Democratic Communication</h2>

<p>Consider an ideally functioning liberal democracy. There is a market economy with winners and losers but robust democratic institutions empower the people to tax and regulate business as they please. Assume only two things about this democracy:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>As per standard models of taxation/redistribution in democracies, taxation and redistribution increase as inequality increases (Meltzer and Richards 1981).<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p></li>
<li><p>Assume that there are strong policies which prevent the concentration of commercial media and actively promote a diversity of grassroots, community-driven media agendas. In other words, assume the intution most of us have when we imagine what media would look like in an ideal democracy, i.e. non-massified, diversified media which questions and criticizes everything from multiple angles. This assumption elides many questions (but that&rsquo;s the privilege of blog posts, right?)</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Now, militaries of democracies are driven by what Yagil Levy calls <a href="http://cmp.sagepub.com/content/27/4/386.abstract">a force/casualty tradeoff:</a> Voters punish politicians when soldiers on the home team die, but since voters don&rsquo;t punish politicians for killing foreign civilians, democratic pressure actually encourages militaries to use excessive lethal force overseas (killing civilians) in order to prevent their own soldiers from dying. Assume this is true of our hypothetical liberal democracy.</p>

<p>In response foreigners attack civilians in the liberal democracy precisely in order to raise the costs of the democracy&rsquo;s violence abroad beyond what is politically sustainable in the democracy. There&rsquo;s an excellent book by <a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=10&amp;cad=rja&amp;ved=0CF0QFjAJ&amp;url=http%253A%252F%252Fbooks.google.com%252Fbooks%252Fabout%252FWinning_hearts_and_minds.html%253Fid%253DzvMLAQAAMAAJ&amp;ei=I1u7UZeEH-Lo0gGWl4HADg&amp;usg=AFQjCNE_2mo-CgGxjJ_pQerUwM3BhafstQ&amp;sig2=jI0zNa2fZ6sr8wcF-R7HBw&amp;bvm=bv.47883778,d.dmQ">Susan Carruthers (1995)</a> which provides ample evidence that, from Mau Mau to Malaysia to Cyprus, anti-colonial terrorism against the British colonial government was based on the wager that British citizens would be so horrified that they would pressure their government to withdraw. Interestingly, Carruthers traces how this strategy largely worked, as British media reports of anti-colonial terrorism turned British citizens sour towards colonialism.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> Most important for the moment, however, is the acknowledgement that this logic of political terrorism requires that citizens in the liberal democracy truly learn about the reality of the protesting terrorists. The British media in the 1950s and 1960s roughly meets the assumption laid out above&mdash;definitely some concentration and cronyism but still lots of freewheeling muckraking and radical leftist newspapers with politically significant audiences.</p>

<p>So, in a functioning democracy with relative equality and a relatively healthy media environment, terrorism in protest of a democracy&rsquo;s violence abroad makes citizens in the democracy update their estimation of their military&rsquo;s violence abroad and support declines for the military&rsquo;s violence.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> The military is forced to withdraw from its violent adventures, terrorism stops, and there is neither the need nor the political possibility of a surveillance state.</p>

<h2>2. Colonialism and Anti-Colonial Terrorism with Corporate Mass Media</h2>

<p>Now, let&rsquo;s imagine a rise in inequality without a corresponding rise in taxation/redistribution. I don&rsquo;t think I need to post a graph—we all know indeed that since the 1950s most of the US income gains have gone to the rich, and along the way we&rsquo;ve ended up with only neoliberal cutbacks to redistributive spending. In other words, assume that the Meltzer and Richards expectations no longer hold.</p>

<p>Runaway inequality would have two really important implications for understanding where the surveillance state has come from and how it was possible:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>If inequality rises and democratic redistribution does not occur to level the political playing field, here&rsquo;s a nice political economy model showing with evidence why and how <a href="https://0ec87679-a-62cb3a1a-s-sites.googlegroups.com/site/mariapetrovaphd/inequality%2520media.pdf?attachauth=ANoY7coFxOvpnB1LkvoeH4s47vGIT7Q8baK6IVmtXBnjoUVXUQ97HyVYtGsXxDc3fBhYT4Ve5bTn8Tm-Nar1ekON48VEgQec6qqChEAILiqgcJSHSXoUtOOrWfUmlwSm2nwChy74n1-2apdOtcyZfHyyRlwWYaM3XKe-sc42RXnAMYQ2vXvHPgkLpp4L5CkLODy1AQlKNa0Wax0HcunE64rJqKArAjCZ8nQpckC1RZOQcKw6MyhMYG4%253D&amp;attredirects=0">the media will be captured by the rich</a> (Petrova 2008).<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup></p></li>
<li><p>Media captured by the rich is far less likely to report the ways in which the US military is to blame for terrorism, and far more likely to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rally_'round_the_flag_effect">rally-around-the-flag</a>. First, we know very well that the media tend to index their reporting to what the government says <a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1460-2466.2006.00296.x/abstract?deniedAccessCustomisedMessage=&amp;userIsAuthenticated=false">(one especially apropos example of this finding is Bennett, Lawrence, and Livingston 2006)</a>. If this is a tendency of media in general, it should be more true of media captured by the rich because for obvious reasons the economic interests of elite media actors would have a greater status-quo bias (they would be highly averse to anything that could engender significant mass-public re-evaluations of the status quo). There is ample evidence for this claim in the observation that an outlet such as FOX news, most closely aligned with the wealthiest patrons such as the Koch Brothers, will rally-around-the-flag and defend the military more rabidly than any of the other outlets.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The resulting expectation at this point in our model is that once runaway inequality leads to media capture (i.e. corporate mass media), the <strong>message</strong> of retaliatory political terrorism hardly gets through as elite media rally-around-the-flag. Terrorists <a href="http://www.nbcnews.com/id/4686034/ns/world_news-hunt_for_al_qaida/t/timeline-al-qaida-statements/">repeatedly and explicity</a> <a href="http://www.nydailynews.com/news/crime/boston-bomb-suspect-left-confession-boat-report-article-1.1345642">explain and justify</a> their attacks on US citizens as the only option available to them in discouraging the continued murder of their people by the US military. The problem is that now there is no sufficiently powerful media company with any incentives to really highlight the US government&rsquo;s share of the blame and to editorialize in that direction as vociferously as Great Britain&rsquo;s <em>Daily Worker</em> in the 1950s.<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup></p>

<p>Of course rallying-around-the-flag has always occurred in the media, but in non-captured, democratic media the knee-jerk patriotism is only one voice among many. After runaway inequality, it&rsquo;s basically the only voice in the media, which is what we have in the U.S. today. Because the actual message terrorists attach to their terrorism does not get through, it no longer exerts the &ldquo;error-correction&rdquo; effects it exerted in our baseline model; it no longer alters the subjective cost-benefit analysis of the mass democratic public, and therefore there is no negative feedback, no countervailing electoral pressure against the collateral murder of foreign civilians. The democratic citizens unwittingly incentivize the goverment to recklessly kill foreign civilians and then, when they are attacked by suicide bombers in response, the elite media deprives them of the most important point and leads them to demand more war.</p>

<h2>3. The Surveillance State is a Spillover of Corporate Mass Media</h2>

<p>I would argue that the surveillance state is simply a technological and bureaucratic <a href="http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/2705338?uid=3739864&amp;uid=2&amp;uid=4&amp;uid=3739256&amp;sid=21102408438227">spillover</a> of a militarized democracy with a corporate mass media system. Once a state arrives in the bad equilibrium described above—where &ldquo;democratic&rdquo; electoral pressures and a perverse media environment create an infinite loop of militarized terrorism abroad and retaliatory terrorism at home—the stability of the system is highly <em>vulernable</em> to information precisely because it&rsquo;s built on distortion of the truth. Because this system is increasingly suboptimal for most people in the country and outside of it, true information is increasingly threatening to the status quo.</p>

<p>At the same time this system is highly leveraged on the distortion of information, advantages in the production/dissemination of information also give media elites extraordinary advantage in the surveillance and reconnaisance of information. If you need to be convinced of the complementarity between producing and monitoring information, recall that a significant portion of CIA activities, especially earlier in its history, are also organized around <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morale_Operations_Branch">producing</a> information and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CIA_influence_on_public_opinion">influencing public opinion</a> as much as collecting and monitoring it. The government contractor Booz Allen Hamilton, (former) home of the most recent NSA whistleblower Edward Snowden, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Booz_Allen_Hamilton%23Notable_members_and_alumni">has ties</a> to British Telecommunications PLC, VH1 and CMT television networks, more than one connection to MTV Networks, publisher McGraw-Hill, and individuals who came directly from the information-production side of the CIA. For instance, Booz Allen Hamilton was once the private-sector home of Miles Copeland, a figure who was instrumental in the sabotage of Mossadegh in Iran, an operation which involved elaborate propaganda campaigns, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1953_Iranian_coup_d'%25C3%25A9tat%23Role_of_BBC.27s_Persian_service">manipulation</a> of the Persian media, and some <a href="http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F10F15F73F5C177B93C4A91783D85F408585F9">ideological assistance</a> at home. One cannot run a world-class surveillance operation without some experience in controlling the flow of public information in general, and one cannot get away with it unless one has already produced a pacifying public culture for some time.</p>

<p>Thus, lo and behold, at exactly the same time as true information is increasingly threatening to the system, the elites who have produced the distortions of that system will, and must, easily and naturally turn their resources towards monitoring as many people as possible. The capture and development of corporate mass media produces the informational distortions which engender a cycle of terror abroad and at home. Because this is an inherently suboptimal system which citizens would overthrow if they understood it, it suddenly requires a surveillance system to monitor the possibility of any threats whatsoever domestic or abroad. Then once the actual construction of a surveillance state is triggered, it is only possible on the back of an already developed and elite-controlled mass media—because of the bureaucratic and technological spillovers but also from the already pacified population it has produced.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Richard, Scott F, and Allan H Meltzer. 1981. “A Rational Theory of the Size of Government.” Journal of Political Economy (May 26): 1–15. As the mean income outpaces the income of the median voter, we should find taxation/redistribution increasing because that median voter will prefer governments who tax the rich and redistribute their money. In turn, an ideally functioning representative democracy almost by definition means that the only politician who can win an election is the politician who satisfies the median voter. Thus, in a democracy, as inequality increases, we should find governments taxing and redistributing.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Note also that suicide bombings are more likely against liberal democracies.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Note that it makes no difference whether the democratic citizens drop their support of the military because they empathetically learn about the suffering which drives the protesting terrorists, or out of self-interest (the military&rsquo;s adventure abroad isn&rsquo;t worth the risk of being bombed in the subway).<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Petrova looks in particular at media freedom, i.e. censorship and formal repression, but her model is also equally suggestive of the expectation that rising inequality would allow the rich to unduly influence what the media do and do not say without necessarily buying its formal repression. The difficulty is that there&rsquo;s good data on good old fashioned repression, not so many datasets on informal influence by the rich.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>It is well known that bin Laden launched concerted public messaging campaigns urging the US to leave the Middle East or else there would be attacks against US civilians. I&rsquo;m not aware of research on this in particular, but I think we can be pretty sure these public declarations were not well covered by US media outlets. Needless to say, in the aftermath of 9-11, the knee-jerk patriotism and [rally-around-the-flag][13] effects in the media not only crowded-out but positively punished the empathetic/self-critical line. Remember when Ward Churchill was [absolutely destroyed by the mainstream media][14] for suggesting that 9-11 was like &ldquo;chickens coming home to roost&rdquo;? Agree or disagree with Churchill, the point here is that when there are only a few disproportionately powerful media outlets—and for probably a few other more nuanced reasons—the rally-around-the-flag tendencies are amplified and choke off the very possibility of citizens critically evaluating and updating their assessments of their military&rsquo;s actions abroad.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Civil war and the square of ethnic fractionalization]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/05/22/civil-war-and-the-square-of-ethnic-fractionalization-4/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-22T12:06:22-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/05/22/civil-war-and-the-square-of-ethnic-fractionalization-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Steve Saideman wonders if the relationship between ethnic fractionalization and civil war is curvilinear, where increasing fractionalization increases the probability of civil war up to a certain point but then increasing fractionalization decreases the probability of civil war. Since I have my nose in this data right now, I&rsquo;ve given this conjecture a quick probe. I find no evidence <em>prima facie</em>.</p>

<p>Below is a replication of Sambanis 2004 where I simply add the square of ethnic fractionalization. If Steve&rsquo;s conjecture were true, we&rsquo;d expect <em>ef1</em> to be positive, <em>ef1sq</em> to be negative, and both of them to be significant. They are signed as expected but not significant given the controls recommended by Sambanis. I then try alternative codings of civil war and a simple equation with no controls. If Steve&rsquo;s conjecture is true, it&rsquo;s not obvious.</p>

<p>Everything below is reproducible in R-just download the replication data, easy to find with a quick search, and set your working directory to where the data is.</p>

<h2>Data</h2>

<p><code> r Get data and create the squared variable
</code>
library(foreign)
sambanis &lt;&ndash; read.dta(&ldquo;SambanisJCR2004_replicationdataset.dta&rdquo;)
sambanis$ef1sq &lt;&ndash; sambanis$ef1 * sambanis$ef1</p>

<p><code>
</code>
<code> r Replicate Sambanis 2004 (Table 6 in paper, column 8, pp.845)
</code>model &lt;&ndash; glm(warstnsb  gdpl1 + grol1 + inst3l1 + anoc2l1 + oil2l1 + ef1 + lpopnsl1 +</p>

<pre><code>    mtnl1 + warnsl1, data = sambanis, family = binomial(link = "probit"))
</code></pre>

<p>summary(model)</p>

<p><code>
</code></p>

<pre><code>## Call:
## glm(formula = warstnsb ~ gdpl1 + grol1 + inst3l1 + anoc2l1 + 
##     oil2l1 + ef1 + lpopnsl1 + mtnl1 + warnsl1, family = binomial(link = "probit"), 
##     data = sambanis)
## 
## Deviance Residuals: 
##    Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max  
## -0.604  -0.231  -0.173  -0.106   3.560  
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error z value Pr(&gt;|z|)    
## (Intercept) -3.90226    0.46234   -8.44  &lt; 2e-16 ***
## gdpl1       -0.09271    0.02295   -4.04  5.3e-05 ***
## grol1       -0.51380    0.49750   -1.03  0.30172    
## inst3l1      0.23713    0.09634    2.46  0.01384 *  
## anoc2l1      0.23792    0.08807    2.70  0.00690 ** 
## oil2l1       0.29680    0.11541    2.57  0.01012 *  
## ef1          0.35605    0.16455    2.16  0.03049 *  
## lpopnsl1     0.10503    0.02743    3.83  0.00013 ***
## mtnl1        0.00199    0.00182    1.09  0.27466    
## warnsl1     -0.06609    0.10492   -0.63  0.52873    
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 '***' 0.001 '**' 0.01 '*' 0.05 '.' 0.1 ' ' 1 
## 
## (Dispersion parameter for binomial family taken to be 1)
## 
##     Null deviance: 1133.2  on 5892  degrees of freedom
## Residual deviance: 1038.8  on 5883  degrees of freedom
##   (3567 observations deleted due to missingness)
## AIC: 1059
## 
## Number of Fisher Scoring iterations: 8
</code></pre>

<h2>Adding the square of ethnic fractionalization</h2>

<p><code> r Adding the square of ethnic fractionalization
</code>
model &lt;&ndash; glm(warstnsb  gdpl1 + grol1 + inst3l1 + anoc2l1 + oil2l1 + ef1 + ef1sq +</p>

<pre><code>    lpopnsl1 + mtnl1 + muslim + warnsl1, data = sambanis, family = binomial(link =          "probit"))
</code></pre>

<p>summary(model)</p>

<p><code>
</code></p>

<pre><code>## Call:
## glm(formula = warstnsb ~ gdpl1 + grol1 + inst3l1 + anoc2l1 + 
##     oil2l1 + ef1 + ef1sq + lpopnsl1 + mtnl1 + muslim + warnsl1, 
##     family = binomial(link = "probit"), data = sambanis)
## 
## Deviance Residuals: 
##    Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max  
## -0.595  -0.230  -0.172  -0.103   3.547  
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error z value Pr(&gt;|z|)    
## (Intercept) -3.94606    0.48647   -8.11    5e-16 ***
## gdpl1       -0.09092    0.02370   -3.84  0.00012 ***
## grol1       -0.50874    0.49343   -1.03  0.30253    
## inst3l1      0.23723    0.09641    2.46  0.01386 *  
## anoc2l1      0.24253    0.08838    2.74  0.00607 ** 
## oil2l1       0.26000    0.12119    2.15  0.03192 *  
## ef1          0.51893    0.72622    0.71  0.47488    
## ef1sq       -0.17995    0.71442   -0.25  0.80113    
## lpopnsl1     0.10452    0.02775    3.77  0.00017 ***
## mtnl1        0.00184    0.00188    0.98  0.32529    
## muslim       0.00104    0.00111    0.93  0.35169    
## warnsl1     -0.06888    0.10501   -0.66  0.51185    
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 '***' 0.001 '**' 0.01 '*' 0.05 '.' 0.1 ' ' 1 
## 
## (Dispersion parameter for binomial family taken to be 1)
## 
##     Null deviance: 1133.2  on 5892  degrees of freedom
## Residual deviance: 1037.8  on 5881  degrees of freedom
##   (3567 observations deleted due to missingness)
## AIC: 1062
## 
## Number of Fisher Scoring iterations: 8
</code></pre>

<p><code> r Using Sambanis alternative coding of civil war
</code>
model &lt;&ndash; glm(warstns  gdpl1 + grol1 + inst3l1 + anoc2l1 + oil2l1 + ef1 + ef1sq +</p>

<pre><code>    lpopnsl1 + mtnl1 + muslim + warnsl1, data = sambanis, family = binomial(link = "probit"))
</code></pre>

<p>summary(model)</p>

<p><code>
</code></p>

<pre><code>## Call:
## glm(formula = warstns ~ gdpl1 + grol1 + inst3l1 + anoc2l1 + oil2l1 + 
##     ef1 + ef1sq + lpopnsl1 + mtnl1 + muslim + warnsl1, family = binomial(link = "probit"), 
##     data = sambanis)
## 
## Deviance Residuals: 
##    Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max  
## -0.532  -0.217  -0.165  -0.102   3.499  
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error z value Pr(&gt;|z|)    
## (Intercept) -3.73245    0.52338   -7.13  9.9e-13 ***
## gdpl1       -0.08649    0.02469   -3.50  0.00046 ***
## grol1       -0.09783    0.48861   -0.20  0.84131    
## inst3l1      0.23635    0.10911    2.17  0.03030 *  
## anoc2l1      0.28191    0.09773    2.88  0.00392 ** 
## oil2l1       0.16875    0.14066    1.20  0.23027    
## ef1          0.65104    0.77115    0.84  0.39853    
## ef1sq       -0.38362    0.77341   -0.50  0.61989    
## lpopnsl1     0.08969    0.03039    2.95  0.00316 ** 
## mtnl1        0.00209    0.00205    1.02  0.30854    
## muslim       0.00118    0.00124    0.95  0.34246    
## warnsl1     -0.21649    0.31589   -0.69  0.49313    
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 '***' 0.001 '**' 0.01 '*' 0.05 '.' 0.1 ' ' 1 
## 
## (Dispersion parameter for binomial family taken to be 1)
## 
##     Null deviance: 915.34  on 5161  degrees of freedom
## Residual deviance: 842.13  on 5150  degrees of freedom
##   (4298 observations deleted due to missingness)
## AIC: 866.1
## 
## Number of Fisher Scoring iterations: 8
</code></pre>

<h2>Using Fearon and Laitin 2003 coding of civil war</h2>

<p><code> r Using Fearon and Laitin 2003 coding of civil war
</code>
model &lt;&ndash; glm(warst7b  gdpl1 + grol1 + inst3l1 + anoc2l1 + oil2l1 + ef1 + ef1sq +</p>

<pre><code>    lpopnsl1 + mtnl1 + muslim + warnsl1, data = sambanis, family = binomial(link = "probit"))
</code></pre>

<p>summary(model)</p>

<p><code>
</code></p>

<pre><code>## Call:
## glm(formula = warst7b ~ gdpl1 + grol1 + inst3l1 + anoc2l1 + oil2l1 + 
##     ef1 + ef1sq + lpopnsl1 + mtnl1 + muslim + warnsl1, family = binomial(link = "probit"), 
##     data = sambanis)
## 
## Deviance Residuals: 
##    Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max  
## -0.501  -0.200  -0.145  -0.086   3.590  
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error z value Pr(&gt;|z|)    
## (Intercept) -4.28989    0.54194   -7.92  2.5e-15 ***
## gdpl1       -0.08807    0.02665   -3.30  0.00095 ***
## grol1       -0.27141    0.52732   -0.51  0.60677    
## inst3l1      0.19536    0.10692    1.83  0.06768 .  
## anoc2l1      0.25845    0.09748    2.65  0.00802 ** 
## oil2l1       0.13327    0.14174    0.94  0.34707    
## ef1          0.44027    0.80427    0.55  0.58409    
## ef1sq       -0.22642    0.79784   -0.28  0.77657    
## lpopnsl1     0.11930    0.03065    3.89  9.9e-05 ***
## mtnl1        0.00255    0.00204    1.25  0.21124    
## muslim       0.00155    0.00122    1.26  0.20659    
## warnsl1      0.01688    0.11169    0.15  0.87987    
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 '***' 0.001 '**' 0.01 '*' 0.05 '.' 0.1 ' ' 1 
## 
## (Dispersion parameter for binomial family taken to be 1)
## 
##     Null deviance: 897.81  on 5892  degrees of freedom
## Residual deviance: 822.48  on 5881  degrees of freedom
##   (3567 observations deleted due to missingness)
## AIC: 846.5
## 
## Number of Fisher Scoring iterations: 9
</code></pre>

<h2>Only ethnic fractionalization</h2>

<p><code> r Only ethnic fractionalization
</code>
model &lt;&ndash; glm(warstnsb  ef1 + ef1sq, data = sambanis, family = binomial(link = &ldquo;probit&rdquo;))
summary(model)</p>

<p><code>
</code>   ## Call:</p>

<pre><code>## glm(formula = warstnsb ~ ef1 + ef1sq, family = binomial(link = "probit"), 
##     data = sambanis)
## 
## Deviance Residuals: 
##    Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max  
## -0.303  -0.227  -0.196  -0.161   2.990  
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error z value Pr(&gt;|z|)    
## (Intercept)   -2.302      0.131  -17.63   &lt;2e-16 ***
## ef1            0.323      0.589    0.55     0.58    
## ef1sq          0.283      0.580    0.49     0.63    
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 '***' 0.001 '**' 0.01 '*' 0.05 '.' 0.1 ' ' 1 
## 
## (Dispersion parameter for binomial family taken to be 1)
## 
##     Null deviance: 1249.6  on 6268  degrees of freedom
## Residual deviance: 1230.5  on 6266  degrees of freedom
##   (3191 observations deleted due to missingness)
## AIC: 1237
## 
## Number of Fisher Scoring iterations: 7
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What trust is not]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/22/what-trust-is-not/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-22T12:50:34-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/22/what-trust-is-not</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Trust is not the absence of fear or insecurity regarding the possibility of betrayal. The very structure of our society wounds us so badly from the very beginning of our lives that perhaps such fears and insecurities are doomed to persist. Rather, trust is the feeling of peaceful confidence in a particular relationship <em>despite</em> whatever fears or insecurities one nonetheless continues to feel. Trust is only meaningful as an <em>earned relief</em> from fear and insecurity; as such, it not only implies the continued presence of fear and insecurity outside of the trust relation, it even requires a practiced awareness of the default fear and insecurity which has typically persisted as a fact throughout the greater part of the whole, global human network. We find negative evidence of this in the observation that partners in an honest trust relation often become so absorbed in their own mutual security that they lose awareness of the frightful insecurity against which they have built that trust with great labors and against great odds. When this happens, the storehouse of trust quickly begins to deplete. In colloquial terms, we often refer to exactly this process when we object to being &ldquo;taken for granted.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Historically, the bourgeois defenses against this tendency are typically strategies of locking-into and locking-up the trust relation as soon as it is sufficiently established: make commitments backed by the wrath of God and the law (marriage); construct a physical space that is at once a fortress against external threats and a prison to contain internal threats of flight (the &ldquo;home&rdquo;); then whither until death in the empty husk of a trust that dies six months after it is locked-in.  Trust in the absence of fear and insecurity is not trust; it is merely a glorified emotional comatose which accomplishes nothing more than self-protection and the <em>forgetting</em> of the real omnipresence of fear and insecurity that persists between nearly everyone else.</p>

<p>Furthermore, this bourgeois illusion of trust is not simply pathetic, which would at least be harmless. This false trust of the bourgeois family is <em>productive</em> of more human fear and insecurity than existed before it was &ldquo;locked-in.&rdquo; It produces net fear and insecurity because the little and tawdry security gained by the bourgeois couple is more than offset by all the lonely, isolated peers who are objectively less secure after each and every exclusive, excluding, and acquisitive bourgeois coupling. Finally, the bourgeois techniques of politically organizing trust not only tend to destroy the true and emancipating reality of any real trust they seek to hoard, but additionally, by their exclusive and excluding nature they hardly permit any honest understanding (in private or public) about how this political organization of trust ultimately fails everyone. The basic political form of the bourgeois couple necessarily brings with it a strategically dishonest public ideology because its very strategy is simulative and dissimulative: what is most characteristic of the bourgeois organization of trust relations is the creation of a political edifice that props-up merely an idea of trust, using privatized and therefore rarified social resources. The real production of real trust <em>has nothing to do with it. </em>In fact, the whole bourgeois organization and conception of trust seems almost expressly designed to excise the necessity and anxiety of having to build trust.</p>

<p>In other words, because the bourgeois organization of trust relations is chiefly a system for simulating trust and dissimulating its precariousness, it is especially damning for the overall social trust because it not only fails itself and denies others, it also requires and sustains public allegiance to its honor and continuation at all costs. After all, that is the bourgeois couple&rsquo;s original intention: to sustain a privatized &ldquo;trust&rdquo; at all costs, to hide from the insecurities that have always plagued humans everywhere, to pretend that fear has been abolished, at least until death do it part.  The truth is that people cannot know trust when fear and insecurity have merely been excluded and forgotten. Today, real trust can only be known when real fears and insecurities are so honestly recognized, shared, and accepted as a common problem and common responsibility. When this really truly occurs, the release from bourgeois fakery is so vertiginous and empowering that it cannot be mistaken. It is often named &ldquo;falling in love.&rdquo; Indeed, there is no reason to believe its uncommon and it is almost certainly the once-truly-lived kernel of truth within the dead husk of most bourgeois relationships.</p>

<p>We, on the other hand, do not seek to lock-in or lock-up the truth that together we have glimpsed, because for us, the truth we have shared is the hardest and rarest truth that can be shared: that there is nothing whatsoever to lock-in or lock-up. Recall that <em>to betray</em> means <em>to reveal</em> as much as it means <em>to deceive</em>. We do not betray each other because we neither hide nor reveal anything, but rather we produce shared truths that did not exist before of us. We are not therefore free of insecurities and hardly a day goes by that we do not tremble with some mundane everyday fear; we simply love each other but we truly love each other, and we trust each other <em>despite</em> that real love is a real cause for very real fears.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reactionary law and bourgeois desire]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/18/reactionary-law-and-bourgeois-desire/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-18T22:06:45-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/18/reactionary-law-and-bourgeois-desire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An unfortunate tendency of exceptionally repressive laws and draconian sentences is that, in middle-class eyes, they tend to justify themselves: to bourgeois stiffs, it begins to seem as if anyone who would risk such harsh punishments <em>must be</em> so crazy and dangerous that it feels appropriate and reassuring to be protected by such a vicious legal machine. Indeed, the self-justifying effect of a draconian legal system increases as punishments get more severe for less and less significant behaviors. As the punishments become larger and the crimes smaller, even more inclined is the average person to wonder with a mix of fear and envy why anyone would insist on actions that seem to them so trivial given such great costs.</p>

<p>Knowing already that countless people are jailed for years on simple, non-violent drug charges, we begin to read more and more absurd headlines: a black homeless woman is given a 12-year prison sentence for sending her son to a public school with an incorrect home address; even a white man is given a 2-year prison sentence <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_DeChristopher">for outbidding oil companies in a big land auction</a> and another white man is sentenced <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weev">three years in prison for accessing a publicly available website</a> simply because it wasn&rsquo;t intended for public view. In response to increasingly absurd and vicious applications of the law, the average fish-blooded citizen tends to think only that anyone who still insists on such unorthodox exercises of freedom must <em>lack all sense of proportion</em>. And this frightens them half to death, for good reason. Of course, in some sense, this view is technically correct (to maintain any integrity in a society such as ours requires a deep refusal of its ratios) but what is critical to grasp is that to the average and spineless citizen, those who display any kind of autonomy inconsistent with the police order <em>truly</em> appear <em>that</em> dangerous. And perhaps they really are. Not only because such behavior lacks the proportions of everyday middle-class order and therefore <em>generally</em> threatens it; because middle-class comforts and privileges could and would be re-distributed if it were not for a firm legal system, they are<em> especially</em> threatened when increasingly decent people are punished with increasing absurdity for breaking increasingly stupid laws for engaging in fairly reasonable actions. When there are individuals who insist on doing what they want despite the risk of increasingly insane legal punishment, the average citizen who marginally benefits from this legal system will only prefer more laws, more police, and more prisons.</p>

<p>It will never cease to astound us how impoverished the bottom ranks of the relatively privileged groups (in particular, white people, male-gendered people) can become without rebelling. But the present thesis might solve some portion of this classic puzzle. No matter how obvious it is that the contemporary political system has been destroying, and will continue destroying, even these historically privileged groups, they are paralyzed from resisting because they are wholly indebted to precisely this system and its tendencies of exclusion and oppression for whatever material and psychological possessions they still possess. The reason that rebellion is perhaps impossible for such souls, the reason they can see no other option than to double-down on their reactionary wagers, is because every advancement of capitalist exclusion and oppression is simply the advancement of what they once unconsciously but nonetheless gleefully assumed as the core of their beliefs and behaviors. Their refusal to rebel is suicide, but rebellion too would be suicide. Whichever path they choose, may they only choose quickly!<em> </em> 
Finally, this same thesis which helps us understand absurdly aggressive legal reaction also sheds light on why other types of crime are surprisingly under-punished relative to what we would expect. For example, as the recent and now notorious Steubenville rape case attests, young men who engage in brutal sexual violence against women often receive significantly shorter prison sentences than many non-violent, drug offenders. For the reasons already articulated, it is easy to see why property-related crimes are so grossly over-punished while crimes such as rape are relatively under-punished: crimes even vaguely related to property threaten relatively powerful (but increasingly fearful) groups invested in the status quo, while sexual violence against women—as one of the most basic substructures underwriting our political system built on domination—is the most basic kind of activity that constitutes the power of these relatively privileged but increasingly fearful groups invested in the status quo. From this perspective, it is not at all surprising that the former set of crimes is increasingly punished while the latter is punished less and less.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chapter 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/14/1/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-14T12:51:43-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/14/1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dear Reader,</p>

<p>I am writing to tell you that I love you and I am already scared of losing you. That does not mean I like you, but I do love you and I don’t want to lose you. I don’t know what love is or what exactly people mean by it, but that is almost certainly what I wish to say. More and more I grow convinced that I know less and less, which is disappointing not least because I’ve always expected the opposite, that I would learn more and more as I go. But I also understand this would seem to bode very poorly for you, my dear reader, given our society’s widespread prejudice in favor of smart writers. In fact, I know with certainty that I have nothing to offer you which you do not already have, because despite the exuberance and intensity you’ll find in some of these pages, I have not the slightest idea what I am talking about. I wrote this book not because I had any great ideas or imaginative plots to share with with the world; quite the opposite, I set about writing this book almost to atone for the indecency of having nothing at all to share. If, in the end, I have atoned for nothing, I hope these pages will at least help you understand one human life. Lest, in the end, you still do not understand me, I write you this present message directly and up front, in order that you might at least understand my intentions. I do not really recall if I began this book with the present passage or if I have only recollected it as that good old bugger Plato might have put it, but either way, in the end, it seems sensible to place this here in the beginning.</p>

<p>I don’t really know what I originally wanted to accomplish relating all of these experiences, observations, and fabrications. But I now believe, after reviewing these pages, that I’ve been trying to express <em>what people mean</em> when they say “I love you,” rather than just saying it. Saying “I love you,” just doesn’t do the trick so I’ve had to approach it in a very roundabout way with all kinds of misfirings and false alarms. And my tone and composure are already slipping…</p>

<p>When I see you in person, I say things I do not really want to say and I want to say things I do not or cannot say; and every time, immediately afterwards, I try to think about how to do it better and then I think I will do it better the next time and sometimes I do, but that’s rare and  now with this run-on sentence but my God, I am just tired of editing! My edited formal English always sounds just as stupid as my stupid English so it just doesn’t matter to me anymore. Think the thing, chop it up, say the damn things and just stick periods and commas and all sorts of marks wherever they work. No originality or intelligence or even creativity, it’s actually stupidity and laziness because it’s just easier to say the damn things however. It’s more beautiful, too, of course, but that’s an effect and certainly not a cause of modern stylistic currents.</p>

<p>I thought that if I “wrote a book” then I would find the best way to say the things I want to say and avoid or delete the things I don’t really want to say. Well, that whole idea is a sham: it doesn’t work, you face all the same problems you’ve always faced trying to communicate, the failure just takes longer. Then I thought I could atone for the failure of this book by appending this letter to the beginning. Well, I can’t, and so what? Am I supposed to feel sorry? Am I supposed to shred all of these pages, these pages that I have become? Should I apologize <em>ad nauseum</em> for even the failure of this idiotic apology-in-advance, with another apology that would probably fail just as well? (If I had any consistency, which I don’t, thankfully). Rich people like to say things like “the buck stops here,” which is exactly how I feel, except I despise the rich. The rich have enough bucks to make it stop wherever they want, so it’s interesting that when they say the “buck stops here”, “here” always seems to mean “somewhere else, later” because the buck never seems to stop. But my total store of bucks is negative, so I can confirm that indeed the buck stops here.</p>

<p>Whatever people mean when they say I love you, that’s what I’m trying to say, that’s it and I’m not promising you anything else. I just don’t know. I want you to do everything you want to do and nothing you don’t want to do. Everyone gets to dawdle along as they please but there is a thing that happens when you are writing something about something or to somebody and then at the last minute it somehow swerves toward something else because it’s like a rule of language that you’re not really allowed to just say something true about something directly to someone. Language isn’t necessarily a prison-house as Heidegger said, it’s just illegal to say what you think.</p>

<p>But what an awful book, they’ll say! I would be very satisfied with that, given that one of my chief curiosities has always been the question of why everybody does not write their own book&mdash;everybody having their own style of speaking and failing. I would be quite happy to write a terrible book, given that all the “good” books I’ve ever read were written by perfect idiots; and that most of the really smart people I know, who could write excellent books, never have. That’s always perplexed me and if my book is deemed awful, I would be all the happier to be a bad writer who nonetheless wrote a book. That is beautiful, that is something, I think.</p>

<p>Nothing recommends this book other than the intensities which were strong enough to produce it, intensities which had and continue to have nowhere else to go. Failure though it may be, failure at even being a failure though it may be, this book is my failure and I’m quite happy with it. Everyone deserves their own failure. And ultimately if one is honest about one’s failures, in the exactitude of expressing what is absolutely singular in one’s personal failures, it turns out you can write a pretty decent book if I do say so myself! And even if it’s as awful as this one, you’ve at least written a book. And then, if only you keep going&mdash;why not?&mdash;cultivating a little garden of failures that are at least your failures which you have worked so hard to earn, well then things begin to look pretty okay and a very different place far from here and later also where the buck never stops even for the poor and then you sort of <em>get how this writing thing works </em>but only for a second and then you just feel stupid and scared and you would suddenly feel more than happy if you only sold one article to one magazine but then you realize that that would ruin everything and eveything would be lost and that bad books are the only real books because at least they’re bad and at least they’re true and at least nobody wants to buy them and least you get to keep them for you and your friends, just like my favorite garden of all the gardens I’ve ever had, which is none, is the big idiotic dirt lot on the side of our house&mdash;because nobody ever wants to walk in it with me, nobody ever wants to walk in that lot with me, nobody even wants to sit in that lot with me because I never even ask them because it’s just not good as far as gardens go&mdash;and so it just sits there, empty, ugly, stupid, a waste of space. But what this means is that if our fence gets smashed down by some random person then we don’t have to worry about our beautiful garden being destroyed by some idiot and instead we can just be happy that someone honored our lot.</p>

<p>I want to walk through a dirt lot with you because then you would know for sure that I’m not walking with you because the garden is beautiful, but because you are beautiful and you make the dirt lot beautiful and I only want to write bad books because if any single person ever actually likes one, then I’ll know I must have done something right.</p>

<p>Whatever people mean when they say I love you, that is what I am trying to express here, no matter how hard it is to find on any one particular page. I’m sorry that things might not work out between us forever but if you like this book and sort of “get it” then let’s just spend time whenever we both want to and just be really honest and caring no matter how stupid and obscene that is in real life and destroy the things that get in our way, although the difficulty is destroying what deserves to be destroyed rather than what most people destroy even in equally good-spirited pursuits, namely each other. We might never know what to do or say but if you read this book and even sort of “get it” then as long as we are really, truly trying to get to the bottom of things together, with no ulterior motives hiding in the wings, if there’s nothing else to gain then there’s nothing to fear and we can just laugh when we’re not sure and keep going regardless because the only way to lose is to stop.</p>

<p>Even if you leave me one day for good, that would be fine because I am trying, and I trust that you are trying, and everyone has the right to dawdle along as they see fit. We can all do everything we want if we just let each other and this is not issuing from the perspective of poorly digested religions imported from the East or New Age spiritualism or the Christian heritage of the United States or the teachings of the great Rabbis or Marx or Lenin—fuck them all for they have all failed us so far—but from the patient and rigorous experiences, observations, and fabrications that I am. What else do we have left? Whatever people mean when they say I love you, that is what I’m trying to say, and why not?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A thought on jealousy]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/14/a-thought-on-jealousy/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-14T11:10:04-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/14/a-thought-on-jealousy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When one person is jealous of another, that jealousy can be oppressive for the other, of course, but it can also be perversely comforting: Jealousy <em>is</em> flattering. And in the most dangerous cases, rather than balance each other, the oppressiveness and the comfort fuel each other. If the oppression of jealousy is intolerable and even debilitating, the comfort that is supplied by its flattering component can begin to feel all the more needed. This perverse need or desire for the flattering insecurity of the other can lead the coveted person to continue in behaviors that effectively encourage the covetousness under which they are oppressed, rather than simply confront the jealous person and defuse these obviously unhealthy dynamics. In fact, this dynamic is so dangerous because of its final step: this process tends independently to <em>create</em> and <em>drive</em> jealousy because the person who is oppressed but unable to speak about it makes the jealous person fear—this time <em>rightfully</em>—that the other is hiding something. And, to boot, because there is a flattering component in jealousy, the jealous person is unfortunately and unconsciously encouraged to maintain their jealousy insofar as they observe how the other takes solace in it, however perverse and subtle that solace may be.</p>

<p>By starting this illustration with the jealousy of a jealous person, it might seem that I have set out to describe the perverse effects of jealousy. Although this is true, it is far too easy as it simply flatters our prejudices against a naive conception of the jealous persona, and would merely encourage the scapegoating of individuals for what are inherently social and political problems. The most radical implication of the process I&rsquo;m describing has not so much to do with the effects of jealous people, but the conditions for the very possibility of jealousy itself. That is, if one person is sufficiently oppressed by even the perception of someone else&rsquo;s insecure covetousness, or if the projection of a jealous other is ever simply a defensive mechanism for pushing one&rsquo;s own fears and insecurities onto an other, then at work here could very well be a very base-level mechanism for the possibility and <em>production</em> of jealousy in the first place.</p>

<p>For what is most interesting about the process discussed above is that, strictly speaking, it does not require the original jealous person to be jealous. The jealous person might not even be jealous or their jealousy could be quite mild and they could be quite willing to change if confronted, but the process could still launch from understandably defensive strategies on the part of the other seeking only to deal with their own essential and perhaps even primordial insecurities. Still, this process would tend to produce real jealousy even if there was none to begin with.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The radical core of conservatism]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/02/the-radical-core-of-conservatism/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-02T22:45:13-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/02/the-radical-core-of-conservatism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nobody wants to feel as if there is a &ldquo;big Other&rdquo; against which one has to defend oneself. Most people do generally want to learn about new ideas and the perspectives and experiences of others; I even think many people would be generally open to hearing marginalized voices and trying to understand how oppression works, but nobody wants to learn about new and strange ideas if they see those ideas as a pre-written doctrine which they&rsquo;re simply being told to accept. This is the radical, anti-authoritarian kernel of conservatism: the resistance against new ideas and vigorous reform is often, at its root, a refusal to trust authority—perhaps most often it is the refusal of the uneducated to trust the authority of the better educated. This is a tough and surprising point for educated radicals, but it is real nonetheless: normal bourgeois folks reject and loathe the earnest radical because the radical wants people to believe ideas with which scarcely anybody has the time or resources to ever become familiar. Our society tends to distort and confuse nearly everything in whatever way will make it as reactionary as possible, and the distribution of education is exemplary in this regard. <em>Skhole</em> —the Platonic word for the real leisure required for thinking—is attained by so few that whatever can be found there is doomed to be despised by everyone who has been excluded. Education is a cave no less than ignorance. Privileged or oppressed, no one&rsquo;s thoughts, words, or expressions are immune from accidentally contributing to a repressive society because the <em>effects</em> of even the most genuine, real, and true thoughts are determined quite apart from their authenticity, reality, and truth.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Non-linearity in reflection]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/19/433-non-linearity-in-reflection/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-19T18:20:32-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/19/433-non-linearity-in-reflection</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The problem with self-reflection is that it&rsquo;s a non-linear system. Under certain conditions, the smallest kernel of anxiety grows exponentially because we feel anxiety about having anxiety. And the smaller the original anxiety—that is, the more trite the original problem—the more ashamed and embarrassed we are for even feeling it in the first place, and the greater the rate at which the original minor anxiety morphs into a generalized neurosis.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A note on masculinity and self-expression]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/17/a-note-on-masculinity-and-self-expression/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-17T14:25:11-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/17/a-note-on-masculinity-and-self-expression</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One characteristically masculine technique of expression is to translate feelings of fear and insecurity into verbal and gestural forms of aggression and bids for power. In other words: not expression at all, but rather the opaque, instrumental action of concretely attempting to remove an irritation by subduing its real or imagined sources. Not depleting or reducing fear and insecurity but simply displacing them onto others. What the average man expects from women, and indeed requires from them, in order to exist with the fears and insecurities he knows no other way to deal with, is the woman&rsquo;s passive compliance with this masculinist formula of translating felt fears and insecurities into aggression, and many popular tropes about male-female romance only catalog the most traditional and well-known ways in which women have figured out how to cope with these strategic ruses of masculine dissimulation which are intended to pass for expression. Women who are no longer willing to shoulder all of this displaced insecurity and fear are, for obvious reasons, an extremely fearful threat to the traditional man. If such traditional men were simply backward, hopeless fools with whom it&rsquo;s not even worth bothering, then perhaps we could simply write them off as too far gone. Then those of us with radical interests would have no real reason to be too concerned with the difficulties these men face in coming to terms with the truth of feminism. But it is not so easy because it must be admitted that even we men who are absolutely committed to learning and understanding the nature of patriarchy and are actually committed to changing our practices in a way consistent with the liberation of all people, the truth is that we don&rsquo;t currently have alternative ways of dealing with the fears and insecurities we all suffer from. And it cannot be treated as a matter of heroism: &ldquo;I will just deal with it, I have no right to complain, because I&rsquo;m just a privileged man in a patriarchal society,&rdquo; without this, too, being itself a patriarchal and masculinist recourse.</p>

<p>In other words, those interested in a radical collective resistance against patriarchy have to develop practices that allow men to deal with their insecurities and fears in a way that does not revert to partaking in ultimately masculinist stances. An opposite strategy is to forego all masculinist techniques, to sort of submit or offer oneself unconditionally, to say &ldquo;here I am, relinquishing myself of the only techniques I know for dealing with my securities and fears, here I am, nothing but insecurities and fears, and, in my refusal to displace these fears and insecurities onto others but having no other techniques for dealing with them, I will simply show them and reveal them in honesty.&rdquo; The difficulty here, again, is that the emotional difficulties of such a horrific ordeal of revelation and self-flagellation typically fall onto the shoulders of those who care. Historically, of course, it is on women that the burden of such care labor typically falls, making this strategy of absolutely candid surrender likely to backfire. Another way it backfires is that this sort of practice is truly quite grotesque, monstrous; it is literally inhuman insofar as it is basically the act of relinquishing all of the characteristically human, that is to say dissimulative and instrumental techniques for being in the world and presenting ourselves in the world as subjects. Needless to say, this inhumanity, although perhaps commendable on some ultimate scale, is quite exactly the opposite of what is attractive to humans, and it&rsquo;s nearly impossible to actually live with. The point worth stressing is that alternatives to the dead-ends of masculine self-expression are not readily available; it&rsquo;s not clear that anyone knows how to resist and replace them in a way that does not take recourse to some sort of instrumentalism and exploitation at some level.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The vertigo of social mobility]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/16/400-the-vertigo-of-social-mobility/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-16T13:10:32-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/16/400-the-vertigo-of-social-mobility</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Institutions lure you by flattering you, in a world where it is nearly impossible to find recognition outside of them; you begin to see yourself only in institutions that pre-exist you and over which you exercise no influence. If this is perfectly internalized, then you get typical neuroses, mid-life crises, etc. Alternatively, if it&rsquo;s not perfectly internalized, then you get perpetual, mini crises up front; you perpetually realize you&rsquo;re over-worked and over-working on things that are somehow sterilized in advance so as to make sure you cannot exercise freedom over them and you also realize that no matter how hard you work you will not overcome this impotence. The mythology of hard work is, for this reason, indispensable for the status quo; it&rsquo;s one of the only things that keeps people from realizing that they simply can&rsquo;t win, that nobody can win like that.</p>

<p>Furthermore, growing dependent on such an institution for the most essential and elemental psychological needs is a most deadly vulnerability because, when one steps back from the institution for one&rsquo;s own freedom, to the exact degree one is accustomed to the flattery of that institution, one will feel stupid and worthless and suffer all kinds of the most pathetic problems and embarrassments in trying to step back. This is why the businessman in mid-life crisis is one of the most pathetic figures. However, every downturn of self-esteem that comes from such a precarious and self-betraying identification with an institution, tends to produce an upturn in at least one thing: economic consumption. For, the one thing the institutions will give you is money. And they&rsquo;ll give it to you precisely to the degree you&rsquo;re capable of doing something intense outside of an institution; nothing gets a higher price than that and intellectual history is replete with examples. When the life of the mind faulters and there is money in the bank, an almost automatic transference of energy takes place in which the mind fixates on some new thing to buy. Most important in this respect are upper-class goods such as nice clothing and nice housing. &ldquo;Why am I so stressed and neurotic?&rdquo; they ask themselves. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s because I don&rsquo;t have the proper materials for such an important life.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Because money is the only thing the institutions ultimately offer you, there is an overwhelming tendency to spend it upwards so to speak&mdash;so as to alleviate the stresses incurred in earning it. This point is perhaps banal, but the less observed point here is not just the material compensation of purchased pleasures for working stress; it&rsquo;s that the things purchased actually come to convince people of the legitimacy of the social distribution of resources. &ldquo;I need a nice sunny loft apartment all to myself because I need to focus and that&rsquo;s when I&rsquo;m most creative, because I am an academic.&rdquo; In fact, the exact opposite is the truth: I need a nice sunny loft apartment precisely because I&rsquo;m not an academic, so that in trying to be one for money I get so stressed and distracted I can&rsquo;t even do it how most people live, so I have to spend this money on a new apartment, etc. Then, lo and behold, all of the material and psychological vertigo of upward mobility comes along. That vertigo is real, it is the <em>real movement</em> as the Marxists like to say, of being distributed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The equality in evil]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/16/the-equality-in-evil/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-16T13:07:33-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/16/the-equality-in-evil</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We fetishize words in such a way that when someone says something, we are prone to find them outrageously evil should they choose certain words. But the reality is that the actual quality of human drives probably differs much less across history and space than we wish to believe. This sense is inflated by the significance we attach to particular words, and distorted in severe biases in the social distribution of verbal facility. This is evidenced by the fact that the average, &ldquo;well-bred&rdquo;, sensitive, educated person, almost certainly plays very often, in their head, with certain extremely uncouth and perhaps even wildly offensive ideas and phrasings before instantly knowing or realizing, precisely on account of their well bred discrimination, that such words would likely incur severe social punishment within their peer group. Those who are decent and polite are usually only well educated, which means they&rsquo;re merely better trained in the repression and verbal dissimulation of evil compared to the uneducated who are far more likely to spew all kinds of bigotry in public.</p>

<p>This all suggests a really interesting convergence of the two opposite meanings of the word &ldquo;discrimination&rdquo;: namely that the dominant classes who benefit from social institutions of racial, gender, and class discrimination in the political sense, are precisely those who have the most trained sense of &ldquo;discrimination&rdquo; in the valorized sense of nuance. The same base human drives that more or less unite us all, and the same overarching social institutions organize all of our habits and tendencies, even if they distribute us differentially. The ability to &ldquo;discriminate&rdquo; in the good sense, is itself a privilege of discrimination in the bad sense. We must try to understand better that occupying a position in that discriminate classes in no way makes us better or less evil than people who are simply less adept at hiding their tracks. Ours is simply a different kind of evil, an evil that we have stuffed under layers and layers of torturously complicated rationales, but which is most manifest at the material level of that which we actually enjoy at the cost of the suffering of so many others. There is, then, a certain overall equality of evil in a society such as ours where that evil is so thoroughly mediated and distributed by institutions, such that for some it is transparent and unadorned much to the criticism of the public mind, while for others it is simply buried, dissimulated, and finally rewarded.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Analysis of #GazaUnderAttack tweets]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/12/29/analysis-of-gazaunderattack-tweets/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-29T14:12:32-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/12/29/analysis-of-gazaunderattack-tweets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>During the Israeli-Palestinian attacks of last month, I scraped from the Twitter API about 270,000 tweets containing the hashtag #gazaunderattack. Given the unprecedented degree to which this war was fought online, tweets of this sort could and should become really important data for political scientists. I&rsquo;m too busy right now to say very much here, but I want to share some basic descriptive analyses for anyone who might be interested. The dataset can be downloaded <a href="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/20498362/tweets_%23gazaunderattack.csv">here</a> and the R script that produced these analyses is available at the very bottom.</p>

<p>Almost everything in this post I learned how to do directly and solely from the amazingly smart, open and generous #Rstats community. The scraping and time-series plot follow a script by <a href="http://bommaritollc.com/2011/02/26/archiving-tweets-with-python/">Michael Bommarito</a>, and the rest follows scripts by <a href="https://github.com/benmarwick/AAA2011-Tweets/blob/master/AAA2011.R">Ben Marwick</a>.</p>

<h2>Analysis</h2>

<p>There are 269,158 tweets. These tweets are authored by 79,923 unique users. Of all the tweets, .62 are retweets.</p>

<p>This first graph plots the frequency of #gazaunderattack tweets in 30-minute intervals between November 17th and November 21st. I <em>believe__ </em>this is <em>all</em> of the tweets containing that hashtag within this period. I know the Twitter Search API is subject to weird filters and restrictions, but I believe the technique I used here pages through each and every tweet available within the available time period.</p>

<p><a href="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/timeseries.png"><img src="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/timeseries.png" alt="timeseries" /></a></p>

<p>Most frequent #gazaunderattack tweeters.</p>

<p><a href="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/tweet_counts.png"><img src="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/tweet_counts.png" alt="tweet_counts" /></a></p>

<p>The most retweeted tweeters. Interestingly, Anonymous seems to have had more reach, at least during this period, than the twitter account of Hamas (@AlqassamBrigade).</p>

<p><em><a href="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/retweet_counts.png"><img src="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/retweet_counts.png" alt="retweet_counts" /></a></em>The most retweeted tweeters as a ratio of total quantity of tweets sent.   Anonymous still seems to have had the most reach on the #gazaunderattack hashtag.</p>

<p><a href="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/retweet_ratios.png"><img src="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/retweet_ratios.png" alt="retweet_ratios" /></a></p>

<p>Most frequently tweeted links.<a href="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/links.png"><img src="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/12/links.png" alt="links" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://d3j5vwomefv46c.cloudfront.net/photos/large/688740234.jpg?key=964633&amp;Expires=1356766099&amp;Key-Pair-Id=APKAIYVGSUJFNRFZBBTA&amp;Signature=05VhXXvHpkOc2wqjLXrGMgNasVet~TM9zp9UELk3vd0aCJcGb6uJI4Uv4FEk5LNEQQSGWrUrV9mNKpp5STIrUEwFufBGCwcboTeLJfg55DA75JoXHkMdmedD5P6M2~EOYUbtqSOBFGY7VQgzfN-~UhU6lLSwV3grA4~ZrZDTIlI_">This is the image</a> in the most popular link, capturing an explosion from an Israeli airstrike in Gaza.</p>

<p>Again, the Python code I used to obtain the tweets and the R code I used to analyze them were lifted directly from scripts by the authors linked above.</p>

<p><code> r
</code>
x&lt;-read.csv(&ldquo;tweets_#gazaunderattack.csv&rdquo;, header=FALSE, stringsAsFactors=FALSE)
x$username&lt;-x$V2
x$text&lt;-x$V5</p>

<h6>##################################\</h6>

<h4>Nice Time-Series Plot</h4>

<h6>##################################\</h6>

<p>library(ggplot2)
x$date &lt;&ndash; strptime(x$V4, &ldquo;%a, %d %b %Y %H:%M:%S %z&rdquo;, tz = &ldquo;EST&rdquo;)
x$date &lt;&ndash; as.POSIXct(x$date, tz = &ldquo;EST&rdquo;)
timeseries&lt;-ggplot(data=x, aes(x=date)) + geom_bar(aes(fill=..count..), binwidth=60*30) + theme_bw() + ylab(&ldquo;# of Tweets&rdquo;) + xlab(&ldquo;Time&rdquo;)
timeseries
ggsave(file=&ldquo;timeseries.png&rdquo;)</p>

<h6>##################################\</h6>

<h4>Nice Plot of Frequent Tweeters</h4>

<h6>##################################\</h6>

<p>library(ggplot2)
x$username<a href="">x$username==&ldquo;&rdquo;</a>&lt;-NA
length(unique(x$username)) # see how many unique tweeter accounts in the sample
counts=table(x$username)
counts.sort&lt;-sort(counts)
counts.sort.subset=subset(counts.sort, counts.sort>350) # create a subset of those who tweeted at least 350 times or more
counts.sort.subset.df&lt;-data.frame(people=unlist(dimnames(counts.sort.subset)),count=unlist(counts.sort.subset)) # makes a funny sort of data frame&hellip;
counts.sort.subset.df&lt;-data.frame(people=as.factor(counts.sort.subset.df$people),counts=as.numeric(counts.sort.subset.df$count)) # makes a better data frame for ggplot to work with
ggplot(counts.sort.subset.df, aes(reorder(people,counts),counts)) + xlab(&ldquo;Author&rdquo;) + ylab(&ldquo;Number of messages&rdquo;)+ geom_bar() + coord_flip() + theme_bw() + opts(axis.title.x = theme_text(vjust = -0.5, size = 14)) + opts(axis.title.y=theme_text(size = 14, angle=90)) # plot nicely ordered counts of tweets by person for people > 5 tggsave(file = &ldquo;tweet_counts.pdf&rdquo;) # export the plot to a PDF file
ggsave(file = &ldquo;tweet_counts.png&rdquo;)</p>

<h6>####################################\</h6>

<h4>Nice Plot of Frequent Re-Tweeters</h4>

<h6>####################################\</h6>

<p>library(stringr)
x$text=sapply(x$text,function(row) iconv(row,to=&lsquo;UTF-8&rsquo;)) #remove odd characters
trim &lt;&ndash; function (x) sub(&lsquo;@&rsquo;,&lsquo;&rsquo;,x) # remove @ symbol from user names
x$rt=sapply(x$text,function(tweet) trim(str_match(tweet,&ldquo;^RT (@[[:alnum:]_]()*)&rdquo;)<a href="">2</a>)) #extract who has been RT’d
sum(!is.na(x$rt)) # see how many tweets are retweets
sum(!is.na(x$rt))/length(x$rt) # the ratio of retweets to tweets
countRT&lt;-table(x$rt)
countRT&lt;-sort(countRT)
countRT.subset=subset(countRT,countRT>1000) # subset those RT’d more than 1000 times
countRT.subset.df&lt;-data.frame(people=as.factor(unlist(dimnames(countRT.subset))),RT_count=as.numeric(unlist(countRT.subset)))
ggplot(countRT.subset.df, aes(reorder(people,RT_count),RT_count)) +
 xlab(&ldquo;Author&rdquo;) + ylab(&ldquo;Number of messages retweeted by others&rdquo;) +
 geom_bar() + coord_flip() + theme_bw() +
 opts(axis.title.x = theme_text(vjust = -0.5, size = 14)) +
 opts(axis.title.y=theme_text(size = 14, angle=90))</p>

<h1>plot nicely ordered counts of tweets by person for people > 1000 retweets</h1>

<p>ggsave(file = &ldquo;retweet_counts.png&rdquo;)</p>

<h6>####################################\</h6>

<h4>Nice Plot of RT-Tweet Ratios</h4>

<h6>####################################\</h6>

<p>t&lt;-as.data.frame(table(x$username)) # make table with counts of tweets per person
rt&lt;-as.data.frame(table(x$rt)) # make table with counts of retweets per person
t.rt&lt;-merge(t,rt,by=&ldquo;Var1&rdquo;) # combine tweet count and retweet count per person
t.rt<a href="">&ldquo;ratio&rdquo;</a>&lt;-t.rt$Freq.y / t.rt$Freq.x # creates new col and adds ratio tweet/retweet
sort.t.rt&lt;-t.rt<a href="">order(t.rt$ratio),</a> # sort it to put names in order by ratio
sort.t.rt.subset&lt;-subset(sort.t.rt,sort.t.rt$Freq.y>1000) # exclude those with 1000 tweets or less
sort.t.rt.subset.drop&lt;-droplevels(sort.t.rt.subset) # drop unused levels that got in there somehow&hellip; note that this is already a data frame
ggplot(sort.t.rt.subset, aes(reorder(Var1,ratio),ratio)) +
 xlab(&ldquo;Author&rdquo;) + ylab(&ldquo;Retweets as a ratio of total tweets&rdquo;) +
 geom_bar() + coord_flip() + theme_bw() +
 opts(axis.title.x = theme_text(vjust = -0.5, size = 14)) +
 opts(axis.title.y=theme_text(size = 14, angle=90))
ggsave(file = &ldquo;retweet_ratios.png&rdquo;)</p>

<h6>####################################\</h6>

<h4>Nice Plot of Most Popular Links</h4>

<h6>####################################\</h6>

<p>x$link=sapply(x$text,function(tweet) str_extract(tweet,(&ldquo;http[[:print:]]()+&rdquo;))) # creates new field and extracts the links contained in the tweet
x$link=sapply(x$text,function(tweet) str_extract(tweet,&ldquo;http[[:print:]](){16}&rdquo;)) # limits to just 16 characters after http so I just get the shortened link. They are all shortened, so this is fine, but there might be a better way using regex.
countlink&lt;-table(x$link) # get frequencies of each link
countlink&lt;-sort(countlink) # sort them
barplot(countlink) # plot freqs</p>

<h1>or to use ggplot2, read on&hellip;</h1>

<p>countlink&lt;-data.frame(table(na.omit((x$link))))
countlink&lt;-subset(countlink,countlink$Freq>300) # exclude those with 300 tweets or less
ggplot(countlink, aes(reorder(Var1, Freq), Freq)) +
 geom_bar() + coord_flip() + theme_bw() +
 xlab(&ldquo;Link&rdquo;) + ylab(&ldquo;Frequency&rdquo;) +
 opts(axis.title.x = theme_text(vjust = -0.5, size = 14)) +
 opts(axis.title.y=theme_text(size = 14, angle=90))
ggsave(file = &ldquo;links.png&rdquo;)</p>

<p>&#8220;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Duchamp on sinks and sources]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/11/11/388-Duchamp-on-sinks-and-sources/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-11T18:58:17-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/11/11/388-Duchamp-on-sinks-and-sources</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Duchamp said that he turned to the ready-made for no other reason than to “discharge” ideas. In other words, successful art objects are <em>sinks that become sources</em>. This gives a certain socio-electrical significance to the idea of a &ldquo;Fountain.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Untitled fragment]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/10/29/222/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-29T18:28:26-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/10/29/222</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hurricane Sandy just hit. It&rsquo;s supposed to be the storm of the century. Only question is, Jacob says, which century? So everyone just took a bunch of Adderall and everyone is just fucking around, building shit, reading and writing and all kinds of idiotic shit. We have ice and bottled water and nonperishable food supplies but I don&rsquo;t know what we&rsquo;re going to do if the FiOS goes out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Predicting turnout from Google search data]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/10/27/predicting-turnout-from-google-search-data/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-27T17:58:43-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/10/27/predicting-turnout-from-google-search-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Political scientists <a href="http://themonkeycage.org/blog/2012/10/25/will-2012-be-a-low-turnout-election-some-evidence-from-google-search-activity/%23comments">Jesse Richman</a> and <a href="http://themonkeycage.org/blog/2012/10/25/google-searches-and-turnout-a-cautionary-tale/">Erik Voeten</a> wonder if Google Search data can help us predict turnout in next month&rsquo;s Presidential election. To summarize, Richman finds that searches for &ldquo;vote&rdquo; in the past two elections predict voter turnout, and that low search volume for &ldquo;vote&rdquo; this year suggests a low turnout election. In response, Voeten shows that controlling for who has come online since 2004 and 2008 explains much of why search volume for &ldquo;vote&rdquo; appears small this year. There are lots of reasons search data is pretty tricky for making good inferences, but that shouldn&rsquo;t keep us from trying!</p>

<p>My thinking is that we can look at the <em>composition</em> of &ldquo;vote&rdquo; searches across elections to see whether this year&rsquo;s vote searches are indicative of greater voter turnout or greater voter demobilization/skepticism.</p>

<p>For instance, &ldquo;vote&rdquo; searches containing the terms &ldquo;where&rdquo; or &ldquo;when&rdquo; are probably more directly predictive of turning out to vote than the whole set of &ldquo;vote&rdquo; searches&mdash;as they indicate practical planning to turnout. On the other hand, &ldquo;vote&rdquo; searches containing the term &ldquo;why&rdquo; are probably far less predictive of turnout&mdash;and might even predict how many people are thinking &ldquo;why bother?&rdquo; and are considering staying home on election day.</p>

<p>So I went back to the data with this in mind. As baseline and as Voeten shows, if we consider voting searches (&ldquo;vote&rdquo; and &ldquo;voting&rdquo; together) as a proportion of searches for &ldquo;university&rdquo;, &ldquo;science&rdquo;, and &ldquo;law&rdquo;, this election hardly looks very different. So that&rsquo;s just (vote+voting) / ((university+science+law) / 3). As explained in the posts linked above, search volume data is scaled from 0 to 100 where 100 is the peak of that search term in the given time period, relative to all other search activity.</p>

<p><a href="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/votingsearches2.png"><img src="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/votingsearches2.png" alt="" /></a>And when we look at voting searches also containing the word &ldquo;why&rdquo; (as a proportion of the university-science-law index), again we find almost no difference.</p>

<p><a href="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/whyvotesearches.png"><img src="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/whyvotesearches.png" alt="" /></a>But when we look at voting searches also containing the words &ldquo;where&rdquo; and &ldquo;when&rdquo; (I take the average of vote+where and vote+when as a proportion of the university-science-law index), more people appear to be asking where and when to vote this year than in the past two Presidential elections. The p-value on the difference of means between 2008 and 2012 is .051.</p>

<p><a href="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/votingplansearches.png"><img src="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/votingplansearches.png" alt="" /></a>Finally, I look at the difference between the why-vote searches and the where/when-vote searches. The gap might be taken as an aggregate measure of how much society is using the web to <em>think about</em> the decision to turn out <em>without planning</em> to turnout, so that positive values might capture demobilization within vote searches (why bother?) and negative values reflect relatively resolved mobilization. And what we find is that this whole election year shows greater &ldquo;when/where&rdquo; vote searches than &ldquo;why&rdquo; vote searches at the present moment in the timeline but also for the year as a whole. In both of the previous elections there were more &ldquo;thinking&rdquo; searches than &ldquo;planning&rdquo; searches, but this year there have been more planning searches. As in the previous analyses, these are as a proportion of the university-science-law index, and the difference of means for 2008 and 2012 is statistically significant at the 99.9% confidence level.</p>

<p><a href="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/thinkplangapusl.png"><img src="http://justinmurphy.files.wordpress.com/2012/10/thinkplangapusl.png" alt="" /></a>Arguably, this difference variable perhaps already controls for education or political information because each term reflects a lack of knowledge, so it shouldn&rsquo;t be inflated by less educated/informed people coming online since 2004 and 2008. But the same pattern is evident and statistically significant if we look at this gap as a proportion of all &ldquo;politics&rdquo; search volume or just the raw differences of volume. Obviously, these are back-of-the napkin analyses and these data are plagued by difficulties. But these analyses don&rsquo;t suggest a low-turnout election in 2012. If anything, it looks like the web is registering more vote planning than in previous years.</p>

<p><a href="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/20498362/GoogleTrendsVoting.csv">Here is the data in .csv form</a>. Here is the <a href="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/20498362/GoogleTrendsTurnout.R">R script</a> to reproduce the analyses found here.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Revolutionary fun]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/10/20/revolutionary-fun/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-20T16:48:58-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/10/20/revolutionary-fun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Revolutionary fun is the only justified form of fun. Revolutionary fun is the fun had by playing with the power of those who have more power than oneself. Playing with the power of those who have more power than oneself is fun because it is the assertion of will over and against an illegitimate status quo. It is the enjoyment of creating anti-power. It is revolutionary because in its bold idleness it is inexplicable, enchanting, irresistably attractive. The human who can make a toy out of those who have more power is a magical creature to whom others will always wish to draw nearer. Playing with those who have more power is, in other words, an expression of <em>sheer will, </em>supported by neither material resources nor short-term instrumental calculations. Really though, it is neither magical nor even exceptional; to exercise the will is simply to be human, and to &ldquo;poke fun&rdquo; at the powerful behind closed doors is one of the most natural and common practices in the world. Because power is already levity in the face of suffering, to make light of the powerful is really just a deflation of false cruelty and a return to equilibrium. To actively and provocatively make such a plaything out of the false power of others appears as a magical inversion only because the real exercise of human will has been barred from so many people for so long.</p>

<p>This kind of fun therefore has two effects that are legitimately revolutionary—microscopic no doubt, but real nonetheless. First, it shakes the possession of power within the hands of those who hold it. A cop can easily bash the skull of a protester making some political demand, and a businessman is not phased by the dozen homeless people he passes on his way to work, because the social narrative they had to master to obtain their power in the first place—the narrative in which the strong are strong because they are superior to the weak—is exactly what gives them countless reasons for feeling perfectly fine in their brutality. Those who comfortably and without hesitation execute brutality will only be forced to hesitate, they will only falter and weaken and retreat, when they suddenly find themselves in social theatres for which they have no scripts.</p>

<p>In addition to concretely loosening the grip that the powerful have on power—we could just as well refer to the grip that power has over the powerful—revolutionary fun holds the line against the near abolition of human will altogether. It maintains a model, a memory, an instance no matter what might happen, of sheer will despite anything that might come. At a time when social control has become so solidified and the human will so thoroughly squeezed out of life; when, as in our society, even the prospect of heroic death against an enemy is barred by an enemy whose tactics involve the very impossibility of heroism—to make fun is to hold the last line of defense.</p>

<p>This holding of the last line of defense and the irresistible seduction referred to above are one and the same. In a social war such as ours, people obviously and always want what effectively defends humanity from that which destroys humanity. No matter how microscopic the mechanism may be, anything that effectively resists power and defends humans will be charming, beautiful, attractive, irresistible—and the more microscopic the mechanism the more fuzzy will be the comprehension of the attraction. Of course, unfortunately, it does not follow that everything charming and attractive is in defense of humanity. This is why the powerful have invested so dearly in learning the mechanisms of attraction. But in no way does the malleability of desire and attraction contradict the rule—nearly a tautology—that whatever effectively resists power and defends humans will be charming. If it is not somehow charming and attractive, we can be sure it is not effectively resisting power and defending humanity.</p>

<p>Finally, it is obvious that the privilege of toying with the powerful is a privilege unequally distributed throughout society. A minimum of personal security is necessary to dare and risk the real retribution of cops, bosses, teachers, bureaucrats, etc. But real tactical opportunities must not be dismissed on account of the limited conditions under which they are feasible; rather than discourage the privileged from using their privileges in the calculated, revolutionary fashion that corresponds to their social position, we should simply extend our efforts to delineate different tactical opportunities corresponding to each and every space in our increasingly differentiated social topography.  Just as the engine of an airplane looks, sounds, and functions very differently than the electronics in the cockpit because they are made of different materials and perform different functions in a larger design, the revolutionary machine will have to be composed of very different moving parts. The blueprint for a well-functioning revolutionary machine must be based<em> </em>on the critical awareness that privilege and oppression, abundance and scarcity, power and repression are distributed unevenly. This requires that the question of what is properly revolutionary activity not be confused by our hatred of privilege and the temptation to dismiss legitimately revolutionary tactics because they happen to be those of a privileged group. The critical point is to elaborate, as rigorously as possible, the various sorts of effectively revolutionary activity available to all people depending on the raw material available to them in their particular social position.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
