<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: note | Justin Murphy]]></title>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/categories/note/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-13T01:52:51+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Untitled]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/10/13/cupcakes-taste-like-violence/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-13T22:15:18+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/10/13/cupcakes-taste-like-violence</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>“Cupcakes taste like violence.” &ndash; Ahuviya Harel, at the Ox</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hip pouch (red square solidarity edition)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/05/27/23883065976/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-27T21:34:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/05/27/23883065976</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Ox just got a gnarly industrial-strength sewing machine so this week I decided to make my debut in fashion design.</p>

<p>Hat tip goes to <a href="http://rhls.com/about.html">Ruffeo Hearts Lil Snotty</a>, from whom I got the pattern <a href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;ved=0CGsQFjAA&amp;url=http://www.rhls.com/threadbanger/fannypack.pdf&amp;ei=iXnCT5KCFujG6AGeipSuCg&amp;usg=AFQjCNHyjzo-g5BE7flpB1rrY43PpfcfmA&amp;sig2=UJOrPRPgYAtdA_T6Q0gC4Q">here</a>. As a business their politics and aesthetics are not quite mine&mdash;ultimately they do seem to be selling the false freedoms of frivolity, nostalgia, and the possibility of an ethical life under contemporary capitalism&mdash;but as humans they seem pretty rad (anti-exploitation, &ldquo;anti-fashion&rdquo;, DIY, they closed down for May Day, etc.). Taking some liberties with the design and having neither a shred of experience nor skill in sewing, I feel like my version is sufficiently DIY-looking to at least signal a theoretical rejection of the status quo. Surveying my career as a fashion designer, I feel like my intention over the past six days or so has been to blend the prevailing hipster aesthetic with the, uh, &ldquo;militant anticapitalist aesthetic&rdquo; or something. I think by &ldquo;militant anticapitalist aesthetic&rdquo; I mean militant anticapitalist &ldquo;colors&rdquo; and &ldquo;rhetoric&rdquo; maybe.</p>

<p>In fact, it&rsquo;s a fucking mess of goddam strings sticking out of every nook and crevice in the bloody thing but I feel like that is just my signature style as a fashion designer. Everything I make will just have a million goddamn strings sticking out of every bloody fold and cranny, not on purpose but because that&rsquo;s just my style or something, i.e. what happened this time and will probably keep happening because I feel no desire to learn how to avoid that happening. I can&rsquo;t believe sewing works considering it&rsquo;s just a million little idiotic strings going every which way. Of course that works, so obvious.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s made of standard canvas from a bookbag, which I lined with vinyl to make it uh, possibly water resistant. Incidentally, the vinyl came from the Occupy Philly May Day &ldquo;STRIKE&rdquo; banner! It has belt loops in the back to string my belt through. I added a little D-ring, why? Fuck if I know!l Looks useful, why the fuck not? So easy, should have added a goddamn can opener while I was at it. I also threw in a few pencil holders, a little pouch on the inside, and a red square for the historically unprecedented, spontaneous, indefinite <em>manifestations</em> of hundreds of thousands of Québécois underway right now.</p>

<p><img src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_m4p316Twy31qz9517.jpg" alt="" /><img src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_m4p31yHtjy1qz9517.jpg" alt="" /><img src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_m4p36ijxKb1qz9517.jpg" alt="" />
<img src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_m4p372VTco1qz9517.jpg" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[local weather philadelphia]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/04/28/21940232210/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-28T00:27:59+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/04/28/21940232210</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>General Strike Google Bomb for Occupy Philly</p>

<p>Link: <a href="http://www.facebook.com/events/384999524851887">local weather philadelphia</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An inspired consumer reviews the city of Philadelphia on Yelp.com]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2011/08/21/9204475400/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-21T12:36:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2011/08/21/9204475400</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Written between 2:04 p.m. and 4:21 p.m. on August 19, 2011 by Justin M. (me).</p>

<h4><a href="http://www.yelp.com/biz/rustica-philadelphia%23hrid:4bNAWSbMmz6yObtcldxwCg/src:self">Rustica </a></h4>

<p>903 N 2nd St
Philadelphia, PA 19123
(215) 627-1393</p>

<p>Category: <a href="http://www.yelp.com/c/philadelphia/pizza">Pizza</a>
Neighborhood: Northern Liberties</p>

<p>Rustica is simply the best godd<em>mn place any second on this planet. I just ate a godd</em>mn buffalo chicken sicilian jigger for only $3, which is without a doubt the best pound-for-pound dollar-for-dollar thing to eat anywhere on this terrible website. It made me so f<em>cking happy I decided to sign up for this embarrassingly stupid website. It made me feel like I could be happy every second of every day just from once eating this thing that only cost $3; I was there all by myself, eating, and I just burst out laughing like a maniac. If you don’t go here every godd</em>mn day you are a maniac. A little girl was pointing up at the sign that says Rustica above the front door saying to her mommy how she liked it and I told her that I was the one who designed it, and I was! That’s how happy this place makes me every godd*mn day.</p>

<h4><a href="http://www.yelp.com/biz/frankford-hall-philadelphia%23hrid:IwOWmy1_xBvq8nuXnHNRlQ/src:self">Frankford Hall </a></h4>

<p>1210 Frankford Ave
Philadelphia, PA 19125
(215) 634-3338</p>

<p>Categories: <a href="http://www.yelp.com/c/philadelphia/pubs">Pubs</a>, <a href="http://www.yelp.com/c/philadelphia/german">German</a></p>

<p>This place is so bad that to me the core of the consumer experience is that I would never even think about going to this place unless I was really thirsty/hypnotized, which I might be one day, but not today or ever right now. Judging by the fashion of the people who go here and the quality of the storefront—which I designed, by the way, today, in Photoshop, to make it less intolerably offensively poorly-designed—this place is overpriced, boring, and induces severe anxiety/fear for the nature/future of humanity.</p>

<h4><a href="http://www.yelp.com/biz/the-barbary-philadelphia%23hrid:rfNF211viOiLSLWcmjUU4g/src:self">The Barbary </a></h4>

<p>951 Frankford Ave
Philadelphia, PA 19125</p>

<p>Category: <a href="http://www.yelp.com/c/philadelphia/danceclubs">Dance Clubs</a></p>

<p>This is the best bar and DJ house any f*cking minute of my life, any hemisphere since the Golden Age of ancient Greek civilization; I will recount everything that ever happened here to explain how good it is. Once when I was in college in 2004 I didn’t know places/things, I went there and felt it was exotic/scary/tattoos so then I got tattoos. I did not have intimacy that night (a morally dubious thing to say but this is the core of the consumer experience at this establishment, what the yelp guidelines ask for). Sometime after that I once danced with a girl for 60 minutes on/off and it seemed clear that we liked each other and I almost had intimacy that night but we only kissed, which is not intimacy but rather is typically perceived to be a clarion call for an intimacy that is imminently on the horizon so to speak. Then I remember I went back years later after I had found myself and I just immediately felt at home in this safe haven that now features two different barbaries, one for foodies and people who don’t like to pay covers (upstairs/barbarella), one for people who like to pay 3-5 dollars 2-7 nights per week to get photographed by facebook (downstairs/barbary regular). That one night after I had found myself already and was really at home here, that night I had intimacy. Some people think its awkward when you see someone at the barbary after you only had one intimacy with them after the barbary but I don’t think it is. I think at some places it might be like that but it never is for me at the barbary. A new room on top of the upstairs was just released, this is mysterious/will probably go there soon, you should too. Think that probably there is a nuclear-bomb-shelter in the basement where the owner/employees/photographers/DJs/most-photographe d-people will go if there is ever nuclear war and they will keep an “underground” facebook that holds all the photography archives to be released after the war to kind of like “repopulate” the scene for the third barbary because, as some reviewers have already mentioned, the barbary is currently on its second life.</p>

<h4><a href="http://www.yelp.com/biz/silk-city-diner-and-lounge-philadelphia%23hrid:LMeJmuQormb6lPNRfc8CaQ/src:self">Silk City Diner &amp; Lounge </a></h4>

<p>435 Spring Garden St
Philadelphia, PA 19123
(215) 592-8838</p>

<p>Categories: <a href="http://www.yelp.com/c/philadelphia/newamerican">American (New)</a>, <a href="http://www.yelp.com/c/philadelphia/danceclubs">Dance Clubs</a>
Neighborhoods: Northern Liberties, Spring Garden</p>

<p>I honestly think what happened here was it used to be cool among white hipsters on Thursday nights when they played 90s hip-hop and then many black people and bro’s started going and now it is not cool among white hipsters. I’m willing to be corrected if this is not a fair description of this establishment’s evolution, but this is honestly what I remember observing as a decently well-educated roughly socially-aware member of the white hipster community. I don’t think any of my friends / anyone in my dating pool really goes here anymore and like, nothing else cool or interesting I know of really happens here, so the core of my consumer experience here is that it is irrelevant to my life at this point in time.</p>

<p>People thought this was:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Useful (1)</p></li>
<li><p>Funny (1)</p></li>
</ul>


<h4><a href="http://www.yelp.com/biz/the-adobe-cafe-philadelphia-2%23hrid:2AhpGmVOfJJXe-3Vmaj00Q/src:self">The Adobe Cafe </a></h4>

<p>1919 E Passyunk Ave
Philadelphia, PA 19176
(215) 551-2243</p>

<p>Categories: <a href="http://www.yelp.com/c/philadelphia/mexican">Mexican</a>, <a href="http://www.yelp.com/c/philadelphia/tex-mex">Tex-Mex</a>, <a href="http://www.yelp.com/c/philadelphia/sportsbars">Sports Bars</a></p>

<p>Has dance party called Banana Chips, this fake Mexican restaurant for white people who prefer white people to eating so much really good/cheap Mexican food nearby. Feel like they have parlor games like foosball which I’ve played before and it was fun. They have so many TVs it’s completely godd*mn bonkers no wonder people go upstairs and pay to get into Banana Chips, which I feel like is comparable to Sorted (@ Barbary) in terms of quality/attractiveness/fashion of patrons, but is probably dumber/worse, although I’ve never gone to it. To make this review even more confusing but honest, I feel like they have hosted 8-75 hardcore music shows before. Like, wtf is this place?</p>

<h4><a href="http://www.yelp.com/biz/union-transfer-philadelphia%23hrid:xr0eNA56L-sdXnbm3Qbrog/src:self">Union Transfer </a></h4>

<p>1026 Spring Garden St
Philadelphia, PA 19123
(215) 232-2100</p>

<p>Category: <a href="http://www.yelp.com/c/philadelphia/musicvenues">Music Venues</a>
Neighborhoods: Spring Garden, Callowhill</p>

<p>First to Review
Was good as a spaghetti warehouse then it became the worst venue ever considering it’s never even had one godd<em>mn show. R5 really botched the job on this one: I went here a week ago to get spaghetti under really f</em>cking bright lights while listening to sh<em>tty radio pop music blasted in my dingus ears all f</em>cking night but it was closed because R5 bought it and R5 don’t know sh<em>t about spaghetti or warehouses. So I went back a week later to see a R5 show cuz it beats the sh</em>t out of radio pop blasting in your face while you’re trying to eat Pop’s Lasagna or whatever the godd*mn dish was called (RIP) but, lo and behold, no shows have ever been put on here so my first thought was that this place blows, gets one star, I’m hungry, break my life into pieces, this my last resort, yelp!, etc.</p>

<p>But then I read an exceptional piece of contemporary journalism in the Philadelphia Weekly, which I wish I could review on here but I can’t, and I learned that Union Transfer is the godd*amn best thing to ever happen to music in Philadelphia or anywhere else in the whole scheme of human history other than Bookspace. So the core of my consumer experience started off weak/terrible but is now and into the future just nothing short of Tiger Woods golf-quality, which is to say damn near perfect except when it sucks which is rare.</p>

<p>People thought this was:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Useful (1)</p></li>
<li><p>Funny (7)</p></li>
<li><p>Cool (1)</p></li>
</ul>


<h4><a href="http://www.yelp.com/biz/teris-philadelphia%23hrid:OlAUV90zhCIcisug_nEtmg/src:self">Teri’s </a></h4>

<p>1126 S 9th St
Philadelphia, PA 19147
(267) 761-9154</p>

<p>Categories: <a href="http://www.yelp.com/c/philadelphia/breakfast_brunch">Breakfast &amp; Brunch</a>, <a href="http://www.yelp.com/c/philadelphia/diners">Diners</a></p>

<p>A failed diner that found success through a very clever change of business plan: hiring freelance hipsters to turn it into a local hipster bar and it largely succeeded with flying colors and now it makes mad bank probably and vegan cheesesteaks and “tots.” They very wisely hired the (cool, nice) kinda older hip dude who bartends (or used to bartend, idk) at Bob and Barbara’s and Ray’s and now attractive young people are in there all the time and it’s fantastic. Very generous happy hour, impossible to talk/hear your friends any time of any night given that DJs are f<em>cking bombarding your ears, nice outdoor seating with heaters, and if you get really drunk there and get tired of having your ears destroyed and you feel like an idiot for eating so much seitan you can walk two doors down and do kareoke at Connie’s Ric Rac or just go home on Facebook because the internet is honestly, seriously the best place to express yourself ever invented, like it makes Guttenberg look like a f</em>cking piece of child. Feel like the older hip dude they hired should inherit the place when Teri, like, quits or whatever. Feel like he “did all the work,” and is totally completely responsible for the success of that place. Feel like hipsters are exploited by older people who just use hipsters for their ability to draw crowds and all the profits go to f*cking normies you would never even think about dancing/kissing/intimacy with if they ever actually went to the place you go to and yet you are willing to essentially pour money down their pants, like seriously wtf is wrong with us are we idiots or just drunk / love karaoke too much. But aside from their structural role in the exploitation of hipsters for profit, the owners/manager people are pretty nice cool/too and the older hip dude who is responsible for all the success is cool so this place is great all around.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fragments of automatic writing using Google Voice]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2011/08/02/fragments-of-automatic-writing-using-google-voice/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-02T21:42:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2011/08/02/fragments-of-automatic-writing-using-google-voice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://jmrphy.net/blog/2011/05/14/using-googles-transcription-service-as-a-universal-consciousness/">See here for a note on the theoretical basis of these fragments.</a></p>

<p>Wants me god I wanted to come down. I&rsquo;m not a dot frog concern, I can do anything I do every single thing I don’t even know how to speak but I do it anyway I can translate in French no I barely know the language but I’m a French translator hi… I think we’re working on it and I am the owner of my cell phone and I do not know anything.</p>

<p>Hello there are about 18 people living here right now depending on what you call people and living but … and if you are here or there from … better than doing research on the place … third a third third a friend of a friend.</p>

<p>yeah so one of the things about this place and living with so many people living in a big warehouse and all and radical politics is that if you want things that you will soon want, that it’s like, on this village… but unfortunately it’s rather in the middle of a ticket going like some lingering derek and it’s quite like describing them like american cars, noxious because it’s politically in cold, really truly and kind of like… there’s a lifestyle it is like, broke possibly, but diverse and kind of real possibly… Unlikely I can put very improbable kind of words to it… convergence of the people pass here but… when a lot of people in your house have radical aspirations and kinda radical positions but the actual reality of it… surprisingly incredulously thick and we’re still kind of only just beginning really to understand… for ourselves, the community… that’s what they said that’s kind of happening lately and it’s kinda been like pointing itself out… as early as I was calling you… yeah so that’s the… for room and we went okay so we did a little loop around there… we can just go this way then… city so… this is the bathroom this is the main bathroom … otherwise known as the green bathroom or the tiger bathroom about there this is the only shower … and some of it most of it but … no I mean, looks like the hook ups were here about when we first moved in we had to … yeah we used to pay some guy but recently some occupiers from new haven these kids we know they&rsquo;ve been living in last week or two and they’re often knowing well really handy and in addition they’re fucking rad anyway so we&rsquo;re thinking hoping they&rsquo;re going to stay.</p>

<p>Hi some kind of anyways explanation just drinking a big gas energy drink do 1 jumping jack that&rsquo;s all you need especially if … exporting your time where the work precedents checking with you.</p>

<p>Lovely lady might suck I&rsquo;m gonna really wanna mix between … saint bernard and talk hey docks we&rsquo;re sending our image calling to … which obviously and then it would not look I&rsquo;m even I got those I make give me … a great game in the scene from … meeting love just … gonna since you good … please hey hopefully that lady is leaving at 1030 at order dot com.</p>

<p>What we&rsquo;ve been there now I 1 … and like the 3 is only been there for I think this is like berger for we&rsquo;re just not serve you something like that anyway I like to hear you heard about the rate like great marco like go within like the kind of the report but he&rsquo;s like he&rsquo;s it&rsquo;s not the worst and like you know the now with my mom would like come in … hey like talk to you much hey jim like too crazy at work for most people so I like it but hi I just realize it&rsquo;s anne I just wanted to see that that would be all he does not know kinda handle crazy like crazy because I like what about things like you have later yes yeah well he didn&rsquo;t want to … like I can do anything please give me a ring freaking thing I&rsquo;m stalking you turned it let&rsquo;s catch up okay I don&rsquo;t what would you julie hi meet hey.</p>

<p>We are all guilty we are all guilty but the only thing we&rsquo;ve ever done that&rsquo;s dangerous the only crime we ever committed hey is unused potential, the shell, being ignored or pressed hey all we are dead and wait and we&rsquo;re dead space.</p>

<p>Hello that … hi this is … because he</p>

<p>With this wine I feel like I am part of that all right now I feel like I I feel absolutely sound into it would be easier I feel like I would go to like to go to sleep and 1 second wasn’t already…</p>

<p>Well I can&rsquo;t believe we did it … we did it we could somebody…</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
