<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: note | Justin Murphy]]></title>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/categories/note/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-22T16:00:25+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[j.murphy@soton.ac.uk]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Daily schedule for weekdays (the only legitimate drill-sergeant is autonomous self-discipline)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/12/31/weekday-schedule/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-31T19:01:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/12/31/weekday-schedule</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Below is the daily schedule I will try to follow every weekday while the university is in session. I’ve designed this in a way I think is realistic with respect to my strengths, weaknesses, and priorities, but also as ruthless as possible with respect to my worst demons.</p>

<p><strong>5:55am &ndash; 6:00am.</strong> Wake up and get out of bed immediately. No snooze, no lying around. You’re typically slow to get up after waking because you sometimes dread the day ahead, but this is only <em>because</em> you’re lack of self-discipline makes your days harder and more confusing than they need to be. Break this spell now by just getting the fuck up as soon as the damn sound goes off. Don’t think, just do it. Save your thinking for the thinking that matters, otherwise recall Rousseau: the thinking human is a depraved animal. Don’t be a sick animal, just get the fuck up.</p>

<p><strong>6:00am &ndash; 6:30am.</strong> Go directly to the yoga mat which will already be laid out from the night before; do yoga and meditate for 30 minutes. You always thought yoga was stupid and you’re highly self-conscious about doing bourgeois shit, but you have to face the fact that you’re a paranoid neurotic in the undeniably western, capitalist, egomaniacal mold and that this HAS TO STOP. Yes, it’s privileged and bourgeois as hell to even have the time to do yoga, and it’s evil that this is so, but you need spiritual and physical self-care to make yourself less evil, so you must not be ashamed of doing yoga regularly. Shit works! It chills you the fuck out, and you’re only doing it to become a more balanced, more lucid, more whole person, and therefore more loving toward friends and comrades (less self-obsessed, less patriarchal, less likely to aggressively misfire in complex social situations) and more firmly and militantly opposed to the status quo at all the right times and places. Don’t be paralyzed by shame or self-consciousness just because you’re doing something unfortunately associated with apolitical complacency, trust in yourself knowing that you’re doing it for the right reasons. Also, crucially, remember that all the excuses you make for skipping this are always themselves the toxic ableist hyper-productivity myths that you need to resist. So every time you think of an excuse to skip, realize that that itself is a reason to make sure you do this.</p>

<p><strong>6:30am &ndash; 7:00am.</strong> Prepare coffee and a small healthy breakfast. Listen to public radio, water plants if necessary, tidy the flat a little bit. Remember you don’t have to make the whole flat perfect in any one effort. This thought is what makes you put this off altogether! Just do a few things to this effect to fill the half hour. Remember you’re doing a few easy things frequently so that you <em>won’t have to do</em> big hard cleaning sessions.</p>

<p><strong>7:00am-9:00am.</strong> Read a book related to the project you’re working on (this has always been your best way to get into working) and as soon as the coffee and your thoughts unite, go to the computer and open up the one particular, specifically academic, professionally-respectable project which you&rsquo;ll do at this time everyday until that project is complete. This is huge for you, your biggest demon. You always want to write freely and creatively and blog and tweet and rabble-rouse, but that’s what you’re already good at and it’s already what you have plenty of in the hopper. What you <em>really need</em> to do is get your academic articles published. You have several good articles in various stages, you <em>need</em> to just finish them and send them out. You find these articles alienating because you want to be able to write whatever the fuck you want and feel. But you know you want (and need) to publish good academic articles because you know that nobody will ever give a fuck about whatever else you think unless you can dance their waltz as well. And of course, these are the articles you were hired to write, so you have to just fucking write them because this is a great job as far as jobs go and you want to keep it. Also, let’s be frank: you don’t work on these articles enough because you’re insecure and scared as shit that you’re not actually smart enough to finish them well and publish them well. But remember, that’s just because you’re young and you don’t have any academic publications yet and since you’re ambitious all of your papers swim a bit beyond your depth so yea, you’re fucking scared of them! But that’s bullshit, you were smart enough to start them so you’re smart enough to finish them. The only way you’ll <em>actually</em> fail to live up to them is if you’re so afraid that you don’t commit to them. Thus, if you commit to working on them at a bare minimum from 7am-9am every single weekday, you’ll get fully back into them and probably <em>want</em> to work on them more. But even if you <em>only</em> do this, it will be enough to bring at least 3 of these articles to publication within at least a year, I would think. Remember, these will be <em>actual, real, focused</em> work hours so you’ll actually get shit done.</p>

<p>DO NOT even think about opening Tweetdeck, Feedly, Instapaper, or Facebook. DO NOT even think about opening one of your autonomous projects. No music either. You are afraid of silence and the terror of your own thoughts, but you mustn&rsquo;t be. Also, this period must be actual execution of steps toward the completion of one of these articles. The point is that it has to be actual writing or editing or analysis and NOT organizational, contemplative, or speculative bullshit.</p>

<p><strong>9:00am to 12:00pm.</strong> If teaching, teach. Otherwise, you can continue doing actual execution of the 7-9am research work, OR you can during these hours if you wish to, switch focus and work on your autonomous projects or above-and-beyond teaching work, or blogging/tweeting and other web stuff, the only requirement is that it’s an intentional project-based thing which you state explicitly at 9am as your goal until 12pm and NOT passive timesucking bullshit like commenting on some tweet or FB thread, or even READING twitter or FB, or some other idiotic pastime of yours, such as reading other people’s CVs (why would you EVER do that? well, the answer is insecurity and hero-worship, of course, which can only ever lead to narcissistic/egotistical replication of the hero at best or, at worst, a failure which does not even have the benefit of being an integral failure but would be defined by someone else—the only truly bad kind of failure). This period will be truly free time, but free in the hard Sartrean sense which must be active and responsible for itself.</p>

<p><strong>12:00pm to 1:00pm.</strong> Eat lunch, relax in some good way, like make plans to chat with someone, go for a walk, and/or read a book or newspaper. If flagging, maybe lie down for 15 minutes or if on campus turn off the lights and close your eyes for a little bit.</p>

<p><strong>1:00pm to 5:00pm.</strong> Take care of all your various daily affairs, work responsibilities, quotidian online tasks. Start by checking to-do list and always always work directly from there. If teaching, teach. But also: grading, emails, and teaching prep. You never <em>want</em> to do any of these things because you’re lazy and selfish, and you think you’re precious ideas and writings are the only thing that matter in the world. Well, get over that, because it’s not true!</p>

<p>You’ve already spent a really nice amount of time working on the actual projects of your life. You now must take care of the various remaining work responsibilities. You have to accept that you have a real job with real responsibilities. But take comfort and energy and even inspiration from the absolute fact that this is likely the least alienating and most empowering job for you on the planet right now, so you should be quite happy to do everything you need to do for it. Also be extremely self-aware, humble, and grateful that you <em>already</em> took 3-5 hours that morning to work on semi-to-fully-autonomous projects while almost all people on the planet have 0 hours per day to work on such projects. At the same time, of course, you must constantly turn this self-awareness into rage and opposition against a status quo which makes it possible, but you can’t let this simmer as vague guilt or self-loathing which will simply demobilize you from ever achieving anything against this status quo. At 1:00pm, the philosopher of daybreak puts away their dancing pen and harnesses their awareness of privilege into the daily humility of <em>taking care of business</em>, as grotesque as that sounds, because the truly rebellious will know they themselves are not yet better than the affairs of this world.</p>

<p><strong>5:00pm to 7:00pm.</strong> Prepare a good and healthy dinner, eat, and try to relax a bit, again in some specific intentional way to avoid “relaxing” in some ultimately stressful way (like reading twitter). Pack food for tomorrow if necessary, Like after lunch, lie down or close your eyes for a bit if you’re flagging.</p>

<p><strong>7:00pm to 8:00pm.</strong> Tie up whatever loose ends you need to tie up. This might be working more on your articles or doing extra teaching work that has arisen, whatever. This is open time for you to do whatever most needs to be done at this time, including relaxing if that’s what you really need. Don’t be afraid to do that if that’s what you need. Be happy knowing that if you’re really sticking to your schedule from 6:00am until then, then you’ve actually accomplished more that day than you ever typically do in a day. The only requirement is that you can’t go online without a specific purpose, this is a notoriously dangerous time for you to have hours stolen by the internet. Let’s not beat around the bush: you regularly waste as much as 2 whole hours a day, often at this time, literally doing nothing other than reading idle and sterile “debates” on twitter and Facebook while learning nothing and getting your own most radical and powerful thoughts and visions confused/distracted/shaken by 140-character phantoms. At this time, if you aren’t busy with priorities, you can read books or blog feeds or saved articles on Instapaper or even check in on family or friends on FB, just absolutely no passive twitter or FB reading.</p>

<p>(The whole 5pm-8pm block can also be used, alternatively, for things like having beers with colleagues, or maybe seeing a movie and eating out instead of cooking, whatever, but only once a week or so at most.)</p>

<p><strong>8:00pm to 9:00pm.</strong> Very similar to 7pm-8pm but become more aware of sleep and of the next day coming up. Become more aware that you’re an animal in a nest. Tidy the flat a bit. Bathe or groom if necessary. No radio or podcasts now. Look over schedule for the next day.</p>

<p><strong>9:00pm to 9:30pm.</strong> Meditate/yoga and leave the mat out so it’s natural to do this again first thing in the morning.</p>

<p><strong>9:30pm.</strong> Get into bed, even if you’re not tired. Read a novel or stories or a biography, as long as it’s on paper and it’s not theory or social science. Turn lights off anytime you start to get sleepy. Feel free to write notes or aphorisms or even a letter to a family or friend, but avoid screens unless necessary and nothing too hard or intense.</p>

<p><strong>11:00pm.</strong> Lights off no matter what, whether you’re sleepy or not. If you don’t feel sleepy, it doesn’t matter because you can’t go to bed any later than this if you are going to keep to your plans the next day. Recall that sleeping isn’t something that comes over you but something you choose to do by taking control of breathing and your over-hyper mind; that you need it and want it because you want to have a good day tomorrow. Remember sleep is all about breathing and by this time you simply must go to sleep.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Untitled]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/10/13/cupcakes-taste-like-violence/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-13T22:15:18+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/10/13/cupcakes-taste-like-violence</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>“Cupcakes taste like violence.” &ndash; Ahuviya Harel, at the Ox</p>

<br><br><br><br><br><br>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hip pouch (red square solidarity edition)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/05/27/23883065976/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-27T21:34:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/05/27/23883065976</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Ox just got a gnarly industrial-strength sewing machine so this week I decided to make my debut in fashion design.</p>

<p>Hat tip goes to <a href="http://rhls.com/about.html">Ruffeo Hearts Lil Snotty</a>, from whom I got the pattern <a href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=1&amp;ved=0CGsQFjAA&amp;url=http://www.rhls.com/threadbanger/fannypack.pdf&amp;ei=iXnCT5KCFujG6AGeipSuCg&amp;usg=AFQjCNHyjzo-g5BE7flpB1rrY43PpfcfmA&amp;sig2=UJOrPRPgYAtdA_T6Q0gC4Q">here</a>. As a business their politics and aesthetics are not quite mine&mdash;ultimately they do seem to be selling the false freedoms of frivolity, nostalgia, and the possibility of an ethical life under contemporary capitalism&mdash;but as humans they seem pretty rad (anti-exploitation, &ldquo;anti-fashion&rdquo;, DIY, they closed down for May Day, etc.). Taking some liberties with the design and having neither a shred of experience nor skill in sewing, I feel like my version is sufficiently DIY-looking to at least signal a theoretical rejection of the status quo. Surveying my career as a fashion designer, I feel like my intention over the past six days or so has been to blend the prevailing hipster aesthetic with the, uh, &ldquo;militant anticapitalist aesthetic&rdquo; or something. I think by &ldquo;militant anticapitalist aesthetic&rdquo; I mean militant anticapitalist &ldquo;colors&rdquo; and &ldquo;rhetoric&rdquo; maybe.</p>

<p>In fact, it&rsquo;s a fucking mess of goddam strings sticking out of every nook and crevice in the bloody thing but I feel like that is just my signature style as a fashion designer. Everything I make will just have a million goddamn strings sticking out of every bloody fold and cranny, not on purpose but because that&rsquo;s just my style or something, i.e. what happened this time and will probably keep happening because I feel no desire to learn how to avoid that happening. I can&rsquo;t believe sewing works considering it&rsquo;s just a million little idiotic strings going every which way. Of course that works, so obvious.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s made of standard canvas from a bookbag, which I lined with vinyl to make it uh, possibly water resistant. Incidentally, the vinyl came from the Occupy Philly May Day &ldquo;STRIKE&rdquo; banner! It has belt loops in the back to string my belt through. I added a little D-ring, why? Fuck if I know!l Looks useful, why the fuck not? So easy, should have added a goddamn can opener while I was at it. I also threw in a few pencil holders, a little pouch on the inside, and a red square for the historically unprecedented, spontaneous, indefinite <em>manifestations</em> of hundreds of thousands of Québécois underway right now.</p>

<p><img src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_m4p316Twy31qz9517.jpg" alt="" /><img src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_m4p31yHtjy1qz9517.jpg" alt="" /><img src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_m4p36ijxKb1qz9517.jpg" alt="" />
<img src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_m4p372VTco1qz9517.jpg" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[local weather philadelphia]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/04/28/21940232210/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-28T00:27:59+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/04/28/21940232210</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>General Strike Google Bomb for Occupy Philly</p>

<p>Link: <a href="http://www.facebook.com/events/384999524851887">local weather philadelphia</a></p>

<br><br><br><br><br><br>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open letter to family members on Facebook]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2011/09/03/family-on-facebook/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-03T19:43:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2011/09/03/family-on-facebook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dear Family Members on Facebook,<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>I don’t think you quite understand this yet, but certain formerly separated and once demarcated segments of social space have now, fairly suddenly, collapsed. The transcendental social space into which these separate spaces have collapsed is called Facebook. This collapse has had several interesting, beneficial, and much-discussed implications. It has also had several less-discussed implications—or, at least, implications to which nobody has yet drawn your attention—implications which are, incidentally, making my own life rather difficult. Because there are likely millions of you, beyond the family members of the present author, who do not yet understand these implications, the present author has appointed himself spokesperson for every other young-adult, often urban, “alt”-minded person whose life similarly is being ruined by this recent collapse of social space. I write you, we write you, because we love you.</p>

<p>*</p>

<p>&lsquo;To begin, an extended simile-cum-metaphor. Family members, please try to empathize: Shifting from a college-students-only Facebook to the relatively unfettered virtual commons it has become today is like bringing your grandmother and little brother to a really great dance party with a lot of really good-looking peers; you do not get the best of both worlds, you get neither world. You just stand there not dancing and not drinking because granny has a bad hip and you spent all your money on Shirley Temples for little Johnny, but you also don&rsquo;t have fun with your grandmother or little Johnny because the music is too loud, all you really care about is getting laid, and you, granny, and Johnny have nothing to talk about, anyway. But it&rsquo;s even more awkward for you because little Johnny who is new to dance parties doesn&rsquo;t understand that 12-year-old boys should not rub their private areas on girls at a dance party his own grandmother and brother are attending, or any dance party for that matter; and granny does not realize that she is a little too old for taking glamour photos of herself in the reflection of a bathroom mirror. Then you kind of just ask yourself how the hell things got to be like that but you don&rsquo;t leave (or carefully rig your privacy settings) because what kind of self-respecting person would leave or shut out an old lady and a 12-year-old at a bar by themselves?</p>

<p>*</p>

<p>Dear 14-year-old little sister, you cannot just say “fuck that,” and “what the fuck” all over the place as if you are giggling with your girlfriends in the privacy of your middle-school bathroom stalls. Given how many of our fucking relatives we are both friends with on Facebook, we are effectively sitting at the fucking Thanksgiving table. Also, you can be forgiven for constantly posting terrible song lyrics in your youthful vigor, but when these lyrics are very thinly-veiled allusions to the sexual deed itself, this is just unacceptable. I understand your yearnings, but please, sublimate; in the long run, this will get you to your goal more effectively, anyway. Finally, about all of the self-portraits in which you do that puckered-lips thing. When and how did young women first get the idea that this is somehow universally flattering and photogenicizing. I can’t reiterate how much I (we) love you, but this is just intolerable. Facebook is making you self-obsessed and it worries me and these kinds of images are excruciating to observe in my news feed.</p>

<p>Dear 18-year-old little brother, I know you mean well but my young-adult friends think your language is what they would call “racist.” For instance, a lot of people find the “n-word” hateful and unacceptable in public discourse because, historically, it has been entwined with the ruthless domination and oppression of black people by white people like you and me. Neither leaving off the “r” nor the possibly true fact that indeed you have black friends ever makes it socially acceptable to use such language. I do not know about possible private social groupings among young white kids in which this kind of language is perceived to be normal or acceptable, but on Facebook you are a Netizen of the World.</p>

<p>Dear 22-year-old little sister, as you get older you might be thinking more about your personal brand as represented on websites such as Facebook. Your personal brand consists in the image or value that the rest of the world associates with your web presence, what you uniquely offer them. Your personal brand might be too edgy or idiosyncratic for me to even understand it—maybe I’m just disconnected from your personal audience—but I do not think it will translate well into more cosmopolitan milieus. For instance, take a status update from last week:</p>

<blockquote><p>New oatmeal from mcdonalds = bangin</p></blockquote>

<p>This might be true, but oatmeal, McDonald’s, and the word “bangin,” will often be perceived as unsavory content for microblogging when taken separately; in one positive chain of equivalences containing nothing other than an indication of the oatmeal’s novelty, this will rarely if ever travel well, beyond your personal network, through the World-Wide Web.</p>

<p>Dear Aunts and Uncles, I have been living away from “home” for seven years now. Please try to think about how this might affect my use of language with respect to my nuclear family, and also think about how I might wish to portray myself to my peers and potential sexual partners. For instance, you recently wrote the following on my wall:</p>

<blockquote><p>Merry Christmas! We left a present under the tree for you, did you get it? Ask  Grandma and Grandpa to give it to you!</p></blockquote>

<p>Thanks again for the gift, but with respect to my social-networking life, this was more of a Trojan horse. I suppose many people call their Grandmother and Grandfather by the colloquial form you use here, but this post, minor as it seems, is like shrapnel in the stomach of my own personal brand (which is, if you care to know, “intellectually austere and mature but willing to be calculatedly silly because I don’t ‘give a fuck,’ also somewhat withdrawn but unpredictably forthright when I want to be.”) I see my parents and their parents very rarely. This signals to the world how mature and independent I am, but when you refer to my grandparents as “Grandma” and “Grandpa” it is like a denial-of-service attack on the virtual dissemination of this mature independence.</p>

<p>Love always,
Young-adult alt-types on Facebook</p>

<p>PS: I really am going to get the dates of all your birthdays onto a calendar somewhere. Really, I’m going to do this soon. Thanks for understanding.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Originally published by Thought Catalog (thoughtcatalog.com) on September 2, 2011. I’ve since made some slight edits because I wasn’t entirely comfortable with how I originally tried to address the issue of racism. In the original piece, I wrote out the full version of the “n-word” in scare quotes because I thought at the time that so long as I was invoking it to help other white people understand why they shouldn’t mess with it, that it was appropriate to write it out in full. In my current view, I have no idea if that was “right” or “wrong,” but as I’ve become more attuned to racism, I would rather not put that word into print. So I edited that accordingly (December 20, 2013).<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
