<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: theory | Justin Murphy]]></title>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/categories/theory/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-12T22:52:31+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[There are more than enough hours in the day]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/09/15/there-are-more-than-enough-hours-in-the-day/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-15T16:46:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/09/15/there-are-more-than-enough-hours-in-the-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The popular refrain that &ldquo;there aren&rsquo;t enough hours in the day&rdquo; is an interesting departure from the long and storied political and rhetorical battle to <em>objectively</em> decrease the hours of the working day. It is an extraordinary gauge of our political pacification that when so many people have such a hard time meeting a pervasive social and economic expectation, we would sooner <em>ask for an extension</em> of the expectation than its abolition.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The hatred of freedom]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/08/31/the-hatred-of-freedom/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-31T20:07:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/08/31/the-hatred-of-freedom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The truth is that most people do not want other people to flourish. We all support a general idea of everyone being freer but we tend to feel threatened whenever anyone <em>in particular</em> meets with an increase of freedom. Not long after, we begin to hate them for it if we are not welcome or able to enjoy in the proceeds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[God has not died, and it is we atheists who have resurrected him]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2010/07/10/god-has-not-died/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-10T21:13:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2010/07/10/god-has-not-died</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s not just the rise of religioius fundamentalism, it&rsquo;s more horrific than that. The loose cult we know as atheism, the ecclesiastics of which are well known, are the real defenders of the old faith, the old faith that somewhere the sliding stops, the faith that somewhere there exists a true <em>point de capiton</em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The problem with drugs as counterculture]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2010/07/04/the-problem-with-drugs-as-counterculture/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-04T20:57:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2010/07/04/the-problem-with-drugs-as-counterculture</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sure, Benjamin used hashish and mescaline; the hippies used pot, acid, and any number of other drugs. There are many examples of visionaries who used drugs. But today we have neither the erudition and discipline of a Benjamin, nor the capacity for love which the hippies still had. All we have is increasing atomism and incessant economic dislocations and disruptions. Contemporary recreational drugs, consequently, are misunderstood. Recreational drugs are still often seen as on the side of social change, a vague protest vote, from the critical and liberal-minded individuals opposed to outdated and provincial conservatives.</p>

<p>But the truth is that drugs do not transport one from a square and normal world to a place more fluid and free: the status quo is such an historical aberration, such an abnormal and inhuman disequilibrium, that recreational drug use typically quenches the <em>conservative</em> thirst to slow down incessant and unsettling change, to create an oasis of stability where the world might have a moment to make sense to itself.</p>

<p>Thus, it is an absurd ideological inversion only a capitalist society is capable of, that recreational drug cultures see themselves as on the side of change and their lawmakers&mdash;who in fact preside over daily planetary dislocations&mdash;as lacking flexibility.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
