<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></title>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-11T11:48:18+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notes on walter lippmann]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2014/02/11/notes-on-walter-lippmann/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-11T11:46:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2014/02/11/notes-on-walter-lippmann</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>&lt;!DOCTYPE html></p>

<!-- saved from url=(0014)about:internet -->


<p><html>
<head>
<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8"/></p>

<p><title>Thoughts on Walter Lippmann</title></p>





<!-- MathJax scripts -->


<script type="text/javascript" src="https://c328740.ssl.cf1.rackcdn.com/mathjax/2.0-latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML">
</script>


<p></head></p>

<p><body></p>

<h5>Thoughts on Walter Lippmann</h5>




<p>pp 6. Lippmann writes as if the antagonism determined by national geo-politics is more real than the lived relations of human beings. He thinks in all honesty that they were mistaken to have been acting as friends!</p>




<p>But isn&#39;t it far more reasonable to say that indeed they were friends, despite the war, because they knew nothing of any reasons to oppose one another? And that it was only the media, which acted as a sort of informational tentacle of the state, which informed them that they should be opposed to one another? The news delivery functioned as a sort of order, and here Lippman testifies to this insofar as he literally attributes the messages of national war propaganda more reality than lived relations.</p>




<p>Isn&#39;t this really extraordinary? He suggests that there is a real world outside and merely a picture in our heads, but is it not far more reasonable to say that the world we live with the people around is the world outside and newspaper reports of national state propaganda are \( quite literally! \) only pictures?</p>




<p>We should question what permits him such confidence to suggest the opposite, despite how absurd this is.</p>




<p>p.15: One can think of the fidelity of news reports as a distribution. we tend to think of it as a distribution from left to right politically, but the more interesting distinction to me is the distribution across which a report locates systemic institutional causes or an ideological picture of the status quo which benefits both sides of the status quo spectrum.</p>




<p>p.18: Today, it seems to me that we certainly all live in a variously different world in no small part to the explosion of media choice, but the political issue here is very different than what Lippman identified in the 1920s. It is not that the rich and poor live in different worlds in which they believe the other to be an enemy, it is that they live in different worlds in which they do not see each other as enemies. This strikes me as the remarkable fact today, and it would have to be determined how this came about. One might hypothesis that the market&#39;s explosion of media choice and advertising&#39;s ability to create various specific identity niches solved the &ldquo;class war&rdquo; by simply removing any common ground required for even having any antagonism whatsoever.</p>




<p>p.26: what is interesting about Lippman is that he says the press cannot be expected to supply the truth about the world, because they are too much determined by precisely the political forces which distort our image of the world. </p>


<p></body></p>

<p></html></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The question of revolution is not romantic, it is unavoidable]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2014/02/06/the-question-of-revolution-is-unavoidable/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-06T16:12:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2014/02/06/the-question-of-revolution-is-unavoidable</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If I insist on the revolutionary position, it is not to insist on the dichotomy between revolution and reform. Most of us today will agree with Gorz that there exists a class of <em>revolutionary reforms</em>, at which point the relevant distinction becomes the distinction between revolutionary reforms and reformist reforms. Today, Nancy Fraser suggests the critical distinction is between &ldquo;system-conforming&rdquo; changes and &ldquo;system-transforming&rdquo; changes, but it seems to me that the long-standing theoretical and practical difficulty remains the same: which types of projects (individual or collective) <em>effectively</em> oppose capitalism and push society toward justice, and which types of projects (whether through mystification, co-optation, or defeat) merely improve capitalism for some at the price of renouncing the system-level opposition which would be the maximally true, coherent, and just position.</p>

<p>To my mind, this is the essence of the revolutionary position: To believe that the organisation of the world&rsquo;s institutions are unjust, to see empirically that a key feature of these institutions is precisely that they offer particular groups small gains in return for their renunciation of system-level opposition, to therefore locate <em>this precise mechanism</em> as the essential and perhaps only mechanism which is able to maintain such massive worldwide system-level injustice, and finally to assume the theoretical and practical position <em>to never renounce system-level opposition in exchange for any particular gain less than the absolute system-level transformations which are required for justice</em>, no matter how <em>relatively</em> transformative such gains might be.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Because of the almost primordial or, in any event, perennial quality of this tension and its unavoidable need for resolution in any theoretically defensible political project, I see no way that any political theory today can innocently elide the question of revolution. I do not say that any political theory today must be explicitly revolutionary in any specific sense. I say only that distinctions between &ldquo;system-conforming&rdquo; and &ldquo;system-transforming&rdquo; beg the crucial question which will always arise for those who agree to pursue system-transforming collective action: when the state, the market, and/or the thousands of institutions such as the university (defined by irrevocable cognitive and material allegiances to the state and market) offer us a particular &ldquo;transformation&rdquo; on condition that we demobilise just enough to not threaten the equilibrium of the institutional arrangement as such, <em>should we accept that transformation or not?</em></p>

<p>That is, after individuals and groups choose &ldquo;system-transforming&rdquo; rather than &ldquo;system-conforming&rdquo; agendas, what are the conditions under which it is justified for them to demobilise their system-transformative demands in exchange for some political victory which improves the world but is less than what they see as a fully adequate transformation of the system? For <em>this</em> is the perennial dilemma with which all system-transforming political projects constantly struggle, and indeed it is this dilemma to which the very notion of an anti-capitalist (system-level) perspective is supposed to counter.</p>

<p>Finally, while I zealously affirm that any defensible revolutionary position will not only be anti-capitalist but also feminist, anti-racist, ecologically sustainable, and inclusive of many other human differences which &ldquo;revolutionaries&rdquo; have a long history of betraying, in no way do these inclusions obviate the question of revolution. Indeed, it is precisely because gender, race, and ecological as well as class struggles so urgently require truly system-level institutional transformations, that it is all the more important for us to maintain what is specific about the question of revolution and the meaning of the revolutionary position.</p>

<p>No matter how naively romantic the revolutionary position rings to our contemporary ears, it&rsquo;s naiveté and romanticism is only a function of the merely contingent strength of the current status quo, and moreover our aversion to this seeming romanticism of the revolutionary position is itself merely the cognitive inheritance of a politics now more than ever defined by collaboration with injustice rather than resistance to it. Perhaps the meaning of the revolutionary position is indeed nothing more than an integral naiveté, but on the wager that real integrity to a truth is exactly the most emancipatory political force in the world. And perhaps the most dangerous romanticism existing today is the notion that humans have suddenly been absolved of having to decide whether they will negotiate    with oppressive institutions or overthrow them.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>This phrasing is purposely agnostic about what exactly constitutes justice or what any ultimate institutional configuration should look like (or how this would be determined). This is because, for the moment, I am trying to sketch what is essential and specific about the revolutionary position as inclusively as possible with respect to any particular vision of political justice. Thus, the only essential premises with which one has to agree here are: 1) that there currently exist system-level injustices in the arrangement of institutions, and 2) that we can at least in principle admit the possibility of a globally just arrangement of institutions. One does not even have to agree that capitalism is the name of the currently unjust institutions, to see how a commitment to system-level injustice necessarily implicates one at least in the <em>question</em> of revolution.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[System for managing student course submissions using free web services (proof of concept)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2014/01/23/a-system-for-managing-student-course-submissions-using-free-web-services/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-23T21:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2014/01/23/a-system-for-managing-student-course-submissions-using-free-web-services</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In order to bypass the criminally profligate corporate education contractors who charge universities extortionate prices for almost useless products such as Blackboard and Turnitin, I&rsquo;ve devised a system for managing student course submissions and record keeping throughout the semester, using all free web services. Not as if these free web services live on moral high-ground, but at least they let us dodge these stationary bandits charging rents at the revolving door between universities and the corporate sector.</p>

<p>With this system, students can blog publicly as much as they&rsquo;d like, all of their work is collected and organized automatically, and the instructor can grade submissions quickly, easily, <em>and</em> anonymously, all in one place (in the cloud). Here&rsquo;s how it works.</p>

<p><img src="http://tardis1.tinygrab.com/grabs/3db0911c71468d4f7b8927bd141baeacf08bc2dde1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>All students have a personal blog using one of the major blogging platforms. The RSS feed associated with each blog is channeled into one master RSS feed using Feed.Informer.com. This master feed is then run through IFTTT to distribute every student blog post into two different formats in my private Google Drive. First, every single student blog post is logged into a Google Spreadsheet capturing everything about the post (the content, the url, the student&rsquo;s name, and the time of the post). This is the master spreadsheet. But the critical course submissions are also distributed into individual text files which do <em>not</em> include the student&rsquo;s name. This is achieved by simply having students tag their critical submissions with some specific tag, and telling IFTTT to create the anonymized text file only for posts with that tag.</p>

<p><strong>Proof of concept.</strong> To show that this works, scales reasonably, and is consistent with anonymous grading, I set up a pilot &ldquo;course&rdquo; using about 15 popular political blogs as my &ldquo;student&rdquo; blogs. Then I let the system run for about 6 days. Below, I demonstrate how I set it up and how this system can reliably deliver more than 2,000 blog posts from various blogs for quick, easy, and secure grading.</p>

<p>First, use Feed.Informer.com to turn all of your students&#8217; blogs into one master RSS feed. This is basically just merging all of the blogs into one data stream.</p>

<p><img src="http://tardis1.tinygrab.com/grabs/3db0911c7194daed018d11923956d4e50188172fe1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>You give it many RSS feeds, and then it gives you one RSS feed merging them all.</p>

<p><img src="http://tardis1.tinygrab.com/grabs/3db0911c71a70226a46f3f3b081f724dd3b619d319.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Next, use IFTTT to make two &ldquo;recipes.&rdquo; The first one sends every new entry on a specified RSS feed (you give it your master feed) to a new row in some specified spreadsheet in your Google Drive. Then a second recipe sends <em>only</em> items in the RSS master feed matching some specified tag into their own anonymous Google docs in your Google Drive. You can put them in their own folder to keep things tidy. In this example, only blog posts tagged &ldquo;politics&rdquo; are filed into their own anonymous docs. In practice, you would just tell students to tag their critical assignments (mid-term or final-term essays, for instance) with any specified tag of your choosing, and enter that into IFTTT instead of &ldquo;politics.&rdquo;</p>

<p><img src="http://tardis1.tinygrab.com/grabs/3db0911c71ea24157ead5402a2ef83fffaa7b38c28.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Then, after six days, I have more than 2,000 student blog posts. And a few hundred &ldquo;mid-term essays&rdquo; ready for anonymous grading. After reading the anonymous documents, you can just find the associated title in the spreadsheet and enter a grade. Or just visit the anonymous link from the text document, to see who wrote it and then enter your grades wherever else you might be keeping them. Regardless, the entire written output of your entire class is all collected in one place.</p>

<p><img src="http://tardis1.tinygrab.com/grabs/3db0911c716062ab1087ff050c05017876eee8502c.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a spreadsheet. It will automatically make an additional spreadsheet after any spreadsheet reaches 2000 rows.</p>

<p><img src="http://tardis1.tinygrab.com/grabs/3db0911c716bc8d95d8e915f87cc70c05380b3d070.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Example of an anonymous Google doc.</p>

<p><img src="http://tardis1.tinygrab.com/grabs/3db0911c713d93fd329f14cdd9ebdf136012686b47.png" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Daily schedule for weekdays (the only legitimate drill-sergeant is autonomous self-discipline)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/12/31/weekday-schedule/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-31T19:01:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/12/31/weekday-schedule</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Below is the daily schedule I will try to follow every weekday while the university is in session. I’ve designed this in a way I think is realistic with respect to my strengths, weaknesses, and priorities, but also as ruthless as possible with respect to my worst demons.</p>

<p><strong>5:55am &ndash; 6:00am.</strong> Wake up and get out of bed immediately. No snooze, no lying around. You’re typically slow to get up after waking because you sometimes dread the day ahead, but this is only <em>because</em> you’re lack of self-discipline makes your days harder and more confusing than they need to be. Break this spell now by just getting the fuck up as soon as the damn sound goes off. Don’t think, just do it. Save your thinking for the thinking that matters, otherwise recall Rousseau: the thinking human is a depraved animal. Don’t be a sick animal, just get the fuck up.</p>

<p><strong>6:00am &ndash; 6:30am.</strong> Go directly to the yoga mat which will already be laid out from the night before; do yoga and meditate for 30 minutes. You always thought yoga was stupid and you’re highly self-conscious about doing bourgeois shit, but you have to face the fact that you’re a paranoid neurotic in the undeniably western, capitalist, egomaniacal mold and that this HAS TO STOP. Yes, it’s privileged and bourgeois as hell to even have the time to do yoga, and it’s evil that this is so, but you need spiritual and physical self-care to make yourself less evil, so you must not be ashamed of doing yoga regularly. Shit works! It chills you the fuck out, and you’re only doing it to become a more balanced, more lucid, more whole person, and therefore more loving toward friends and comrades (less self-obsessed, less patriarchal, less likely to aggressively misfire in complex social situations) and more firmly and militantly opposed to the status quo at all the right times and places. Don’t be paralyzed by shame or self-consciousness just because you’re doing something unfortunately associated with apolitical complacency, trust in yourself knowing that you’re doing it for the right reasons. Also, crucially, remember that all the excuses you make for skipping this are always themselves the toxic ableist hyper-productivity myths that you need to resist. So every time you think of an excuse to skip, realize that that itself is a reason to make sure you do this.</p>

<p><strong>6:30am &ndash; 7:00am.</strong> Prepare coffee and a small healthy breakfast. Listen to public radio, water plants if necessary, tidy the flat a little bit. Remember you don’t have to make the whole flat perfect in any one effort. This thought is what makes you put this off altogether! Just do a few things to this effect to fill the half hour. Remember you’re doing a few easy things frequently so that you <em>won’t have to do</em> big hard cleaning sessions.</p>

<p><strong>7:00am-9:00am.</strong> Read a book related to the project you’re working on (this has always been your best way to get into working) and as soon as the coffee and your thoughts unite, go to the computer and open up the one particular, specifically academic, professionally-respectable project which you&rsquo;ll do at this time everyday until that project is complete. This is huge for you, your biggest demon. You always want to write freely and creatively and blog and tweet and rabble-rouse, but that’s what you’re already good at and it’s already what you have plenty of in the hopper. What you <em>really need</em> to do is get your academic articles published. You have several good articles in various stages, you <em>need</em> to just finish them and send them out. You find these articles alienating because you want to be able to write whatever the fuck you want and feel. But you know you want (and need) to publish good academic articles because you know that nobody will ever give a fuck about whatever else you think unless you can dance their waltz as well. And of course, these are the articles you were hired to write, so you have to just fucking write them because this is a great job as far as jobs go and you want to keep it. Also, let’s be frank: you don’t work on these articles enough because you’re insecure and scared as shit that you’re not actually smart enough to finish them well and publish them well. But remember, that’s just because you’re young and you don’t have any academic publications yet and since you’re ambitious all of your papers swim a bit beyond your depth so yea, you’re fucking scared of them! But that’s bullshit, you were smart enough to start them so you’re smart enough to finish them. The only way you’ll <em>actually</em> fail to live up to them is if you’re so afraid that you don’t commit to them. Thus, if you commit to working on them at a bare minimum from 7am-9am every single weekday, you’ll get fully back into them and probably <em>want</em> to work on them more. But even if you <em>only</em> do this, it will be enough to bring at least 3 of these articles to publication within at least a year, I would think. Remember, these will be <em>actual, real, focused</em> work hours so you’ll actually get shit done.</p>

<p>DO NOT even think about opening Tweetdeck, Feedly, Instapaper, or Facebook. DO NOT even think about opening one of your autonomous projects. No music either. You are afraid of silence and the terror of your own thoughts, but you mustn&rsquo;t be. Also, this period must be actual execution of steps toward the completion of one of these articles. The point is that it has to be actual writing or editing or analysis and NOT organizational, contemplative, or speculative bullshit.</p>

<p><strong>9:00am to 12:00pm.</strong> If teaching, teach. Otherwise, you can continue doing actual execution of the 7-9am research work, OR you can during these hours if you wish to, switch focus and work on your autonomous projects or above-and-beyond teaching work, or blogging/tweeting and other web stuff, the only requirement is that it’s an intentional project-based thing which you state explicitly at 9am as your goal until 12pm and NOT passive timesucking bullshit like commenting on some tweet or FB thread, or even READING twitter or FB, or some other idiotic pastime of yours, such as reading other people’s CVs (why would you EVER do that? well, the answer is insecurity and hero-worship, of course, which can only ever lead to narcissistic/egotistical replication of the hero at best or, at worst, a failure which does not even have the benefit of being an integral failure but would be defined by someone else—the only truly bad kind of failure). This period will be truly free time, but free in the hard Sartrean sense which must be active and responsible for itself.</p>

<p><strong>12:00pm to 1:00pm.</strong> Eat lunch, relax in some good way, like make plans to chat with someone, go for a walk, and/or read a book or newspaper. If flagging, maybe lie down for 15 minutes or if on campus turn off the lights and close your eyes for a little bit.</p>

<p><strong>1:00pm to 5:00pm.</strong> Take care of all your various daily affairs, work responsibilities, quotidian online tasks. Start by checking to-do list and always always work directly from there. If teaching, teach. But also: grading, emails, and teaching prep. You never <em>want</em> to do any of these things because you’re lazy and selfish, and you think you’re precious ideas and writings are the only thing that matter in the world. Well, get over that, because it’s not true!</p>

<p>You’ve already spent a really nice amount of time working on the actual projects of your life. You now must take care of the various remaining work responsibilities. You have to accept that you have a real job with real responsibilities. But take comfort and energy and even inspiration from the absolute fact that this is likely the least alienating and most empowering job for you on the planet right now, so you should be quite happy to do everything you need to do for it. Also be extremely self-aware, humble, and grateful that you <em>already</em> took 3-5 hours that morning to work on semi-to-fully-autonomous projects while almost all people on the planet have 0 hours per day to work on such projects. At the same time, of course, you must constantly turn this self-awareness into rage and opposition against a status quo which makes it possible, but you can’t let this simmer as vague guilt or self-loathing which will simply demobilize you from ever achieving anything against this status quo. At 1:00pm, the philosopher of daybreak puts away their dancing pen and harnesses their awareness of privilege into the daily humility of <em>taking care of business</em>, as grotesque as that sounds, because the truly rebellious will know they themselves are not yet better than the affairs of this world.</p>

<p><strong>5:00pm to 7:00pm.</strong> Prepare a good and healthy dinner, eat, and try to relax a bit, again in some specific intentional way to avoid “relaxing” in some ultimately stressful way (like reading twitter). Pack food for tomorrow if necessary, Like after lunch, lie down or close your eyes for a bit if you’re flagging.</p>

<p><strong>7:00pm to 8:00pm.</strong> Tie up whatever loose ends you need to tie up. This might be working more on your articles or doing extra teaching work that has arisen, whatever. This is open time for you to do whatever most needs to be done at this time, including relaxing if that’s what you really need. Don’t be afraid to do that if that’s what you need. Be happy knowing that if you’re really sticking to your schedule from 6:00am until then, then you’ve actually accomplished more that day than you ever typically do in a day. The only requirement is that you can’t go online without a specific purpose, this is a notoriously dangerous time for you to have hours stolen by the internet. Let’s not beat around the bush: you regularly waste as much as 2 whole hours a day, often at this time, literally doing nothing other than reading idle and sterile “debates” on twitter and Facebook while learning nothing and getting your own most radical and powerful thoughts and visions confused/distracted/shaken by 140-character phantoms. At this time, if you aren’t busy with priorities, you can read books or blog feeds or saved articles on Instapaper or even check in on family or friends on FB, just absolutely no passive twitter or FB reading.</p>

<p>(The whole 5pm-8pm block can also be used, alternatively, for things like having beers with colleagues, or maybe seeing a movie and eating out instead of cooking, whatever, but only once a week or so at most.)</p>

<p><strong>8:00pm to 9:00pm.</strong> Very similar to 7pm-8pm but become more aware of sleep and of the next day coming up. Become more aware that you’re an animal in a nest. Tidy the flat a bit. Bathe or groom if necessary. No radio or podcasts now. Look over schedule for the next day.</p>

<p><strong>9:00pm to 9:30pm.</strong> Meditate/yoga and leave the mat out so it’s natural to do this again first thing in the morning.</p>

<p><strong>9:30pm.</strong> Get into bed, even if you’re not tired. Read a novel or stories or a biography, as long as it’s on paper and it’s not theory or social science. Turn lights off anytime you start to get sleepy. Feel free to write notes or aphorisms or even a letter to a family or friend, but avoid screens unless necessary and nothing too hard or intense.</p>

<p><strong>11:00pm.</strong> Lights off no matter what, whether you’re sleepy or not. If you don’t feel sleepy, it doesn’t matter because you can’t go to bed any later than this if you are going to keep to your plans the next day. Recall that sleeping isn’t something that comes over you but something you choose to do by taking control of breathing and your over-hyper mind; that you need it and want it because you want to have a good day tomorrow. Remember sleep is all about breathing and by this time you simply must go to sleep.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A diagram of stratification]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/12/19/dg-stratifcation/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-19T06:53:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/12/19/dg-stratifcation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Below is a sketch of what Deleuze and Guattari describe as &ldquo;the pincer&rdquo; or &ldquo;double articulation&rdquo; of stratification.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<iframe src="http://wl.figshare.com/articles/881284/embed?show_title=0" width="650" height="424" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<p></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Deleuze, Gilles, and Félix Guattari. 1987. A Thousand Plateaus. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press. pp. 40-41.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What really changed after the Cold War?]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/12/13/what-really-changed-after-the-cold-war/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-13T17:36:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/12/13/what-really-changed-after-the-cold-war</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The traditional textbook story about the end of the Cold War and its effect on the international system completely misses the most important and extraordinary changes taking place at that time. The debate between realists and neoliberal institutionalists is a red herring. The most important transformation wrought by the collapse of the Soviet Union has nothing to do with the power of states vs. the power of international institutions. This debate in international relations theory completely distracts from what are very clearly the most world-historical changes taking place at that time, changes which actually have huge relevance to the lives of students and the global masses more generally.</p>

<p>In brief, the most important changes wrought by the collapse of the Soviet Union, in my view, are the following. These are not original insights, they have been well documented and highlighted by others but I bring them together here for my students and others who might be interested. I’m writing this off-the-cuff right after a seminar, but if I get a chance I’ll  come back and add some citations.</p>

<p>First, during the Cold War, there was a huge global alternative to capitalism (no matter how bad that alternative failed, the point is simply that capitalism was not the only game in town). Because of this, the U.S. and the other capitalist states had to at least pretend that they cared about people, they had to actually convince people that capitalism was a good system, they had to win the &ldquo;hearts and minds&rdquo; of people around the world.</p>

<p>What students today don&rsquo;t realise is that between the end of WWII and the collapse of the Soviet Union, poor people around the world were overthrowing their bosses, overthrowing their governments, and black and brown people of the global south were waging wars against their Western colonial rulers. These uprisings were NOT inherently authoritarian or Stalinesque projects: most of them were just radically democratic- and anti-capitalist uprisings where people were basically just saying &ldquo;take the land, resources, and political power back from the elites who have stolen from us; redistribute the land, cancel the debts, and let&rsquo;s make sure everyone has access to a decent life.&rdquo; And when these anti-colonial and essentially anti-capitalist uprisings would occur, the Soviet Union would give them money, recognition, and often implicit military backing. In this kind of global environment, the U.S. and other western capitalist states HAD to constrain their greed. Almost everything humane achieved within capitalist states since the end of WWII was in part because capitalist elites in the West were terrified that their own citizens would hang them and redistribute their wealth, power, and privileges.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> That was a real threat, and no matter how much we disagree with Stalin or Mao, they&rsquo;re global power gave huge inspiration and real military power to democratic and anti-capitalist uprisings (however badly they would also oppress these projects while supporting them).</p>

<p>So there&rsquo;s that: because the USSR was a threat, the capitalist elites of the West had to actually give their people some resources to at least make it look like capitalism was worth believing in. Or else the poor countries would go with the USSR and the US (and US capitalism) would be finished.</p>

<p>Second, though, is the other side of this coin. During the Cold War, the capitalist elites of the world had to worry about many things other than making money. Trade relations were obviously fraught around the world. Democratic uprisings in the global south were always threatening to expropriate foreign investment capital, whether it was explicitly colonial or not; the U.S. saw extraordinary wildcat strikes at the end of WWII; all kinds of anti-capitalist resistance made it very hard for the rich to get much richer! But it&rsquo;s not just that making money was inhibited by political antagonisms, it&rsquo;s that if anyone within a country got too rich, it would have instigated revolutionary uprisings to cut them down to size!</p>

<p>With the end of the Cold War and the collapse of a powerful global counterweight to the rule of capitalist elites, there was no longer anything to prevent the wealthiest and most powerful people in each country from becoming even wealthier and more powerful! Thus, one of the most extraordinary transformations at the end of the Cold War, which is often omitted or neglected from IR textbooks, is that formerly Communist elites quickly converted to capitalist elites in the single largest transfer of wealth the world has ever seen. In Russia and its Eastern European satellites, the whole economy which was previously owned by the state was simply handed over (often at extremely low prices) to Communist elites who would then simply become capitalist business people. The privatisation of state-owned enterprises after the collapse of the Soviet Union was the single largest transfer of wealth that&rsquo;s ever taken place in world history.</p>

<p>In countries such as Russia, China, India, and many smaller countries as well, the end of the Cold War meant the sudden appearance of the shadiest figure alive today: the billionaire. It is only after the collapse of the USSR, the disappearance of any moral, political, or military check on the power of national capitalist elites, that it is even conceivable for a country such as Mexico to generate one of the wealthiest billionaires in the world, Carlos Slim. Globalisation after the collapse of the USSR is simply the global unleashing of national capitalist elites, the complete global freedom of millionaires to become billionaires and to do whatever they want while politically crushing the masses of the world into more and more helpless, low-wage workers.</p>

<p>When an IR textbook asks us to debate whether states or markets are more powerful, we should be extremely skeptical. States and markets are quickly becoming the same thing, and the old debates of IR appear increasingly dubious. In my opinion, we should always follow the money: find out who is winning, who is losing, and formulate our own questions based on what we&rsquo;re actually observing. To do anything less runs the huge risk of being trapped in a perspective which is itself so narrow in part because of the very transformations we&rsquo;re only beginning to understand.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>The prime example in the UK is, of course, the National Health Service. Such broad-based social provision was a concession which the wealthy made to the masses because they were terrified that the British Communist Party would simply take what they saw as belonging to them. In the U.S., an interesting example is the limited success of the civil rights movement. So long as U.S. capitalism meant the domination and subjugation of its own racial minorities, that didn&rsquo;t look so good to the black and brown people of the world! If the U.S. was going to convince the black and brown people of the world to go the way of capitalism, it had to at least pretend that it supported the freedom of its own black people. Now that every single person born into the UK and US since 1985 is told from birth that there is no alternative to capitalism, is it any wonder that welfare spending is on the decline and the rich white people of the world don&rsquo;t give a shit about racism?<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Remodeling revolutionary agency]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/11/17/remodeling-revolutionary-agency/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-17T14:25:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/11/17/remodeling-revolutionary-agency</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When thinking about revolutionary agency, I move away from the traditional Marxian concept of the “proletariat,” a particular class which is most able to generate revolutionary resistance, in favor of a more general conception of whosever happens to fall through the cracks of capitalist subjectivation.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> I am interested in those whose thoughts, behaviors, and projects, <em>for whatever reason</em>, remain relatively undisciplined by the normalizing and neutralizing tendencies inherent in contemporary society. Is someone’s life very consistent with what the status quo expects of them, or is it very inconsistent. What proportion of someone’s thoughts and behaviors are <em>systematic</em> (predictable) and what proportion are in the statistical error term?</p>

<p>This would be consistent with, but more general than, the classical conception. Immiseration of the “workers” as in the Marxian eschatology would become only a special case of such falling through the cracks. Capitalism grinds the workers to the bottom of its barrel and the revolutionary mechanism in the Marxian view is essentially that, eventually, the workers are pushed through the barrel itself, they see the system from its outside (class consciousness), and therefore are finally free to smash the barrel. But metaphors for the “system” are just metaphors, and however we wish to model the system, there’s no reason why there shouldn’t be many conceivable pathways where individuals could find themselves (intentionally or randomly) having dodged the social conditioning which normalizes individuals into identification with the system. This would explain why and how intellectuals are disproportionately inclined to revolutionary conversion: they fall through the cracks by a totally different path, via the leisure of education, study, and creative intellectual work. But the essential logic which makes workers radical in the Marxian view could thus be unified with the same logic that makes intellectuals revolutionary. And then it would be a matter of identifying through theoretical and empirical research the necessary and sufficient conditions for individuals to escape the grid which so thoroughly shapes most individuals.</p>

<p>Capitalist subjectivation requires a layered process of ideological conditioning; the typical lifespan of a human being in the modern world is a complete archeology of layered ideological conditioning processes that would be dangerously obvious if they were not so effective: the family, where life itself begins as emotional and physical indentured servitude and continues as a process of paying back the father and mother until death; the school, where the cost of food for the social intellect is not just cultivating a taste for obedience to arbitrary authority, but contributing to its legitimacy insofar as the students’ presence constitutes that legitimacy; the workplace, where the price paid for survival outside of the family is just more uncritical submission to whatever institution which takes its place; and finally the re-production of the family itself, which is not actually a successful egress from this inherited chain of uninterrupted submissions that constitute everyday life (however much modern weddings pretend it is), it is actually just passing the buck to the next generation. Having children is merely a debt-swap in which the creditor (society) allows the indentured servant (the young adult) to escape its unpaid and unpayable debt on the condition that it produce a new person who will pay it with interest (the child). The stress, self-sacrifice, and perpetual ethical castration of raising a child today is akin to an exorbitant transaction fee for this debt-swap.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> Yea, OK, we’ll let you pass the debt on to a new person but don’t think you get freedom instantly: if you don’t pay the transaction fee that saps whatever desire might remain in you, then you will be unbearably stigmatized and ostracized as a “bad parent.” Notice that, for better or worse, the most famoulsy radical and effective intellectuals have historically been awful parents, effectively defaulting on this debt altogether.</p>

<p>To measure this concept of proletariat, we would highlight Marx’s main variable of material degradation but also intellectual and spiritual degradation, without necessarily privileging one or the other. Thus, a general formula would understand all individuals as characterized by three variable terms <em>work</em>, <em>ideology</em>, <em>capital</em> and different values under which an individual breaks from identification with the system. Thus a worker’s interest in the system is increasing in ideology and income but decreasing in work:</p>

<p> <em>u = ideology + income &ndash; work</em>,</p>

<p>The traditional Marxian theory of the individual-level revolutionary mechanism is that workers are invested in the system by ideology but the hold of ideology breaks as their labor is increasingly alienating while their income is decreasing. According to Marx, a worker becomes revolutionary when work increases and income decreases enough to <em>outweigh</em> the investments from ideology.</p>

<p>But Marx and so many of his followers never really took seriously the revolutionary positions of bourgeois intellectuals. What this reconceptualization suggests, though, is that the revolutionary defection of bourgeois intellectuals is according to the same essential conception of human beings as the theory of worker defection, only from different movements of the same variables. The defecting bourgeois intellectual receives relatively high income for relatively little work but dis-identifies with the system through decreasing ideological investment. This is simply because true education is the depletion of ideology. This also explains why as anyone’s true education increases, status quo institutions either increase their income, decrease their work, and/or dilute their ability to think and speak freely.</p>

<p>Of course, in reality, a multitude of other, additional institutional investments enter into the equation, such as family investments or racial, gendered, or nationalist investments. All of these institutional investments provide individuals with perceived utility from the system and therefore increase their attachment to the system, and decrease the probability of a revolutionary break. And theoretical and empirical research would have to pursue as an open question the degree to which these different investments account for the inertia of the status quo, and the conditions under which they decrease or increase their hold on individuals.</p>

<p>As for strategy, two thoughts suggest themselves. The first is to search for and find all those who for any reason have fallen through the cracks and to organize around the simple criterion of minimal investment in the status quo.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> The second is that statistical probabilities are essentially scientific maps for how not to think and behave. Statistics allow us to map with extreme precision the paths of resistance. This is because statistical distributions of thought and behavior across the status quo are exact measurements of what the system desires. Thus, I would make the case that the inversion of empirical statistical likelihoods is revolutionary political ethics. Randomness, along the lines of vulgar faux-Situationism or faux-Dada is not sufficient, for capitalism has an extraordinarily high tolerance for randomness. What is necessary is to produce systematically unlikely social outcomes. Notions of “affirmative action” and even more radical variants on that theme are correct to move in this direction, but they typically fail to take seriously that producing unlikely outcomes is far more difficult a challenge than switching some seats at status quo tables. It requires that we have a far more sophisticated theoretical and empirically defensible model of how macro-structures actually respond to low-level individual or group behavior, and it requires that we orchestrate our individual and group behavior according to what are likely far more complicated and sophisticated strategic requirements.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>This Marxian schema of the proletariat still looms behind radical identity politics today in that a special revolutionary agency is now simply associated with various different groups other than the Marxian worker. Even where the concept of intersectionality is highlighted, implicitly or explicitly there is very often the notion that certain intersections of identity uniquely prime certain groups to certain aspects of revolutionary struggle.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>For instance, it&rsquo;s EITHER feed one’s children disgustingly shitty food in solidarity with the masses or naturalize them into hideously bourgeois food privilege, or intellectualized self-loathing privilege, OR&hellip;<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>As a side note, it’s interesting how the internet at once enables this organization and has so quickly supplied its own institutional brakes, as radicals find themselves on the internet but they’re only allowed to find themselves so long as their theoretical and communicative frameworks are adequately consistent with the status quo. See my piece on media choice, the internet, and what has happened to leftist communication.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A concept of political validity in quantitative social science]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/11/03/a-concept-of-political-validity-in-quantitative-social-science/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-03T17:12:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/11/03/a-concept-of-political-validity-in-quantitative-social-science</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let us call <em>bourgeois data</em> any research data the collection of which is funded by groups invested in the status quo. Bourgeois data, which is to say nearly all the quantitative data used by social scientists, suffer from a specific type of bias for which most methodologists show very little concern, despite the extraordinary analytical attention they devote to the question of bias in social-scientific inference more generally. Methodologists are likely unconcerned about the possibility of <em>institutional</em> biases in data collection because they have precisely the same institutional investments as the funders of data collection projects. Methodologists will consider &ldquo;external validity&rdquo; (whether the data reflects what we think it reflects in the world) and &ldquo;internal validity&rdquo; (the logical coherence of inferences), but rarely do they consider what we might call <em>political validity</em>, which we might provisionally define as the scientific legitimacy of the basic worldview, determined by a researcher’s institutional environment, with which scientific inferences are verbally constructed. In other words, we must take seriously the question of whether the institutional environment which sponsors data-collection and research activity more generally is itself non-random and non-trivial. I suspect that for too long this question has been delegated to “critical” theorists in a disingenuous gesture which gives them just enough attention so that positivist social scientists can say their discipline already has people “working on” this issue, but not so much attention that positivists have to make any serious adjustments in how we actually think, write, or speak about the political implications of our research agendas.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, bourgeois data are almost by definition generated by a non-random, non-trivial social process which biases at the very least its <em>terms</em>, if not necessarily the internal or external validity of conclusions drawn from it. By beginning with a vocabulary drawn from a status quo which is from a social-scientific perspective perfectly arbitrary, it ends with conclusions the <em>meaning of which</em> are equally arbitrary, no matter how internally or external valid those conclusions might be. More to the point, the non-random, non-trivial process which shapes a status quo into one vocabulary rather than another is, of course, power. This is why critical theory&rsquo;s demand for reflexivity in social science is not empty posturing, as so many positivist social scientists dismissively believe. Rather, that demand points to a bona fide problem of scientific inference which is not merely humanistic critique from cultural studies departments. To put the issue in the words of positivist social science: the problem is that the words we use to draw conclusions from empirical patterns are never &ldquo;controlled for.&rdquo; We need theoretical work which will, in a methodologically rigorous fashion, subject the naive vocabularies of contemporary social science to a verification process where arbitrary power-driven linguistic determinations are &ldquo;controlled for&rdquo; and replaced in those theoretical edifices we devise to “house” the empirical patterns we discover.</p>

<p>(Social scientists, it must be admitted, have a child-like trust of the politicians and institutions from which they inherit their vocabularies, perhaps because like children they live from the good graces of these parents.)</p>

<p>Most contemporary datasets respond to some research demand that is considered valuable from the perspective of the status quo; it will be motivated by hypotheses the confirmation and rejection of which are consistent with the status quo, for no other reason than all of the actors involved prefer the status quo to a radical overhaul. One doesn’t need to even be a Marxist to believe this, perfectly mainstream rational-choice theories as well as sociological institutionalism confirm this point easily. Because we know these simple truths about institutions but can’t be bothered to take them very seriously in our own work—because the committment to truth, to unbiased inference, would actually demand an explicitly revolutionary politics for which social science does not have the courage today, quantiative social scientists in particular are like finance columnists who evaluate businesses they own stock in without disclosing this fact to readers.</p>

<p>Fortunately, for those of us who take seriously the revolutionary political agenda implied by the necessity of the scientific method, it is not at all the case that we are simply awash with hopelessly and uselessly prejudiced data. Bourgeois data cannot help but accidentally shed light on aspects of the social system it never had any interest in and would have preferred to omit. And it is these aspects to which we must devote our attention if we are to glean from biased data the stories which are most important for correcting the data’s institutional biases. I will call <em>epiphanic data</em> those datasets which emerge from transforming, subsetting, modeling, and otherwise manipulating bourgeois data in order to glean from it radical, anti-institutional insights. It might be objected that if the institutions which sponsor data collection so contaminate data with political bias, then what allows us to think we can glean non-biased conclusions from it? In that voice which positivists use to insinuate that critical theorists are merely conspiracy theorists with paranoiac worldviews: “Why is it not the case that this data is doomed to reproduce the status quo, if the data-collecting instituions are so politically perverse?” There are a few reasons why even the most bourgeois data can be used for anti-bourgeis, epiphanic social science.</p>

<p>The drive for short-term profit incentivizes institutions and individuals to collect dangerously more data than is ideal for the perpetuation of the status quo, at the risk of revealing contradictions which indict the system as a whole. Those groups funding data collection in one area are often unaware and, in any event, politically unconcerned with data collected in another area. Of course, they are politically aware of issues such as general conflicts of bureaucratic “turf” but certainly not in the long-term, revolutionary political dimensions under consideration here. Bourgeois data collection is complacent also because the division of academic labor is so developed and intensely enforced that status quo institutions don’t really have to worry about anyone discovering relationships <em>across many interdisciplinary datasets</em>, even though such datasets are widely and freely available. Bourgeois institutions have been emboldened by a severe undersupply of revolutionaries in quantitative social science. This has permitted data-collectiong institutions a great deal of complacency on this point. A sudden exogenous increase in radical social scientists could quickly seize on bourgeois data and extract from it extremely damning indictments of the status quo, which from a technical perspective would be almost childishly simple but have never yet been performed because the institutional biases are such that these findings are not rewarded. At the same time, phenomena such as racism, colonialism and patriarchy have, for a very long time, artifically depressed literacy, education, and civil rights to specific groups, suppressing demand for a really true, popular social science which would dispel the most vicious falsities and generate more legitimate equilibria. So long as the less privileged groups could not effectivley demand true social science, bourgeois institutions felt safe to collect data to their cold heart’s content.</p>

<p>But today, decolonization, civil rights movements, feminist movements, various democratic uprisings, and the rise of mass education as well as the internet, have all lead to a huge increase in the aggregate demand for precisely this kind of social science. Witness the rise of the “data visualizer”, that not-quite-data-scientist internet persona who specializes in fashionable data-intensive infographics for mass distribution on the web. Such a persona is merely an inane example of how millions of people around the world would be increasingly amenable to a popular, emancipatory social science.</p>

<p>In summary, for those who wish to read between the lines of bourgeois data, there always exists epiphanic data in the simple will to read it differently, a parallax data which promises a wide world of revolutionary intellectual exploration. Unfortunately, this world of data is currently available only to those few of us who have been given the unequally distributed privileges required to mine it <em>and</em> a sufficiently youthful spirit to still <em>want to</em>. But a mass defection of radical young social scientists from currently privileged research agendas toward anti-institutional perspectives would open a large range of research which need not be technically sophisticated to quickly produce huge increases in both the overall truth quotient of social science and its overall effectiveness in radical egalitarian political change.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[There are more than enough hours in the day]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/09/15/there-are-more-than-enough-hours-in-the-day/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-15T16:46:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/09/15/there-are-more-than-enough-hours-in-the-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The popular refrain that &ldquo;there aren&rsquo;t enough hours in the day&rdquo; is an interesting departure from the long and storied political and rhetorical battle to <em>objectively</em> decrease the hours of the working day. It is an extraordinary gauge of our political pacification that when so many people have such a hard time meeting a pervasive social and economic expectation, we would sooner <em>ask for an extension</em> of the expectation than its abolition.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ego and revolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/08/31/ego-and-revolution/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-31T20:42:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/08/31/ego-and-revolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My ego often wrestles with itself: Obviously I want to avoid arrogance and self absorption and selfishness, but the project of revolution almost presupposes delusions of grandeur and extraordinary self-confidence (if only a confidence in the collectives of which one is a constituent). Capitalist individualism is highly egoistic but ironically it keeps egos small and frail under a herd mentality inclusive of exploitation and alienation. I would much prefer the opposite contradiction of wildly inflated egos demanding and creating revolutionary egalitarianism. Indeed, in such a truly egoistic society such as ours, a powerful and disruptive political project to truly force egalitarian movement might require not the altruistic ethos of shrunken egos but a proliferation of individuals sufficiently egoistic to see themselves as truly and immediately capable of changing the world.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The hatred of freedom]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/08/31/the-hatred-of-freedom/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-31T20:07:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/08/31/the-hatred-of-freedom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The truth is that most people do not want other people to flourish. We all support a general idea of everyone being freer but we tend to feel threatened whenever anyone <em>in particular</em> meets with an increase of freedom. Not long after, we begin to hate them for it if we are not welcome or able to enjoy in the proceeds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Resentment and vegetarianism]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/06/27/resentment-and-eating-animals/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-27T03:29:16+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/06/27/resentment-and-eating-animals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People only eat meat because their repressed rage makes them bloodthirsty. All forms of bloodthirst are driven by resentment and revenge; this is the only conceivable reason why smart and good-natured people insist on eating meat. Everyone is so oppressed by social institutions but unable to kill any of the <em>humans</em> responsible for those institutions, that the half-hearted laments of unapologetic animal-eaters often reduce to: “I must reserve at least this one right to exercise my insatiable need to <em>take life</em> for  myself.” I think this is why after great ventings of repressed rage, I find it impossible to eat the flesh of an animal. In such instances, one is free of the resentment which drives such a vicious appetite.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A mass media theory of the surveillance state]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/06/16/a-mass-media-theory-of-the-surveillance-state/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-16T19:57:30+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/06/16/a-mass-media-theory-of-the-surveillance-state</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://twitter.com/sarahljaffe/status/344555375170842624">Sarah Jaffe</a> asks for a political economy of the surveillance state. I felt especially behooved to send her something not just because I&rsquo;m a young academic roughly in political economy but also because, as one of thousands of young adults in the U.S. who were radicalized in through Occupy Wall Street—I strongly identify with independent intellectuals like Sarah and the class war of which she writes. I believe, contrary to many activists and radicals, that the tools of academic political economy can be extremely powerful in the struggle for truth and justice in the social war. So I really wanted to give Sarah a good link and say, &ldquo;Here you go, sure it&rsquo;s bourgeois but look this really can help us understand what&rsquo;s going on&hellip;&rdquo;</p>

<p>Surveying the political economy blogosphere, however, I&rsquo;m hard pressed to find anything worth sending her. Tyler Cowen <a href="http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2013/06/a-simple-public-choice-theory-of-universal-surveillance.html?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%253A+marginalrevolution%252Ffeed+%2528Marginal+Revolution%2529&amp;utm_content=Google+Reader">takes a stab</a>, which Kindred Winecoff <a href="http://ipeatunc.blogspot.com/2013/06/tree-dont-care-what-little-bird-sings.html">finds unconvincing</a>. Winecoff, though, is admittedly unable to do much better, offering only a smattering of thoughts and links. A little discussion on <a href="http://crookedtimber.org/2013/06/13/insubordination-and-the-surveillance-state/">Crooked Timber</a>, a very interesting and link-rich <a href="http://www.cnas.org/blogs/abumuqawama/2013/06/through-murky-prism.html">story from Adam Elkus</a>, but no especially compelling model.</p>

<p><strong>I&rsquo;d like to offer a model of the US surveillance state as a natural outgrowth of any militarized democracy with a corporate mass media. </strong>I&rsquo;ll summarize the argument succinctly up front, and develop an informal model below.</p>

<p><strong>Abstract:</strong></p>

<p>Basically, in an ideally functioning democracy, anti-colonial terrorism is an effective check on colonial tendencies of democratic states. In an ideally functioning democracy with a healthy communication/information environment, 9-11 would have elicited a massive domestic uproar against the US militarism which incited 9-11, that militarism abroad would have been withdrawn, and terrorism would have stopped.</p>

<p>When a capitalist democracy is overrun with rampant inequality and the media are captured by wealthy elites, terrorism does not produce a check against colonialism because the wealthy have incentives to stifle the message attached to anti-colonial terrorism. This leads to a bad equilibrium of colonial terror abroad and retaliatory terror at home. At the same time, wealthy elites who already have a monopoly on information production also already have economies of scale in information monitoring and surveillance. Because the system is increasingly suboptimal for everyone but the wealthy of the colonial regime, and because it is increasingly leveraged on distorted information, it is therefore increasingly <em>vulnerable</em> to the very nature of information <em>anywhere</em>.</p>

<p>The communication/information of domestic citizens becomes as threatening to the elite as terrorism from abroad, because the increasingly suboptimal system was built on a fundamentally manipulative basis of a corporate-captured media culture. Thus, once the system crosses some threshold of suboptimality, a surveillance state is rapidly and easily turned on populations at home and abroad—the bureacratic and technological resources easily spillover and an already pacified population even happily accepts it.</p>

<h2>1. A Baseline Model of Colonialism and Anti-Colonial Terrorism with Democratic Communication</h2>

<p>Consider an ideally functioning liberal democracy. There is a market economy with winners and losers but robust democratic institutions empower the people to tax and regulate business as they please. Assume only two things about this democracy:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>As per standard models of taxation/redistribution in democracies, taxation and redistribution increase as inequality increases (Meltzer and Richards 1981).<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p></li>
<li><p>Assume that there are strong policies which prevent the concentration of commercial media and actively promote a diversity of grassroots, community-driven media agendas. In other words, assume the intution most of us have when we imagine what media would look like in an ideal democracy, i.e. non-massified, diversified media which questions and criticizes everything from multiple angles. This assumption elides many questions (but that&rsquo;s the privilege of blog posts, right?)</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Now, militaries of democracies are driven by what Yagil Levy calls <a href="http://cmp.sagepub.com/content/27/4/386.abstract">a force/casualty tradeoff:</a> Voters punish politicians when soldiers on the home team die, but since voters don&rsquo;t punish politicians for killing foreign civilians, democratic pressure actually encourages militaries to use excessive lethal force overseas (killing civilians) in order to prevent their own soldiers from dying. Assume this is true of our hypothetical liberal democracy.</p>

<p>In response foreigners attack civilians in the liberal democracy precisely in order to raise the costs of the democracy&rsquo;s violence abroad beyond what is politically sustainable in the democracy. There&rsquo;s an excellent book by <a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;rct=j&amp;q=&amp;esrc=s&amp;source=web&amp;cd=10&amp;cad=rja&amp;ved=0CF0QFjAJ&amp;url=http%253A%252F%252Fbooks.google.com%252Fbooks%252Fabout%252FWinning_hearts_and_minds.html%253Fid%253DzvMLAQAAMAAJ&amp;ei=I1u7UZeEH-Lo0gGWl4HADg&amp;usg=AFQjCNE_2mo-CgGxjJ_pQerUwM3BhafstQ&amp;sig2=jI0zNa2fZ6sr8wcF-R7HBw&amp;bvm=bv.47883778,d.dmQ">Susan Carruthers (1995)</a> which provides ample evidence that, from Mau Mau to Malaysia to Cyprus, anti-colonial terrorism against the British colonial government was based on the wager that British citizens would be so horrified that they would pressure their government to withdraw. Interestingly, Carruthers traces how this strategy largely worked, as British media reports of anti-colonial terrorism turned British citizens sour towards colonialism.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> Most important for the moment, however, is the acknowledgement that this logic of political terrorism requires that citizens in the liberal democracy truly learn about the reality of the protesting terrorists. The British media in the 1950s and 1960s roughly meets the assumption laid out above&mdash;definitely some concentration and cronyism but still lots of freewheeling muckraking and radical leftist newspapers with politically significant audiences.</p>

<p>So, in a functioning democracy with relative equality and a relatively healthy media environment, terrorism in protest of a democracy&rsquo;s violence abroad makes citizens in the democracy update their estimation of their military&rsquo;s violence abroad and support declines for the military&rsquo;s violence.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> The military is forced to withdraw from its violent adventures, terrorism stops, and there is neither the need nor the political possibility of a surveillance state.</p>

<h2>2. Colonialism and Anti-Colonial Terrorism with Corporate Mass Media</h2>

<p>Now, let&rsquo;s imagine a rise in inequality without a corresponding rise in taxation/redistribution. I don&rsquo;t think I need to post a graph—we all know indeed that since the 1950s most of the US income gains have gone to the rich, and along the way we&rsquo;ve ended up with only neoliberal cutbacks to redistributive spending. In other words, assume that the Meltzer and Richards expectations no longer hold.</p>

<p>Runaway inequality would have two really important implications for understanding where the surveillance state has come from and how it was possible:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>If inequality rises and democratic redistribution does not occur to level the political playing field, here&rsquo;s a nice political economy model showing with evidence why and how <a href="https://0ec87679-a-62cb3a1a-s-sites.googlegroups.com/site/mariapetrovaphd/inequality%2520media.pdf?attachauth=ANoY7coFxOvpnB1LkvoeH4s47vGIT7Q8baK6IVmtXBnjoUVXUQ97HyVYtGsXxDc3fBhYT4Ve5bTn8Tm-Nar1ekON48VEgQec6qqChEAILiqgcJSHSXoUtOOrWfUmlwSm2nwChy74n1-2apdOtcyZfHyyRlwWYaM3XKe-sc42RXnAMYQ2vXvHPgkLpp4L5CkLODy1AQlKNa0Wax0HcunE64rJqKArAjCZ8nQpckC1RZOQcKw6MyhMYG4%253D&amp;attredirects=0">the media will be captured by the rich</a> (Petrova 2008).<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup></p></li>
<li><p>Media captured by the rich is far less likely to report the ways in which the US military is to blame for terrorism, and far more likely to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rally_'round_the_flag_effect">rally-around-the-flag</a>. First, we know very well that the media tend to index their reporting to what the government says <a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1460-2466.2006.00296.x/abstract?deniedAccessCustomisedMessage=&amp;userIsAuthenticated=false">(one especially apropos example of this finding is Bennett, Lawrence, and Livingston 2006)</a>. If this is a tendency of media in general, it should be more true of media captured by the rich because for obvious reasons the economic interests of elite media actors would have a greater status-quo bias (they would be highly averse to anything that could engender significant mass-public re-evaluations of the status quo). There is ample evidence for this claim in the observation that an outlet such as FOX news, most closely aligned with the wealthiest patrons such as the Koch Brothers, will rally-around-the-flag and defend the military more rabidly than any of the other outlets.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The resulting expectation at this point in our model is that once runaway inequality leads to media capture (i.e. corporate mass media), the <strong>message</strong> of retaliatory political terrorism hardly gets through as elite media rally-around-the-flag. Terrorists <a href="http://www.nbcnews.com/id/4686034/ns/world_news-hunt_for_al_qaida/t/timeline-al-qaida-statements/">repeatedly and explicity</a> <a href="http://www.nydailynews.com/news/crime/boston-bomb-suspect-left-confession-boat-report-article-1.1345642">explain and justify</a> their attacks on US citizens as the only option available to them in discouraging the continued murder of their people by the US military. The problem is that now there is no sufficiently powerful media company with any incentives to really highlight the US government&rsquo;s share of the blame and to editorialize in that direction as vociferously as Great Britain&rsquo;s <em>Daily Worker</em> in the 1950s.<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup></p>

<p>Of course rallying-around-the-flag has always occurred in the media, but in non-captured, democratic media the knee-jerk patriotism is only one voice among many. After runaway inequality, it&rsquo;s basically the only voice in the media, which is what we have in the U.S. today. Because the actual message terrorists attach to their terrorism does not get through, it no longer exerts the &ldquo;error-correction&rdquo; effects it exerted in our baseline model; it no longer alters the subjective cost-benefit analysis of the mass democratic public, and therefore there is no negative feedback, no countervailing electoral pressure against the collateral murder of foreign civilians. The democratic citizens unwittingly incentivize the goverment to recklessly kill foreign civilians and then, when they are attacked by suicide bombers in response, the elite media deprives them of the most important point and leads them to demand more war.</p>

<h2>3. The Surveillance State is a Spillover of Corporate Mass Media</h2>

<p>I would argue that the surveillance state is simply a technological and bureaucratic <a href="http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/2705338?uid=3739864&amp;uid=2&amp;uid=4&amp;uid=3739256&amp;sid=21102408438227">spillover</a> of a militarized democracy with a corporate mass media system. Once a state arrives in the bad equilibrium described above—where &ldquo;democratic&rdquo; electoral pressures and a perverse media environment create an infinite loop of militarized terrorism abroad and retaliatory terrorism at home—the stability of the system is highly <em>vulernable</em> to information precisely because it&rsquo;s built on distortion of the truth. Because this system is increasingly suboptimal for most people in the country and outside of it, true information is increasingly threatening to the status quo.</p>

<p>At the same time this system is highly leveraged on the distortion of information, advantages in the production/dissemination of information also give media elites extraordinary advantage in the surveillance and reconnaisance of information. If you need to be convinced of the complementarity between producing and monitoring information, recall that a significant portion of CIA activities, especially earlier in its history, are also organized around <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morale_Operations_Branch">producing</a> information and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CIA_influence_on_public_opinion">influencing public opinion</a> as much as collecting and monitoring it. The government contractor Booz Allen Hamilton, (former) home of the most recent NSA whistleblower Edward Snowden, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Booz_Allen_Hamilton%23Notable_members_and_alumni">has ties</a> to British Telecommunications PLC, VH1 and CMT television networks, more than one connection to MTV Networks, publisher McGraw-Hill, and individuals who came directly from the information-production side of the CIA. For instance, Booz Allen Hamilton was once the private-sector home of Miles Copeland, a figure who was instrumental in the sabotage of Mossadegh in Iran, an operation which involved elaborate propaganda campaigns, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1953_Iranian_coup_d'%25C3%25A9tat%23Role_of_BBC.27s_Persian_service">manipulation</a> of the Persian media, and some <a href="http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F10F15F73F5C177B93C4A91783D85F408585F9">ideological assistance</a> at home. One cannot run a world-class surveillance operation without some experience in controlling the flow of public information in general, and one cannot get away with it unless one has already produced a pacifying public culture for some time.</p>

<p>Thus, lo and behold, at exactly the same time as true information is increasingly threatening to the system, the elites who have produced the distortions of that system will, and must, easily and naturally turn their resources towards monitoring as many people as possible. The capture and development of corporate mass media produces the informational distortions which engender a cycle of terror abroad and at home. Because this is an inherently suboptimal system which citizens would overthrow if they understood it, it suddenly requires a surveillance system to monitor the possibility of any threats whatsoever domestic or abroad. Then once the actual construction of a surveillance state is triggered, it is only possible on the back of an already developed and elite-controlled mass media—because of the bureaucratic and technological spillovers but also from the already pacified population it has produced.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Richard, Scott F, and Allan H Meltzer. 1981. “A Rational Theory of the Size of Government.” Journal of Political Economy (May 26): 1–15. As the mean income outpaces the income of the median voter, we should find taxation/redistribution increasing because that median voter will prefer governments who tax the rich and redistribute their money. In turn, an ideally functioning representative democracy almost by definition means that the only politician who can win an election is the politician who satisfies the median voter. Thus, in a democracy, as inequality increases, we should find governments taxing and redistributing.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Note also that suicide bombings are more likely against liberal democracies.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Note that it makes no difference whether the democratic citizens drop their support of the military because they empathetically learn about the suffering which drives the protesting terrorists, or out of self-interest (the military&rsquo;s adventure abroad isn&rsquo;t worth the risk of being bombed in the subway).<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Petrova looks in particular at media freedom, i.e. censorship and formal repression, but her model is also equally suggestive of the expectation that rising inequality would allow the rich to unduly influence what the media do and do not say without necessarily buying its formal repression. The difficulty is that there&rsquo;s good data on good old fashioned repression, not so many datasets on informal influence by the rich.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>It is well known that bin Laden launched concerted public messaging campaigns urging the US to leave the Middle East or else there would be attacks against US civilians. I&rsquo;m not aware of research on this in particular, but I think we can be pretty sure these public declarations were not well covered by US media outlets. Needless to say, in the aftermath of 9-11, the knee-jerk patriotism and [rally-around-the-flag][13] effects in the media not only crowded-out but positively punished the empathetic/self-critical line. Remember when Ward Churchill was [absolutely destroyed by the mainstream media][14] for suggesting that 9-11 was like &ldquo;chickens coming home to roost&rdquo;? Agree or disagree with Churchill, the point here is that when there are only a few disproportionately powerful media outlets—and for probably a few other more nuanced reasons—the rally-around-the-flag tendencies are amplified and choke off the very possibility of citizens critically evaluating and updating their assessments of their military&rsquo;s actions abroad.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Civil war and the square of ethnic fractionalization]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/05/22/civil-war-and-the-square-of-ethnic-fractionalization-4/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-22T17:06:22+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/05/22/civil-war-and-the-square-of-ethnic-fractionalization-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Steve Saideman wonders if the relationship between ethnic fractionalization and civil war is curvilinear, where increasing fractionalization increases the probability of civil war up to a certain point but then increasing fractionalization decreases the probability of civil war. Since I have my nose in this data right now, I&rsquo;ve given this conjecture a quick probe. I find no evidence <em>prima facie</em>.</p>

<p>Below is a replication of Sambanis 2004 where I simply add the square of ethnic fractionalization. If Steve&rsquo;s conjecture were true, we&rsquo;d expect <em>ef1</em> to be positive, <em>ef1sq</em> to be negative, and both of them to be significant. They are signed as expected but not significant given the controls recommended by Sambanis. I then try alternative codings of civil war and a simple equation with no controls. If Steve&rsquo;s conjecture is true, it&rsquo;s not obvious.</p>

<p>Everything below is reproducible in R-just download the replication data, easy to find with a quick search, and set your working directory to where the data is.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Replicate Sambanis 2004 (Table 6 in paper, column 8, pp.845)</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='r'><span class='line'>library<span class="p">(</span>foreign<span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>sambanis<span class="o">&lt;-</span>read.dta<span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&quot;SambanisJCR2004_replicationdataset.dta&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>sambanis<span class="o">$</span>ef1sq<span class="o">&lt;-</span>sambanis<span class="o">$</span>ef1 <span class="o">*</span> sambanis<span class="o">$</span>ef1
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>model <span class="o">&lt;-</span> glm<span class="p">(</span>warstnsb  gdpl1 <span class="o">+</span> grol1 <span class="o">+</span> inst3l1 <span class="o">+</span> anoc2l1 <span class="o">+</span> oil2l1 <span class="o">+</span>
</span><span class='line'>          ef1 <span class="o">+</span> lpopnsl1 <span class="o">+</span> mtnl1 <span class="o">+</span> warnsl1<span class="p">,</span> data <span class="o">=</span> sambanis<span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>          family <span class="o">=</span> binomial<span class="p">(</span>link <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s">&quot;probit&quot;</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>summary<span class="p">(</span>model<span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<pre><code>## Call:
## glm(formula = warstnsb ~ gdpl1 + grol1 + inst3l1 + anoc2l1 + 
##     oil2l1 + ef1 + lpopnsl1 + mtnl1 + warnsl1, family = binomial(link = "probit"), 
##     data = sambanis)
## 
## Deviance Residuals: 
##    Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max  
## -0.604  -0.231  -0.173  -0.106   3.560  
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error z value Pr(&gt;|z|)    
## (Intercept) -3.90226    0.46234   -8.44  &lt; 2e-16 ***
## gdpl1       -0.09271    0.02295   -4.04  5.3e-05 ***
## grol1       -0.51380    0.49750   -1.03  0.30172    
## inst3l1      0.23713    0.09634    2.46  0.01384 *  
## anoc2l1      0.23792    0.08807    2.70  0.00690 ** 
## oil2l1       0.29680    0.11541    2.57  0.01012 *  
## ef1          0.35605    0.16455    2.16  0.03049 *  
## lpopnsl1     0.10503    0.02743    3.83  0.00013 ***
## mtnl1        0.00199    0.00182    1.09  0.27466    
## warnsl1     -0.06609    0.10492   -0.63  0.52873    
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 '***' 0.001 '**' 0.01 '*' 0.05 '.' 0.1 ' ' 1 
## 
## (Dispersion parameter for binomial family taken to be 1)
## 
##     Null deviance: 1133.2  on 5892  degrees of freedom
## Residual deviance: 1038.8  on 5883  degrees of freedom
##   (3567 observations deleted due to missingness)
## AIC: 1059
## 
## Number of Fisher Scoring iterations: 8
</code></pre>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Adding the square of ethnic fractionalization</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='r'><span class='line'>model <span class="o">&lt;-</span> glm<span class="p">(</span>warstnsb  gdpl1 <span class="o">+</span> grol1 <span class="o">+</span> inst3l1 <span class="o">+</span> anoc2l1 <span class="o">+</span> oil2l1 <span class="o">+</span> ef1 <span class="o">+</span>
</span><span class='line'>          ef1sq <span class="o">+</span> lpopnsl1 <span class="o">+</span> mtnl1 <span class="o">+</span> muslim <span class="o">+</span> warnsl1<span class="p">,</span> data <span class="o">=</span> sambanis<span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>          family <span class="o">=</span> binomial<span class="p">(</span>link <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s">&quot;probit&quot;</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>summary<span class="p">(</span>model<span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<pre><code>## Call:
## glm(formula = warstnsb ~ gdpl1 + grol1 + inst3l1 + anoc2l1 + 
##     oil2l1 + ef1 + ef1sq + lpopnsl1 + mtnl1 + muslim + warnsl1, 
##     family = binomial(link = "probit"), data = sambanis)
## 
## Deviance Residuals: 
##    Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max  
## -0.595  -0.230  -0.172  -0.103   3.547  
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error z value Pr(&gt;|z|)    
## (Intercept) -3.94606    0.48647   -8.11    5e-16 ***
## gdpl1       -0.09092    0.02370   -3.84  0.00012 ***
## grol1       -0.50874    0.49343   -1.03  0.30253    
## inst3l1      0.23723    0.09641    2.46  0.01386 *  
## anoc2l1      0.24253    0.08838    2.74  0.00607 ** 
## oil2l1       0.26000    0.12119    2.15  0.03192 *  
## ef1          0.51893    0.72622    0.71  0.47488    
## ef1sq       -0.17995    0.71442   -0.25  0.80113    
## lpopnsl1     0.10452    0.02775    3.77  0.00017 ***
## mtnl1        0.00184    0.00188    0.98  0.32529    
## muslim       0.00104    0.00111    0.93  0.35169    
## warnsl1     -0.06888    0.10501   -0.66  0.51185    
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 '***' 0.001 '**' 0.01 '*' 0.05 '.' 0.1 ' ' 1 
## 
## (Dispersion parameter for binomial family taken to be 1)
## 
##     Null deviance: 1133.2  on 5892  degrees of freedom
## Residual deviance: 1037.8  on 5881  degrees of freedom
##   (3567 observations deleted due to missingness)
## AIC: 1062
## 
## Number of Fisher Scoring iterations: 8
</code></pre>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Using Sambanis alternative coding of civil war</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='r'><span class='line'>model <span class="o">&lt;-</span> glm<span class="p">(</span>warstns  gdpl1 <span class="o">+</span> grol1 <span class="o">+</span> inst3l1 <span class="o">+</span> anoc2l1 <span class="o">+</span> oil2l1 <span class="o">+</span>
</span><span class='line'>          ef1 <span class="o">+</span> ef1sq <span class="o">+</span> lpopnsl1 <span class="o">+</span> mtnl1 <span class="o">+</span> muslim <span class="o">+</span> warnsl1<span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>          data <span class="o">=</span> sambanis<span class="p">,</span> family <span class="o">=</span> binomial<span class="p">(</span>link <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s">&quot;probit&quot;</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>summary<span class="p">(</span>model<span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<pre><code>## Call:
## glm(formula = warstns ~ gdpl1 + grol1 + inst3l1 + anoc2l1 + oil2l1 + 
##     ef1 + ef1sq + lpopnsl1 + mtnl1 + muslim + warnsl1, family = binomial(link = "probit"), 
##     data = sambanis)
## 
## Deviance Residuals: 
##    Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max  
## -0.532  -0.217  -0.165  -0.102   3.499  
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error z value Pr(&gt;|z|)    
## (Intercept) -3.73245    0.52338   -7.13  9.9e-13 ***
## gdpl1       -0.08649    0.02469   -3.50  0.00046 ***
## grol1       -0.09783    0.48861   -0.20  0.84131    
## inst3l1      0.23635    0.10911    2.17  0.03030 *  
## anoc2l1      0.28191    0.09773    2.88  0.00392 ** 
## oil2l1       0.16875    0.14066    1.20  0.23027    
## ef1          0.65104    0.77115    0.84  0.39853    
## ef1sq       -0.38362    0.77341   -0.50  0.61989    
## lpopnsl1     0.08969    0.03039    2.95  0.00316 ** 
## mtnl1        0.00209    0.00205    1.02  0.30854    
## muslim       0.00118    0.00124    0.95  0.34246    
## warnsl1     -0.21649    0.31589   -0.69  0.49313    
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 '***' 0.001 '**' 0.01 '*' 0.05 '.' 0.1 ' ' 1 
## 
## (Dispersion parameter for binomial family taken to be 1)
## 
##     Null deviance: 915.34  on 5161  degrees of freedom
## Residual deviance: 842.13  on 5150  degrees of freedom
##   (4298 observations deleted due to missingness)
## AIC: 866.1
## 
## Number of Fisher Scoring iterations: 8
</code></pre>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Using Fearon and Laitin 2003 coding of civil war</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='r'><span class='line'>model <span class="o">&lt;-</span> glm<span class="p">(</span>warst7b  gdpl1 <span class="o">+</span> grol1 <span class="o">+</span> inst3l1 <span class="o">+</span> anoc2l1 <span class="o">+</span> oil2l1 <span class="o">+</span>
</span><span class='line'>          ef1 <span class="o">+</span> ef1sq <span class="o">+</span> lpopnsl1 <span class="o">+</span> mtnl1 <span class="o">+</span> muslim <span class="o">+</span> warnsl1<span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>          data <span class="o">=</span> sambanis<span class="p">,</span> family <span class="o">=</span> binomial<span class="p">(</span>link <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s">&quot;probit&quot;</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>summary<span class="p">(</span>model<span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<pre><code>## Call:
## glm(formula = warst7b ~ gdpl1 + grol1 + inst3l1 + anoc2l1 + oil2l1 + 
##     ef1 + ef1sq + lpopnsl1 + mtnl1 + muslim + warnsl1, family = binomial(link = "probit"), 
##     data = sambanis)
## 
## Deviance Residuals: 
##    Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max  
## -0.501  -0.200  -0.145  -0.086   3.590  
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error z value Pr(&gt;|z|)    
## (Intercept) -4.28989    0.54194   -7.92  2.5e-15 ***
## gdpl1       -0.08807    0.02665   -3.30  0.00095 ***
## grol1       -0.27141    0.52732   -0.51  0.60677    
## inst3l1      0.19536    0.10692    1.83  0.06768 .  
## anoc2l1      0.25845    0.09748    2.65  0.00802 ** 
## oil2l1       0.13327    0.14174    0.94  0.34707    
## ef1          0.44027    0.80427    0.55  0.58409    
## ef1sq       -0.22642    0.79784   -0.28  0.77657    
## lpopnsl1     0.11930    0.03065    3.89  9.9e-05 ***
## mtnl1        0.00255    0.00204    1.25  0.21124    
## muslim       0.00155    0.00122    1.26  0.20659    
## warnsl1      0.01688    0.11169    0.15  0.87987    
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 '***' 0.001 '**' 0.01 '*' 0.05 '.' 0.1 ' ' 1 
## 
## (Dispersion parameter for binomial family taken to be 1)
## 
##     Null deviance: 897.81  on 5892  degrees of freedom
## Residual deviance: 822.48  on 5881  degrees of freedom
##   (3567 observations deleted due to missingness)
## AIC: 846.5
## 
## Number of Fisher Scoring iterations: 9
</code></pre>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Only ethnic fractionalization</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='r'><span class='line'>model <span class="o">&lt;-</span> glm<span class="p">(</span>warstnsb  ef1 <span class="o">+</span> ef1sq<span class="p">,</span> data <span class="o">=</span> sambanis<span class="p">,</span> family <span class="o">=</span> binomial<span class="p">(</span>link <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s">&quot;probit&quot;</span><span class="p">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>summary<span class="p">(</span>model<span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<pre><code>## Call:
## glm(formula = warstnsb ~ ef1 + ef1sq, family = binomial(link = "probit"), 
##     data = sambanis)
## 
## Deviance Residuals: 
##    Min      1Q  Median      3Q     Max  
## -0.303  -0.227  -0.196  -0.161   2.990  
## 
## Coefficients:
##             Estimate Std. Error z value Pr(&gt;|z|)    
## (Intercept)   -2.302      0.131  -17.63   &lt;2e-16 ***
## ef1            0.323      0.589    0.55     0.58    
## ef1sq          0.283      0.580    0.49     0.63    
## ---
## Signif. codes:  0 '***' 0.001 '**' 0.01 '*' 0.05 '.' 0.1 ' ' 1 
## 
## (Dispersion parameter for binomial family taken to be 1)
## 
##     Null deviance: 1249.6  on 6268  degrees of freedom
## Residual deviance: 1230.5  on 6266  degrees of freedom
##   (3191 observations deleted due to missingness)
## AIC: 1237
## 
## Number of Fisher Scoring iterations: 7
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What trust is not]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/22/what-trust-is-not/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-22T16:50:34+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/22/what-trust-is-not</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Trust is not the absence of fear or insecurity regarding the possibility of betrayal. The very structure of our society wounds us so badly from the very beginning of our lives that perhaps such fears and insecurities are doomed to persist. Rather, trust is the feeling of peaceful confidence in a particular relationship <em>despite</em> whatever fears or insecurities one nonetheless continues to feel. Trust is only meaningful as an <em>earned relief</em> from fear and insecurity; as such, it not only implies the continued presence of fear and insecurity outside of the trust relation, it even requires a practiced awareness of the default fear and insecurity which has typically persisted as a fact throughout the greater part of the whole, global human network. We find negative evidence of this in the observation that partners in an honest trust relation often become so absorbed in their own mutual security that they lose awareness of the frightful insecurity against which they have built that trust with great labors and against great odds. When this happens, the storehouse of trust quickly begins to deplete. In colloquial terms, we often refer to exactly this process when we object to being &ldquo;taken for granted.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Historically, the bourgeois defenses against this tendency are typically strategies of locking-into and locking-up the trust relation as soon as it is sufficiently established: make commitments backed by the wrath of God and the law (marriage); construct a physical space that is at once a fortress against external threats and a prison to contain internal threats of flight (the &ldquo;home&rdquo;); then whither until death in the empty husk of a trust that dies six months after it is locked-in.  Trust in the absence of fear and insecurity is not trust; it is merely a glorified emotional comatose which accomplishes nothing more than self-protection and the <em>forgetting</em> of the real omnipresence of fear and insecurity that persists between nearly everyone else.</p>

<p>Furthermore, this bourgeois illusion of trust is not simply pathetic, which would at least be harmless. This false trust of the bourgeois family is <em>productive</em> of more human fear and insecurity than existed before it was &ldquo;locked-in.&rdquo; It produces net fear and insecurity because the little and tawdry security gained by the bourgeois couple is more than offset by all the lonely, isolated peers who are objectively less secure after each and every exclusive, excluding, and acquisitive bourgeois coupling. Finally, the bourgeois techniques of politically organizing trust not only tend to destroy the true and emancipating reality of any real trust they seek to hoard, but additionally, by their exclusive and excluding nature they hardly permit any honest understanding (in private or public) about how this political organization of trust ultimately fails everyone. The basic political form of the bourgeois couple necessarily brings with it a strategically dishonest public ideology because its very strategy is simulative and dissimulative: what is most characteristic of the bourgeois organization of trust relations is the creation of a political edifice that props-up merely an idea of trust, using privatized and therefore rarified social resources. The real production of real trust <em>has nothing to do with it. </em>In fact, the whole bourgeois organization and conception of trust seems almost expressly designed to excise the necessity and anxiety of having to build trust.</p>

<p>In other words, because the bourgeois organization of trust relations is chiefly a system for simulating trust and dissimulating its precariousness, it is especially damning for the overall social trust because it not only fails itself and denies others, it also requires and sustains public allegiance to its honor and continuation at all costs. After all, that is the bourgeois couple&rsquo;s original intention: to sustain a privatized &ldquo;trust&rdquo; at all costs, to hide from the insecurities that have always plagued humans everywhere, to pretend that fear has been abolished, at least until death do it part.  The truth is that people cannot know trust when fear and insecurity have merely been excluded and forgotten. Today, real trust can only be known when real fears and insecurities are so honestly recognized, shared, and accepted as a common problem and common responsibility. When this really truly occurs, the release from bourgeois fakery is so vertiginous and empowering that it cannot be mistaken. It is often named &ldquo;falling in love.&rdquo; Indeed, there is no reason to believe its uncommon and it is almost certainly the once-truly-lived kernel of truth within the dead husk of most bourgeois relationships.</p>

<p>We, on the other hand, do not seek to lock-in or lock-up the truth that together we have glimpsed, because for us, the truth we have shared is the hardest and rarest truth that can be shared: that there is nothing whatsoever to lock-in or lock-up. Recall that <em>to betray</em> means <em>to reveal</em> as much as it means <em>to deceive</em>. We do not betray each other because we neither hide nor reveal anything, but rather we produce shared truths that did not exist before of us. We are not therefore free of insecurities and hardly a day goes by that we do not tremble with some mundane everyday fear; we simply love each other but we truly love each other, and we trust each other <em>despite</em> that real love is a real cause for very real fears.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reactionary law and bourgeois desire]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/19/reactionary-law-and-bourgeois-desire/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-19T02:06:45+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/19/reactionary-law-and-bourgeois-desire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>An unfortunate tendency of exceptionally repressive laws and draconian sentences is that, in middle-class eyes, they tend to justify themselves: to bourgeois stiffs, it begins to seem as if anyone who would risk such harsh punishments <em>must be</em> so crazy and dangerous that it feels appropriate and reassuring to be protected by such a vicious legal machine. Indeed, the self-justifying effect of a draconian legal system increases as punishments get more severe for less and less significant behaviors. As the punishments become larger and the crimes smaller, even more inclined is the average person to wonder with a mix of fear and envy why anyone would insist on actions that seem to them so trivial given such great costs.</p>

<p>Knowing already that countless people are jailed for years on simple, non-violent drug charges, we begin to read more and more absurd headlines: a black homeless woman is given a 12-year prison sentence for sending her son to a public school with an incorrect home address; even a white man is given a 2-year prison sentence <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_DeChristopher">for outbidding oil companies in a big land auction</a> and another white man is sentenced <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weev">three years in prison for accessing a publicly available website</a> simply because it wasn&rsquo;t intended for public view. In response to increasingly absurd and vicious applications of the law, the average fish-blooded citizen tends to think only that anyone who still insists on such unorthodox exercises of freedom must <em>lack all sense of proportion</em>. And this frightens them half to death, for good reason. Of course, in some sense, this view is technically correct (to maintain any integrity in a society such as ours requires a deep refusal of its ratios) but what is critical to grasp is that to the average and spineless citizen, those who display any kind of autonomy inconsistent with the police order <em>truly</em> appear <em>that</em> dangerous. And perhaps they really are. Not only because such behavior lacks the proportions of everyday middle-class order and therefore <em>generally</em> threatens it; because middle-class comforts and privileges could and would be re-distributed if it were not for a firm legal system, they are<em> especially</em> threatened when increasingly decent people are punished with increasing absurdity for breaking increasingly stupid laws for engaging in fairly reasonable actions. When there are individuals who insist on doing what they want despite the risk of increasingly insane legal punishment, the average citizen who marginally benefits from this legal system will only prefer more laws, more police, and more prisons.</p>

<p>It will never cease to astound us how impoverished the bottom ranks of the relatively privileged groups (in particular, white people, male-gendered people) can become without rebelling. But the present thesis might solve some portion of this classic puzzle. No matter how obvious it is that the contemporary political system has been destroying, and will continue destroying, even these historically privileged groups, they are paralyzed from resisting because they are wholly indebted to precisely this system and its tendencies of exclusion and oppression for whatever material and psychological possessions they still possess. The reason that rebellion is perhaps impossible for such souls, the reason they can see no other option than to double-down on their reactionary wagers, is because every advancement of capitalist exclusion and oppression is simply the advancement of what they once unconsciously but nonetheless gleefully assumed as the core of their beliefs and behaviors. Their refusal to rebel is suicide, but rebellion too would be suicide. Whichever path they choose, may they only choose quickly!<em> </em> 
Finally, this same thesis which helps us understand absurdly aggressive legal reaction also sheds light on why other types of crime are surprisingly under-punished relative to what we would expect. For example, as the recent and now notorious Steubenville rape case attests, young men who engage in brutal sexual violence against women often receive significantly shorter prison sentences than many non-violent, drug offenders. For the reasons already articulated, it is easy to see why property-related crimes are so grossly over-punished while crimes such as rape are relatively under-punished: crimes even vaguely related to property threaten relatively powerful (but increasingly fearful) groups invested in the status quo, while sexual violence against women—as one of the most basic substructures underwriting our political system built on domination—is the most basic kind of activity that constitutes the power of these relatively privileged but increasingly fearful groups invested in the status quo. From this perspective, it is not at all surprising that the former set of crimes is increasingly punished while the latter is punished less and less.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chapter 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/14/1/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-14T16:51:43+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/14/1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dear Reader,</p>

<p>I am writing to tell you that I love you and I am already scared of losing you. That does not mean I like you, but I do love you and I don’t want to lose you. I don’t know what love is or what exactly people mean by it, but that is almost certainly what I wish to say. More and more I grow convinced that I know less and less, which is disappointing not least because I’ve always expected the opposite, that I would learn more and more as I go. But I also understand this would seem to bode very poorly for you, my dear reader, given our society’s widespread prejudice in favor of smart writers. In fact, I know with certainty that I have nothing to offer you which you do not already have, because despite the exuberance and intensity you’ll find in some of these pages, I have not the slightest idea what I am talking about. I wrote this book not because I had any great ideas or imaginative plots to share with with the world; quite the opposite, I set about writing this book almost to atone for the indecency of having nothing at all to share. If, in the end, I have atoned for nothing, I hope these pages will at least help you understand one human life. Lest, in the end, you still do not understand me, I write you this present message directly and up front, in order that you might at least understand my intentions. I do not really recall if I began this book with the present passage or if I have only recollected it as that good old bugger Plato might have put it, but either way, in the end, it seems sensible to place this here in the beginning.</p>

<p>I don’t really know what I originally wanted to accomplish relating all of these experiences, observations, and fabrications. But I now believe, after reviewing these pages, that I’ve been trying to express <em>what people mean</em> when they say “I love you,” rather than just saying it. Saying “I love you,” just doesn’t do the trick so I’ve had to approach it in a very roundabout way with all kinds of misfirings and false alarms. And my tone and composure are already slipping…</p>

<p>When I see you in person, I say things I do not really want to say and I want to say things I do not or cannot say; and every time, immediately afterwards, I try to think about how to do it better and then I think I will do it better the next time and sometimes I do, but that’s rare and  now with this run-on sentence but my God, I am just tired of editing! My edited formal English always sounds just as stupid as my stupid English so it just doesn’t matter to me anymore. Think the thing, chop it up, say the damn things and just stick periods and commas and all sorts of marks wherever they work. No originality or intelligence or even creativity, it’s actually stupidity and laziness because it’s just easier to say the damn things however. It’s more beautiful, too, of course, but that’s an effect and certainly not a cause of modern stylistic currents.</p>

<p>I thought that if I “wrote a book” then I would find the best way to say the things I want to say and avoid or delete the things I don’t really want to say. Well, that whole idea is a sham: it doesn’t work, you face all the same problems you’ve always faced trying to communicate, the failure just takes longer. Then I thought I could atone for the failure of this book by appending this letter to the beginning. Well, I can’t, and so what? Am I supposed to feel sorry? Am I supposed to shred all of these pages, these pages that I have become? Should I apologize <em>ad nauseum</em> for even the failure of this idiotic apology-in-advance, with another apology that would probably fail just as well? (If I had any consistency, which I don’t, thankfully). Rich people like to say things like “the buck stops here,” which is exactly how I feel, except I despise the rich. The rich have enough bucks to make it stop wherever they want, so it’s interesting that when they say the “buck stops here”, “here” always seems to mean “somewhere else, later” because the buck never seems to stop. But my total store of bucks is negative, so I can confirm that indeed the buck stops here.</p>

<p>Whatever people mean when they say I love you, that’s what I’m trying to say, that’s it and I’m not promising you anything else. I just don’t know. I want you to do everything you want to do and nothing you don’t want to do. Everyone gets to dawdle along as they please but there is a thing that happens when you are writing something about something or to somebody and then at the last minute it somehow swerves toward something else because it’s like a rule of language that you’re not really allowed to just say something true about something directly to someone. Language isn’t necessarily a prison-house as Heidegger said, it’s just illegal to say what you think.</p>

<p>But what an awful book, they’ll say! I would be very satisfied with that, given that one of my chief curiosities has always been the question of why everybody does not write their own book&mdash;everybody having their own style of speaking and failing. I would be quite happy to write a terrible book, given that all the “good” books I’ve ever read were written by perfect idiots; and that most of the really smart people I know, who could write excellent books, never have. That’s always perplexed me and if my book is deemed awful, I would be all the happier to be a bad writer who nonetheless wrote a book. That is beautiful, that is something, I think.</p>

<p>Nothing recommends this book other than the intensities which were strong enough to produce it, intensities which had and continue to have nowhere else to go. Failure though it may be, failure at even being a failure though it may be, this book is my failure and I’m quite happy with it. Everyone deserves their own failure. And ultimately if one is honest about one’s failures, in the exactitude of expressing what is absolutely singular in one’s personal failures, it turns out you can write a pretty decent book if I do say so myself! And even if it’s as awful as this one, you’ve at least written a book. And then, if only you keep going&mdash;why not?&mdash;cultivating a little garden of failures that are at least your failures which you have worked so hard to earn, well then things begin to look pretty okay and a very different place far from here and later also where the buck never stops even for the poor and then you sort of <em>get how this writing thing works </em>but only for a second and then you just feel stupid and scared and you would suddenly feel more than happy if you only sold one article to one magazine but then you realize that that would ruin everything and eveything would be lost and that bad books are the only real books because at least they’re bad and at least they’re true and at least nobody wants to buy them and least you get to keep them for you and your friends, just like my favorite garden of all the gardens I’ve ever had, which is none, is the big idiotic dirt lot on the side of our house&mdash;because nobody ever wants to walk in it with me, nobody ever wants to walk in that lot with me, nobody even wants to sit in that lot with me because I never even ask them because it’s just not good as far as gardens go&mdash;and so it just sits there, empty, ugly, stupid, a waste of space. But what this means is that if our fence gets smashed down by some random person then we don’t have to worry about our beautiful garden being destroyed by some idiot and instead we can just be happy that someone honored our lot.</p>

<p>I want to walk through a dirt lot with you because then you would know for sure that I’m not walking with you because the garden is beautiful, but because you are beautiful and you make the dirt lot beautiful and I only want to write bad books because if any single person ever actually likes one, then I’ll know I must have done something right.</p>

<p>Whatever people mean when they say I love you, that is what I am trying to express here, no matter how hard it is to find on any one particular page. I’m sorry that things might not work out between us forever but if you like this book and sort of “get it” then let’s just spend time whenever we both want to and just be really honest and caring no matter how stupid and obscene that is in real life and destroy the things that get in our way, although the difficulty is destroying what deserves to be destroyed rather than what most people destroy even in equally good-spirited pursuits, namely each other. We might never know what to do or say but if you read this book and even sort of “get it” then as long as we are really, truly trying to get to the bottom of things together, with no ulterior motives hiding in the wings, if there’s nothing else to gain then there’s nothing to fear and we can just laugh when we’re not sure and keep going regardless because the only way to lose is to stop.</p>

<p>Even if you leave me one day for good, that would be fine because I am trying, and I trust that you are trying, and everyone has the right to dawdle along as they see fit. We can all do everything we want if we just let each other and this is not issuing from the perspective of poorly digested religions imported from the East or New Age spiritualism or the Christian heritage of the United States or the teachings of the great Rabbis or Marx or Lenin—fuck them all for they have all failed us so far—but from the patient and rigorous experiences, observations, and fabrications that I am. What else do we have left? Whatever people mean when they say I love you, that is what I’m trying to say, and why not?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A thought on jealousy]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/14/a-thought-on-jealousy/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-14T15:10:04+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/14/a-thought-on-jealousy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When one person is jealous of another, that jealousy can be oppressive for the other, of course, but it can also be perversely comforting: Jealousy <em>is</em> flattering. And in the most dangerous cases, rather than balance each other, the oppressiveness and the comfort fuel each other. If the oppression of jealousy is intolerable and even debilitating, the comfort that is supplied by its flattering component can begin to feel all the more needed. This perverse need or desire for the flattering insecurity of the other can lead the coveted person to continue in behaviors that effectively encourage the covetousness under which they are oppressed, rather than simply confront the jealous person and defuse these obviously unhealthy dynamics. In fact, this dynamic is so dangerous because of its final step: this process tends independently to <em>create</em> and <em>drive</em> jealousy because the person who is oppressed but unable to speak about it makes the jealous person fear—this time <em>rightfully</em>—that the other is hiding something. And, to boot, because there is a flattering component in jealousy, the jealous person is unfortunately and unconsciously encouraged to maintain their jealousy insofar as they observe how the other takes solace in it, however perverse and subtle that solace may be.</p>

<p>By starting this illustration with the jealousy of a jealous person, it might seem that I have set out to describe the perverse effects of jealousy. Although this is true, it is far too easy as it simply flatters our prejudices against a naive conception of the jealous persona, and would merely encourage the scapegoating of individuals for what are inherently social and political problems. The most radical implication of the process I&rsquo;m describing has not so much to do with the effects of jealous people, but the conditions for the very possibility of jealousy itself. That is, if one person is sufficiently oppressed by even the perception of someone else&rsquo;s insecure covetousness, or if the projection of a jealous other is ever simply a defensive mechanism for pushing one&rsquo;s own fears and insecurities onto an other, then at work here could very well be a very base-level mechanism for the possibility and <em>production</em> of jealousy in the first place.</p>

<p>For what is most interesting about the process discussed above is that, strictly speaking, it does not require the original jealous person to be jealous. The jealous person might not even be jealous or their jealousy could be quite mild and they could be quite willing to change if confronted, but the process could still launch from understandably defensive strategies on the part of the other seeking only to deal with their own essential and perhaps even primordial insecurities. Still, this process would tend to produce real jealousy even if there was none to begin with.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The radical core of conservatism]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/03/the-radical-core-of-conservatism/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-03T03:45:13+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/03/03/the-radical-core-of-conservatism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nobody wants to feel as if there is a &ldquo;big Other&rdquo; against which one has to defend oneself. Most people do generally want to learn about new ideas and the perspectives and experiences of others; I even think many people would be generally open to hearing marginalized voices and trying to understand how oppression works, but nobody wants to learn about new and strange ideas if they see those ideas as a pre-written doctrine which they&rsquo;re simply being told to accept. This is the radical, anti-authoritarian kernel of conservatism: the resistance against new ideas and vigorous reform is often, at its root, a refusal to trust authority—perhaps most often it is the refusal of the uneducated to trust the authority of the better educated. This is a tough and surprising point for educated radicals, but it is real nonetheless: normal bourgeois folks reject and loathe the earnest radical because the radical wants people to believe ideas with which scarcely anybody has the time or resources to ever become familiar. Our society tends to distort and confuse nearly everything in whatever way will make it as reactionary as possible, and the distribution of education is exemplary in this regard. <em>Skhole</em> —the Platonic word for the real leisure required for thinking—is attained by so few that whatever can be found there is doomed to be despised by everyone who has been excluded. Education is a cave no less than ignorance. Privileged or oppressed, no one&rsquo;s thoughts, words, or expressions are immune from accidentally contributing to a repressive society because the <em>effects</em> of even the most genuine, real, and true thoughts are determined quite apart from their authenticity, reality, and truth.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Non-linearity in reflection]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/19/433-non-linearity-in-reflection/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-19T23:20:32+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/02/19/433-non-linearity-in-reflection</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The problem with self-reflection is that it&rsquo;s a non-linear system. Under certain conditions, the smallest kernel of anxiety grows exponentially because we feel anxiety about having anxiety. And the smaller the original anxiety—that is, the more trite the original problem—the more ashamed and embarrassed we are for even feeling it in the first place, and the greater the rate at which the original minor anxiety morphs into a generalized neurosis.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
