<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: insurrection | Justin Murphy]]></title>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/categories/insurrection/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-07T11:45:44+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[j.murphy@soton.ac.uk]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Corbynism and Fuck Parades]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2015/10/02/why-corbyn-supporters-should-support-events-such-as-fuck-parade/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-02T13:28:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2015/10/02/why-corbyn-supporters-should-support-events-such-as-fuck-parade</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Not a lot of time right now but I want to quickly say some things about some of the recent events. My thoughts are somehow really simple and obvious but also seemingly under-reported perhaps because they are also somewhat ridiculous; that they might seem ridiculous is an index of how ridiculous is our current alienation and separation.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s interesting to see how Class War&rsquo;s recent &ldquo;Fuck Parade&rdquo; made quite a splash. There is probably a reason why a good old fashioned, lightly riotous march could produce some ripples it wouldn&rsquo;t have produced last year. Totally surprising, unpredictable election results; the sudden appearance of a proper socialist at the head of Labour, after so many said it wouldn&rsquo;t happen. Whenever ruling opinion is flatly contradicted by <em>events</em>, it increases our capacity to be moved by events; thus a lightly riotous march might be perceived to <em>mean something</em> now, to indicate something <em>happening</em>, and so more people will actually talk about it, think about it as a live thing that might point to something else, and so on. It can&rsquo;t be stressed enough how significant are these most minor tears in the fabric of fake status quo tranquility. Honestly I think seeking media attention is one of the worst red herrings in all of activist wisdom, but when it is received in spite of itself&mdash;try to think up something less &ldquo;media friendly&rdquo; than a &ldquo;Fuck Parade&rdquo;&mdash;it is hugely valuable as a <em>signal</em> of the status quo&rsquo;s fractures. It proves there are new openings, new connections, new corridors to rush down&mdash;new lines of flight, if you please&mdash;in this weird place they call society, which is, of course, nothing more than a weighted average of what it is perceived to be.</p>

<p>This is why it&rsquo;s so important we don&rsquo;t split up and divide the events in the world according to the episodic framing provided by the media. Duh&mdash;I know&mdash;but no, really. We all do this, so badly. When liberals perennially disavow militants, and militants perennially disavow liberals, it is basically a lived sociological version of what the media does when it reports any kind of resistant political behavior as discrete and separated episodes. Even the enlighted refusal to get caught up in these sociological distributions is, obviously, one of many very well-worn ruts in the status quo fabric.</p>

<p>There aren&rsquo;t all these little events which we either agree or disagree with, identify or disidentify with&mdash;the Corbyn surge, Fuck Parade, etc. There are simply lots of people asserting themselves against status quo institutions in all kinds of new ways, and then there is a set of status quo institutions which chop it all up to reduce it to status quo correlates. Even the radical commentariat is about as bad in this regard as the mainstream media. Revolution means all of us becoming events with each other in ways which are not ultimately reduced to current, status quo correlates. It would be a kind of mass departure from what they call reality, finding ourselves in actual reality, pleasantly unrecognizable to them.</p>

<p>In my view, Corbynism and Fuck Parade are the same thing. Events of human beings becoming themselves against status quo institutions, they are just channelled by sociology into different styles, performances, vocabularies, and identifications. To agree with one or the other&mdash;I could not think of a less interesting question. The only question is: in what way can I become a Corbyn and a Fuck Parade and a FocusE15 mum and myself, more authentically (yea I said it) and more dangerously than I ever have, in a way that draws from and feeds back to others becoming their own monstrous concoctions? Very many people think this is masturbatory Deleuzian bullshit but it&rsquo;s not; it&rsquo;s actually more concrete, practical, and credible than any other model I&rsquo;m aware of.</p>

<p>I want to see Corbyn and some Corbynites show up to the next Fuck Parade. Walk in the back or middle, don&rsquo;t have to support anything in particular but refusing to condemn anything. I want to see radicals not putting down Corbyn or Corbynites; not necessarily oozing with confidence but at least not putting out a fire themselves simply because they believe it will be put out eventually. Ridiculous idea, right? But imagine! And why not? It&rsquo;s not like radicals would lose power or momentum, they have very little of either left to themselves. It&rsquo;s not like Corbyn would lose elite respect, he doesn&rsquo;t have any to lose.</p>

<p>The main final point I want to make is that Corbyn and Corbynites actually really really need things like Fuck Parade. This one is not a provocative thought experiment, I mean that very strictly speaking.</p>

<p>Corbyn is smart and honest enough to admit he will not be able to do anything without a mass movement. He is referring to the simple maths of power, but the point is poorly understood and under-reported. The reason no Corbyn has yet to save us is because status quo institutions do not permit a Corbyn to save us. The status quo functions exactly as it should based on the current distribution of power in our society, and the laws and norms of society are precisely those which secure the current distribution of power (duh, that’s why they are there, right?). Ergo, the only possible way Corbyn could ever deliver significant but currently prohibited political and economic change is if the final variable of the equation gets a massive increase: the power of the people must literally force the stakeholders of the status quo to prefer Corbyn’s policies to what the people will do in the absence of Corbyn’s policies. When Corbyn refers to a mass movement—if he is sincere—that “mass” cannot refer to anything other than a wide diversity of folks asserting themselves against the status quo in diverse ways. It means a generalised proliferation of autonomous energies currently blocked by status quo institutions, which implies disruption of that status quo order and therefore dangerous consequences to different degrees at different times, to those invested in status quo institutions.</p>

<p>Thus, even if you are personally opposed to engaging in property destruction and foul language—such as Class War’s Fuck Parade smashing some windows here and there—you can’t sincerely wish for Corbyn to succeed <em>and</em> wish that all other human beings obey all law and etiquette. Anyone with this profile of positions is in bad faith. It is not even that, as the Stalinists would say, you can’t have an omelette without breaking some eggs. You are more than welcome to have an omelette with dairy-free egg substitute. Rooting for Corbyn and condemning Fuck Parade is like asking for an omelette, refusing to cook it, but also asking that <em>nobody else</em> cook it.</p>

<p>Not only is the proliferation of disruptive militancy necessary for Corbyn to make a dent in British politics, the more militant is the mass movement the more successful Corbyn will be. I refer to the well-documented phenomena known as the “radical flank effect.” Currently, mainstream opinion casts Corbyn as a looney-lefty too far on the fringes of respectable “realistic” opinion to be taken seriously. If there were groups of people blasting music and smashing windows in openly declared class war <em>across the UK</em>, suddenly Corbyn’s positions would become only centre-left and realistic by comparison. This would tend to pull currently skeptical centre-left voters toward Corbyn, as he would begin to seem more realistic and reasonable (and just to shut up all those troublemakers). If militant mass movement grew and escalated further, it would be in the rational self-interest of status quo stakeholders to cooperate with Corbyn, even giving him currently unthinkable political concessions, in the attempt to deligitimate and buy-off the unruly bunch.</p>

<p>If you honestly support Corbyn, your only available critique of Fuck Parade is that it remains too rare—and still too polite.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One way to end the government is to become ungovernable]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2015/05/17/becoming-ungovernable/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-17T13:15:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2015/05/17/becoming-ungovernable</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4>Reflections on social science, honesty, insurrection, communism, carts, and horses.</h4>

<ol>
<li><p>I took a bus from Southampton to attend the Radical Left General Assembly in London last Thursday night. I took the trip for two special reasons. The Tory victory completely flummoxed political scientists, so as a political scientist I was especially curious to see how London radicals would start filling this cognitive vacuum left open by the systematic errors of the official intelligentsia. But as someone who came into ultraleft politics through Occupy Wall Street, I have to admit the second reason I went to London that evening: I once again fell for that last temptation of the sad insurrectionary, the hope that someone else might kick off somewhere else. A few people asked me to report back and some others asked me what I thought about it. Here is my report back. There were a lot of people there. Different people said most of the usual things. It was kind of interesting at times and not at others. Most of the time all I could really think about was the image of a cart in front of a horse. Here are my personal thoughts on it. I want everyone there to succeed in everything they want to do and I’m going to do everything I can to help, no less and certainly no more.</p></li>
<li><p>As the internet fills with what everyone thinks everyone else should do now that the Tories are in power, here is what I’m <em>not</em> going to do. I’m not going to criticise the Assembly or any of the ideas expressed there. I’m not bothered. I’m glad to see anyone saying and doing anything they want, whether I think it’s ridiculous or not.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> I’m certainly not going to propose my brilliant vision for what everyone else should do. If there is anything I would criticise, it’s the way that our deep-seated, individual wills to power require us to express judgment of others and seek recognition from them at the same time. But I’m not going to criticise that because the only motivation for doing so is to feel smart and powerful. I don’t want to feel smart or powerful, I want collective liberation immediately. We have lots of people who are smart and who present themselves powerfully, but we do not have enough collective liberation. While correlation does not necessarily imply causation, my own wager is that there is a causal relation here.</p></li>
<li><p>Most people in the pacified capitalist democracies do not live human lives and few of us still aspire to; I don’t blame anyone, for we have been robbed and we may any day take back what belongs to us, I just think it necessary to take an honest measure of things. I’m not romantically speculating on a mythical age, it is an empirical fact that while humans persist life itself has long been going extinct. While this deserves more empirical attention than is possible here, everything seems to indicate that all of our very capacities for participating in meaningful relationships and taking risks for principled ethical convictions—essential features of any truly human life and certainly basic requirements for any liberal pluralist fantasy of organising out of contemporary domination—were unfathomably stronger across many countries even forty years ago.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> One can debate the details but to speak about movement-building while not seriously reckoning with fundamental changes in the most basic capacities of human beings cannot help but reek of bad faith.</p></li>
<li><p>People have meetings and assemblies to talk about how to stop a government. I was barely convinced that it was worth getting out of bed today and I hardly live up to my part in one or two good human relationships but OK, I’ll vote on a resolution to stop the Tory government, because that <em>sounds like</em> something a living human being would try to do. The only problem is that I’m not a living human being. For most people activism means play-acting the role of a good, living human being as a solution to the vexing and intolerably challenging <em>fact</em> that one is actually neither very good nor very living. I work 40-60 hours some weeks and 95% of everything I say on a daily basis is neither lying nor truth-telling but simple functioning for a status quo order which I absolutely know to be wrong. I can’t even smell the roses when I literally walk by roses on my way to work, and someone wants me to vote on what we should name our political movement against the government? I don’t want to do that anymore. I think that honesty is <a href="http://jmrphy.net/blog/2015/04/19/on-being-honestly-bad/">a kind of North star for finding roads to liberation</a>, for it is the only thing that can guide diverse people from diverse starting points to a destination that all parties can trust. I will come to the general assemblies and I will come to the demos and I will stand by eviction defenses and I will continue to write, but I won’t pretend to be alive by pretending to start a movement when I know perfectly well that my main problem, and probably ours, is precisely having lost the capacity to move and be moved.</p></li>
<li><p>There is a chasm between what it is reasonable to talk about in <em>serious</em> organising meetings—namely, goals, strategies, tactics, and movements—and what is often dismissed as merely antics, such as the art of well-timed defiant laughter, graffiti, random or systematic acts of queering, unspoken work slowdowns, <a href="http://jmrphy.net/blog/2012/10/20/revolutionary-fun/">fun</a>, the aesthetics of walking in mobs, pilfering and shoplifting, etc. These latter don’t qualify as the stuff of “serious organising,” and indeed they are not. What they are, however, are indications or measures of true human life bubbling up through the surface of institutions fortified primarily by instrumental seriousness; these are, in short, the only things in the world that could ever be worth organising, after the fact of their emergence. In other words, organising a “movement” presupposes some excess of human energy <em>already</em> circulating and beginning to escape the institutional order: it presupposes horses to which organisers believe we would do well to attach some carts. But today, those who speak of carts know nothing of horses; while this could certainly be forgiven, it is much harder to understand those cart mechanics who believe themselves independent of the equestrian. On the other hand, those who still ride horses have learned too well to steer clear of these odd mechanics.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p></li>
<li><p>All collectives which are able solve this puzzle, those which are able to become and attract healthy horses <em>and</em> build carts which fit well enough <em>behind  them</em> that the horses don’t prefer to flee the stables at night or otherwise die from exhaustion, will be the multiple centers of the present insurrection. For such beings it is always a present insurrection. But what does this imply for those, like me most of the time, and perhaps most people in the pacified Western countries, who are merely isolated, alienated, individual creatures? It follows that one crucial task is to intensify as much as possible the process of more openly and publicly becoming who one is with anyone else mutually attracted—and <em>everyone</em> can be certain of finding mutual attraction somewhere because in some sense this is the core operation of beauty itself, like the flower in bloom. Concretely, this refers to a process which can be summarised as follows.</p></li>
<li><p>First, I incrementally remove from my perception of the future those hesitations of calculation and calculated hesitations which together constitute my paralysing anxiety, but which are rooted only in the protection and extension of ultimately false, private investments in the status quo (material and symbolic). Each instance of doing this is well known to free up disalienating and inherently liberatory energies, and each ounce of this energy, being precisely the only fuel that could ever make any honest project run truly, is then invested in those with whom I believe I have the best chance of kicking something off. If they receive it and invest themselves in the same fashion, then this unit has achieved the most basic operation of what is called communism. From even the most minor of such communalisations, be they symbolic or material, limitlessly large groups of militant resistance can then be spun further. Building a movement for true social justice as soon as possible may only mean increasing the density of this web by any means necessary until everyone has freely and sincerely chosen it. Beyond a certain threshold (which some network-analytic research suggests may be much lower than one would think, possibly as low as 10% of people fully defected from the institutions and fully invested in the commons), the generalised ethical insurrection that is real communism becomes <em>a fait accompli</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>I want to gain and help spread the will to live at any cost. I don’t want to fight on a plane that’s already been vanquished. To end the new government and all other unjust institutions which dominate our lives, it is enough to become ungovernable. Such a process is as amenable to serious empirical investigation, experimentation, and, ultimately, “organisation,” as any other. But to put this horse in front of our carts in many ways requires us to let go or at least, with extreme irreverence, re-invent quite a many activist truisms, “social movement” wisdoms, and inherited routines. For instance, I doubt that the name of a “movement” is something we should ever be so bored to be concerned with, a name is something status quo investors will impose on us when our will to live has revived enough that we can be said to collectively exist. But this time around it will hardly matter because we will know better than to listen to anything other than what our comrades are saying right in front of us.</p>

<p> In this light, “organising” suddenly means something very different. It becomes a matter of gaining theoretical mastery over the empirical mechanisms of radicalisation to know and practice the concrete operations which actually increase the amount of insurrectionary energy and decrease the amount of status quo inertia in the world, developing styles of life consistent with these operations but obedient to nothing, such that we become not only able to demonstrate the real and reliable empirical mechanisms which underwrite our own trajectories of liberation and therefore make us a reasonable bet for others to risk themselves on (an instrumental aspect), but also become actual life forces which draw sincere attraction by virtue of our actual truth and beauty rather than sadly begging for it as human beings we are precisely not yet becoming.</p></li>
</ol>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I quite liked one pamphlet I was handed, though it&rsquo;s probably indicative of something that I already read and liked it <a href="http://davidcameronsspittle.tumblr.com/">on the internet</a> the day before, and the person who handed me a copy in London didn&rsquo;t have much time to chat despite my expression of interest. I don&rsquo;t blame them, I probably seemed like a cop or something, some random American dude who doesn&rsquo;t know anybody asking questions about some pamphlet. Still, taken as a whole, I could not help but read into the evening a number of possible blockages or mis-wirings in the circuits that run from different types of public communication to relationships to action and collective change.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Not to mention a slew of other maladies which have been on the rise, including depression, interpersonal mistrust, anomie, and <a href="http://www.weareplanc.org/blog/we-are-all-very-anxious/">the dominant affect of our moment: anxiety.</a><a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>It is in this space that I understand the idea of a <a href="http://www.weareplanc.org/">Plan C:</a> Trying to take seriously the reality of contemporary experiences such as pervasive anxiety through a radically creative politics of openness and the refusal of inherited but obviously failing, activist commonplaces. For instance, the vision of <a href="http://www.weareplanc.org/blog/on-social-strikes-and-directional-demands/">an updated social strike fit to the current moment.</a> Yet this is also a good example of how I am still interested in probing further what political scientists might call the &ldquo;microfoundations&rdquo; of such a macro-level vision. I fear that even such nuanced macro-level visions still beg the question of how to get the horse in front of the cart: how to catalyze enough currently non-existing human vitality in enough quarters such that there comes into existence the <em>energy required to withdraw one&rsquo;s energy,</em> let alone invest it in communism.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Revolutionary fun]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/10/20/revolutionary-fun/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-20T21:48:58+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/10/20/revolutionary-fun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Revolutionary fun is the only justified form of fun. Revolutionary fun is the fun had by playing with the power of those who have more power than oneself. Playing with the power of those who have more power than oneself is fun because it is the assertion of will over and against an illegitimate status quo. It is the enjoyment of creating anti-power. It is revolutionary because in its bold idleness it is inexplicable, enchanting, irresistably attractive. The human who can make a toy out of those who have more power is a magical creature to whom others will always wish to draw nearer. Playing with those who have more power is, in other words, an expression of <em>sheer will, </em>supported by neither material resources nor short-term instrumental calculations. Really though, it is neither magical nor even exceptional; to exercise the will is simply to be human, and to &ldquo;poke fun&rdquo; at the powerful behind closed doors is one of the most natural and common practices in the world. Because power is already levity in the face of suffering, to make light of the powerful is really just a deflation of false cruelty and a return to equilibrium. To actively and provocatively make such a plaything out of the false power of others appears as a magical inversion only because the real exercise of human will has been barred from so many people for so long.</p>

<p>This kind of fun therefore has two effects that are legitimately revolutionary—microscopic no doubt, but real nonetheless. First, it shakes the possession of power within the hands of those who hold it. A cop can easily bash the skull of a protester making some political demand, and a businessman is not phased by the dozen homeless people he passes on his way to work, because the social narrative they had to master to obtain their power in the first place—the narrative in which the strong are strong because they are superior to the weak—is exactly what gives them countless reasons for feeling perfectly fine in their brutality. Those who comfortably and without hesitation execute brutality will only be forced to hesitate, they will only falter and weaken and retreat, when they suddenly find themselves in social theatres for which they have no scripts.</p>

<p>In addition to concretely loosening the grip that the powerful have on power—we could just as well refer to the grip that power has over the powerful—revolutionary fun holds the line against the near abolition of human will altogether. It maintains a model, a memory, an instance no matter what might happen, of sheer will despite anything that might come. At a time when social control has become so solidified and the human will so thoroughly squeezed out of life; when, as in our society, even the prospect of heroic death against an enemy is barred by an enemy whose tactics involve the very impossibility of heroism—to make fun is to hold the last line of defense.</p>

<p>This holding of the last line of defense and the irresistible seduction referred to above are one and the same. In a social war such as ours, people obviously and always want what effectively defends humanity from that which destroys humanity. No matter how microscopic the mechanism may be, anything that effectively resists power and defends humans will be charming, beautiful, attractive, irresistible—and the more microscopic the mechanism the more fuzzy will be the comprehension of the attraction. Of course, unfortunately, it does not follow that everything charming and attractive is in defense of humanity. This is why the powerful have invested so dearly in learning the mechanisms of attraction. But in no way does the malleability of desire and attraction contradict the rule—nearly a tautology—that whatever effectively resists power and defends humans will be charming. If it is not somehow charming and attractive, we can be sure it is not effectively resisting power and defending humanity.</p>

<p>Finally, it is obvious that the privilege of toying with the powerful is a privilege unequally distributed throughout society. A minimum of personal security is necessary to dare and risk the real retribution of cops, bosses, teachers, bureaucrats, etc. But real tactical opportunities must not be dismissed on account of the limited conditions under which they are feasible; rather than discourage the privileged from using their privileges in the calculated, revolutionary fashion that corresponds to their social position, we should simply extend our efforts to delineate different tactical opportunities corresponding to each and every space in our increasingly differentiated social topography.  Just as the engine of an airplane looks, sounds, and functions very differently than the electronics in the cockpit because they are made of different materials and perform different functions in a larger design, the revolutionary machine will have to be composed of very different moving parts. The blueprint for a well-functioning revolutionary machine must be based<em> </em>on the critical awareness that privilege and oppression, abundance and scarcity, power and repression are distributed unevenly. This requires that the question of what is properly revolutionary activity not be confused by our hatred of privilege and the temptation to dismiss legitimately revolutionary tactics because they happen to be those of a privileged group. The critical point is to elaborate, as rigorously as possible, the various sorts of effectively revolutionary activity available to all people depending on the raw material available to them in their particular social position.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Art and bribery]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/01/31/16825969225/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-31T18:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/01/31/16825969225</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The history of art is a history of bribery. A young person who for many possible reasons was lucky enough to escape complete and total ideological subjugation in the first few years of life keeps in touch with their sense of desire, a desire for everything, a desire obscurely but undeniably not satisfied by the social organization of the life into which they have been thrown. Thus, they create, they permit themselves the curious project of ascertaining that part of everything to which they are not permitted access. For obvious reasons already elucidated, this ambition is always a fatal threat to the social system, wherever and whenever it appears. But a social system has always already evolved an almost infinite series of offers, one after another, for the individual to exchange the ambition for exiting or revolutionizing the whole system in return for some better individual offering within the system.</p>

<p>All life hitherto is the experience of being brought to a restaurant one never chose and given a menu that offers nothing especially desirable. But at this restaurant, when one decides one would rather leave and search for food elsewhere, the server begs you not to leave, promises the chef can arrange something for you, reads off one special dish after another, to be made just for you, each one a little more attractive than the last but never arriving at anything one genuinely wants to order, until he arrives at one that is just good enough for you to say, all right, you’ll take it. And the very few who politely listen to a thousand inadequate offerings before finally standing and walking toward the door? They find that the door was locked all along and, on the other side of it: a cop.</p>

<p>Interesting in this light is the practice of many restaurants to offer children crayons and paper to keep them pacified before their meal arrives.</p>

<p>So-called artists who go on to achieve successful bourgeois lives through profitable artistic work are akin to those who, after taking a look at the menu, make an announcement to leave, are met by the waiter and eventually settle on one of the very nice special dishes made “just for them,” but which, curiously, looks a lot like what the other artists are eating. Consider the <em>Salon des Refusés</em>, where the Impressionists famously took refuge. It was decreed by Napoleon. in 1863 by Napoleon. Why? Because no regime can tolerate painters of such talent breaking the rules and running around the dinner tables of the bourgeoisie; he had to give them a nice little room of their own in the corrupt and rotten regime despite which they were clearly going to keep working on their own. The true artist, the revolutionary artist, is the one who stands up, walks away, and meets his or her fate at the locked door guarded by police. When he or she gets there, such radical artists typically choose one of a few possible fates.</p>

<p>One choice is to kill oneself, an unfortunately common choice of some really great individuals. Another is to return to the table voluntarily and take something from the menu, also very common (rarely achieving fame, artists who enjoy bohemianism in their twenties in hopes of locking in middle-class security from their thirties onward).</p>

<p>A third choice is to go on hunger strike and wait until your either force-fed (your works are bought and sold by entreprenurial dealers you never even asked (Beuys, for instance, who consciously desired detachment from money but took as a <em>fait accompli</em> that his things were being bought and sold) or your dead corpse is taxidermied, polished up, and returned to the table you left (academic canonization, the exemplary case here being figures such as Nietzsche who die penniless, friendless, and delusional, completely rejected by society, only to become universally respected as an obvious genius. The popular idea of some people just being “ahead of one’s time” is an absurd ideological mystification for the simple and easily demonstrated process through which societies systematically identifies and banishes individuals precisely because they are “geniuses”, i.e. they refuse to be assimilated because they see their society better than it sees itself, but then reclaims and sterilizes their ideas which are at once too destructive of society and <em>too true</em> to be left lying around untouched.)</p>

<p>The final option is to stand up on one of the tables and suggest that everyone in the restaurant ignore the waiters, ignore the chefs, agree that the restaurant belongs to them, and proceed collectively to do whatever they all wish to do. This last option is the strategy characteristic of what is known as the avant-garde (a useful example for reasons to be elaborated below is the Situationist International and CoBrA, both of which insisted on just going into the kitchen and using what’s there to make new dishes, e.g. <em>detournement, </em>in order to subvert it according to theoretical, exploratory analyses of how the restaurant functions “normally”).</p>

<p>More urgent is the question about what is to be done given this castration faced by a critically rigorous artist or intellectual? The first is to become theoretically cognizant of its mechanisms, a work we have begun here. The second is to elucidate its implications, the first of which is the necessary, unconditional refusal by every genuine artist and intellectual to accept profit for anything he or she calls artistic or intellectual work. If one makes money from it, it’s simply not artistic or intellectual work. It’s a commodity, which is a betrayal of the inherent content of the genuine artistic impulse (revolutionary desire). Our analyses show that to profit monetarily from a production is the precise mechanism by which one volunteers to transform a potential freedom-source into a freedom-sink. Every manifestation of honesty in the history of the human intellect, as well as their consistent failures to achieve widespread and durable emancipation for anyone but a few passers of the torch in every generation, together represent an historical index of the capitalist transformation of freedom-sources into freedom-sinks.</p>

<p>The second is to form a community that is minimally but absolutely exclusive with respect to nothing other than this simple commitment, to develop one’s work as much as possible without implicating it in profit. The Situationists are an interesting example because they sensed very clearly the necessity of drawing sharp lines and rejecting those invested in the status quo, but they erred in their paranoiac politics that surrounded the line itself. For, it is not so much about the positive content of any works or ideas&mdash;it’s not even clear what content means anymore. Of chief importance today is the the relation works of art assume with the institutional status quo, the lines of the social circuitry with which it does or does not connect itself.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
