<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: miscellaneous | Justin Murphy]]></title>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/categories/miscellaneous/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-09T01:41:54-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Untitled Play about Maybe Getting Rid of a Bed]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/09/06/31012223438/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-06T16:58:25-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/09/06/31012223438</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With <a href="http://thebreadfromonesownmouth.tumblr.com">The Bread From One&rsquo;s Own Mouth</a>.</p>

<p>*</p>

<p><em>XX &amp; XY in bed, lying. Both moderately tall, attractive moderately dark-haired people, roughly 22-26 years old. </em></p>

<p><em>Enter Z, a moderately tall, attractive dark-haired man, roughly 26-years old. He walks to the foot of the bed.</em></p>

<p>Z: Why are you in this bed?</p>

<p>XY sits up.</p>

<p>XY: Good question, I really have no idea. (to no one) Why do we even have it?</p>

<p>XX: (to Z) Why are you in this room? Fuck you.</p>

<p>Z: What!? Why wouldn’t I be? It’s so easy!</p>

<p>XX: (sits up, smiling suddenly) Oh yeah, it’s so obvious! We should just get rid of the bed!</p>

<p>XY: We should definitely get rid of it right now. It’s so obvious.</p>

<p>XX: It’s so easy.</p>

<p>XY: Okay, great. Let’s get rid of it right now.</p>

<p>XX: What should we do with it? (lays back down, solemnly) I hate this bed. I just want to get it out of here. This bed does nothing for me.</p>

<p>XY: It’s so obvious. Let’s just put it on the roof. Then we wouldn’t even have to see it!</p>

<p>XX: But what about when we go on the roof? Then there’d be this dumb bed just staring at us. And when we’re not on the roof, I feel like we’d feel it’s presence coming through the ceiling or something. No, we can’t put it on the roof.</p>

<p>XY: Yeah, there is no reason to do that. That would be the dumbest thing.</p>

<p>XX: Let’s just put a really hard surface on top of the bed. Let’s negate the bedness of the bed.</p>

<p>XY: Yeah, it’s so obvious! Wait, no it’s not. It’d be so hard to find a hard surface.</p>

<p>XX: Yeah, that’d be such a pain in the ass. Granite weighs so much. It’s so stupid.</p>

<p>XY: Yeah, it’s so obvious! Let’s just move out.</p>

<p>XX: Like, abandon the bed? Yeah, that is definitely so obvious!</p>

<p>XY: Yeah, it would be so easy to leave right now. You can basically leave anywhere you want at any time.</p>

<p>XX: But I never want to see a bed ever again. There are going to be beds anywhere we go. I want to completely escape the bed as both a physical object and as a paradigm of bourgeois comfort and pacification.</p>

<p>XY: Really? Are there beds everywhere? I feel like there are never any beds anywhere. Just awake bourgeois people.</p>

<p>XX: Where is a place where there are no beds and no bourgeois people? Let’s go there. It’s so obvious.</p>

<p>XY: I feel like the bed idea is just an excuse to express and present ourselves and to also spend time together doing something “productive,” I think it’s sad we need the bed for that, so we should burn it to prove we don’t need it to write a play.</p>

<p>XY: Feel like “burning the bed” has been a funny/cool idea but just now got a really strong flash of a feeling that I think if you agreed I would maybe literally, really truly light it on fire in my room and maybe burn the house down accidentally. Really, actually felt for one second that I would definitely do that.</p>

<p>XX: Into burning the bed, turning it into an effigy to all the shit that we do not need, the feeling of ‘doing it anyway’ in the face of perhaps not immediately being able to. Re: the bed, we do not need it for the things that we do. Let’s burn it. Really, truly, let’s burn this goddamn bed.</p>

<p>XX: ALSO
I AM FUCKING AMPED UP ON JUICE AND ADDERALL
IS THIS HOW GOD FEELS??????????</p>

<p>XX: I FEEL LIKE APHRODITE AND THE ENTIRE WORLD IS MY BOW</p>

<p>XY: I think I have \~6 Word documents open, all of which I just started. I am so glad you are not in my room, but I am so glad that you are alive. I am so glad that you are a breathing, pulsing, desiring, knowing and unknowing being who is not in my room this minute but is aliving.</p>

<p>XX: I think the number of tabs I have open on my computer is directly related to the number of drugs I have taken that day.</p>

<p>XY: I feel like, uh, the little pink block with your name in it is a symbol of your, uh, heart beating.</p>

<p>XX: That’s because it is. We got to know each other as pixels, after all. Although my heart is probably beating much faster than the little pink block. Because of the adderall.</p>

<p>XY: I think this is how rich people feel by default and that’s why they get rich. I’m really glad I’m not like this by default, but instead only get like this when I’m poor and so become rich only in feelings and ideas and non-monetized digital productivity.</p>

<p>XX: I feel like Jesus said something along those lines. Right? That our richness is not measured by how much money we have, etc etc. Jesus was so radical. Maybe this is why heart attacks are so prevalent amongst businesspeople. Their hearts are beating this fast all the fucking time!</p>

<p>XY: Yea and amphetamines make people talk past each other full speed ahead—which we are even kind of doing right now, but which is totally OK because I know you genuinely care about my thoughts and feelings, you’re just overflowing with your own and I want you to do that. And I want to do that too, although I just wanted to register that a certain frantic, selfish insensitivity to the ideas or thoughts of others is possessing me right now. Like we are two really really fast speedboats zooming around a lake right now, which is OK and really fun but you also still make me so tender and I just want to register that. Uh, ok, I’m just going to keep going.</p>

<p>We had a couchsurfer from France once, he was an art history PhD student, actually, I’m glad you weren’t here because he was very handsome and I would have felt scared because I’m still a little boy probably—but he told me something that I really appreciated, and that I think in my life plan I am going to really, really sort of double-down on. His dissertation focused on American Pop Art and he said the truth is that Andy Warhol only gets so much credit for the very simple and mundane fact that he archived things better than anyone else at the time. That it’s really only about keeping good records, leaving behind a lot. Kind of like what I talk about when I talk about intensity as the only thing that matters, if you just do every single thing and record it then you’re a world historical genius. So easy. Feel like we should only ever write to each other on one Google Word Doc for the rest of our lives. We could maybe, truly, literally, write the most epic, uh, I wanna say “love letter” but you know, not trying to pack too much into that lol, just like, as a genre or something.</p>

<p>XX: Listen —</p>

<p>XX: Free bird —</p>

<p>XX: You are a fucking free fucking bird and so am I and we should like, fly around together but totally stick to own trajectories. And when we intersect, on occasion, it’ll be a cool thing and we can catch each other up on our flights.</p>

<p>XX: I like the idea of legacy but I find it unsatisfactory. Perhaps patriarchal. Because my legacy will be and already is intricately connected to the people around me, shit is relational, it is constituted by others, which is why I like what we are doing, simultaneously, constituting this relationship &amp; each other’s legacies in the process. I am going to go smoke a cigarette and maybe inhale deeply and slowly, but I am glad that you are out there somewhere &ndash; &ndash; not just somewhere, but somewhere that I have been, which is fucking cool, that we have occupied the same spaces for once in our fucking lives &ndash; &ndash;</p>

<p>XX: fly free, bird.</p>

<p>XY: Maybe good point about the desire for legacy being patriarchal. Yea, I think that’s right. It’s narcissistic and really a desire to dominate. I’d say I only want to dominate the dominators, but I don’t know if that’s OK. In the opposite direction, after our conversation last night I feel very comfortable right now sharing the silliest little micro-insecurities, because I’m prepared to release all fear of being a pathetic mess of ugly nerve endings. So I just want to tell you that in your last paragraph the last two lines made me feel really sad, actually, not for too long or anything but they really kinda made me happiness and ecstatic energy sink low very suddenly because you used the past tense and the word “once.” Those last two lines make me scared you are going to leave me.</p>

<p>XY: Also feel like I want to intersect more than “on occasion,” maybe felt tiny sad when you wrote “occasion.” Feel like I intersect with my family “on occasion” and I don’t really ever want to hang out with them that much. These few things make me scared you are going to leave me, they really feel shitty and scary. Trying not to act tough.</p>

<p>XX: Don’t act tough, toughness is stupid. It’s so obvious. I’m scared you’re going to leave too &ndash; when I went outside to smoke I thought about how great all of this is but how absolutely terrifying. I keep telling people that I came here to fail, which I find kind of funny, but of course affirming the possibility of failure is very different than affirming the failure itself. But, for what it is worth, my heart is ‘soaring’ (more bird/flight imagery) when I think about what has happened &amp; will continue. I do find it interesting that I am choosing to use flight imagery, but less maybe to point out the leaving and maybe moreso to point to the ‘touching down.’ The taking a breath, which is a really important part of flying but isn’t really talked about, taking a rest and then, maybe most beautifully, the deep breath before the next take-off. With you I am taking breaths! It’s such a cool thing to share with someone. In any case, I feel super positive about you —- wow positive is such a silly word but I won’t delete it — and I am really excited/terrified.</p>

<p>XX: Also, you know, I feel insecure all of the time. And not in the sense that all the time I am in a state of insecurity, which is obviously not true, but that, you know, I carry them with me. They are like kids screaming on the back of a school bus, and I’m like the driver, and getting them to shut up is a lot harder than just arriving at a stop and making them get off.</p>

<p>XX: “Get off my bus, you punks.”</p>

<p>XX: &lt;3</p>

<p>XX: lol</p>

<p>XY: Aria can you just not use the past tense talking about me or us? Like, unless it’s past.</p>

<p>XX: okay. I won’t.</p>

<p>XX: I won’t. I am wont to want you.</p>

<p>XY: What scares me is that this sort of high speed stream of consciousness dialogue maybe reveals things we might not reveal consciously—so it’s sad you used the past tense. And diminutives such as “on occasion.” It’s ok, of course! It’s just that I feel more like I’m soaring and want to keep soaring and not really breathe or stop or intersect with you but just like we’re both soaring, so simple to me, so obvious and amazing heh.</p>

<p>XX: “WHAT HAS HAPPENED &amp; WILL CONTINUE.”</p>

<p>XX: You know, lovebirds got their name because they actually cannot psychologically exist without another around. A friend of mine had a single lovebird and one day it started puking up its food — in any case it created a little puke-statue dovebird that it hung out with. I don’t know why I bring this up except maybe to say that if you weren’t around I might make a puke statue to you. This is my way of showing affection, heh.</p>

<p>XY: I’m not worried about becoming attached like lovebirds, because I have been feeling exactly as happy when you are in my physical presence as when you’re not—and we’re both rad independent ambitious folks so i’m just not worried on that front. because i’m not worried on that front, i want to only use the fucking realest most courageous and scary but beautiful language toward you and with you and about you. i want to not be afraid to feel and say crazy shit that’s only real and big and awesome. and if it’s not intense then i don’t want to say feel or do it, or something. feel like that is how we are powerful, or how we can become the kind of powerful we have alluded to before, like i think that’s the only way we can take over the world—didn’t that come up, taking over the world or something?</p>

<p>XX: OK, another random micro-insecurity: things will not always be so intense, arent’ there lulls and landings and breaths in every relationship? What if it is not so intense anymore? Or for a while? Taking over the world did come up. I feel like I can do that w you.</p>

<p>XY: Exactament! Uh, I think you’re totally right of course that lulls and landings come up, for sure! But they’ll come whether we want them or not—so I guess I’d rather just formally declare war on them, anyway. Might as well. Like I don’t want to produce more of them then are necessary just because we know they’re inescapable—with you Aria I want to destroy all lulls, landings, bores, bourgeois, breaths, parties, hangouts, cheap talk, small talk, fluff flarther furthings and even fun—to hell with it all, I just want to be, like, real, and intense and insane and beautiful and truthful, and if you want to with me then I will try to do that so hard, yea.</p>

<p>XX: Destroy all parties. The only way we’ll get there I think is by being honest. After our conversation last night I similarly feel ready to really open up to you. I really want to do that with you, I want it so badly and I am prepared to put every bit of myself towards it. Like, really, I am, yes I say yes I will yes.</p>

<p>XX: Let’s burn the fucking bed.</p>

<p>XY: (Lights match.)</p>

<p>XX: (Pours….kerosene? Gas? Olive oil!)</p>

<p>XY: Fin?</p>

<p>XY: Go do something beautiful, yea? We can talk plenty later!</p>

<p>XX: Okay. you do the same. Meet u in the sky.</p>

<p>FIN.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dialogue on Trying to Live a Revolutionary Life]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/09/06/30998215017/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-06T11:59:45-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/09/06/30998215017</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With <a href="http://thebreadfromonesownmouth.tumblr.com">The Bread From One’s Own Mouth</a>.</p>

<p>*</p>

<p>Barclay Shields: At a time when deeply ideological&mdash;and deeply conservative&mdash;ways of thinking and behaving have become so entrenched, when mechanisms of social control have become so pervasively solidified, the most truly revolutionary life might not even look political. That would be pretending we are still politicized subjects! In an era such as ours, a truly revolutionary life might not even dabble in what is thought of as radical politics, agitation, or organizing, practices which are themselves, especially in their ideologies (of self-sacrifice, discipline, instrumental calculation, personal profit, etc.) so much a function of contemporary bureaucratic capitalism&mdash;but might rather commit to creating a new effectively revolutionary subjectivity that fractures that inert base of contemporary depoliticization in order to once again make political organizing possible. But the specific dilemma I’d like to note is that the bureaucratic, capitalist contamination of contemporary activism and organizing quickly pounce on any freshly radicalized individual, sterilizing everything that is potently, contagiously revolutionary about all fresh converts&mdash;namely, naivete, zeal, impatience, intransigence, and that paradoxically fearless joyousness that always follows from properly lucid realizations of hopelessness. I think this explains my dissatisfaction with currently available forms of political activism and, not to mention, incidentally, feelings you and I have shared about the legitimately revolutionary significance of true love&mdash;how an absolutely committed, defiant, and public love between even two people could be provocatively disruptive if only all the commonly fascist baggage is successfully resisted.</p>

<p>The Bread From One’s Own Mouth: On this topic I certainly agree with much you have articulate to me, both in this current conversation and in those countless others we’ve entertained previously. On this topic I’ve been particularly occupied with the notion of newness, which appears as a foundational point of contact for Hannah Arendt. According to her, humans have the unique capacity for newness, which she calls &ldquo;natality.” Not only is natality humanity’s paramount achievement, it constitutes the primary condition for political engagement. This concept seems especially fitting now, not only as we both attempt to construct for ourselves a revolutionary life-looking, but also within this historical moment, in the shadow of Occupy, the Arab Spring, drone strikes, global capitalism. Although Occupy prompted mass action &ndash; indeed, in some sense it seemed to bring into being a new polis, or public/political space &ndash; it’s time of natality has clearly passed. This became particularly evident, or even inevitable, after the encampments were violently suppressed, which I believe is a major source of its current transition into the more conservative activism that you describe. The political actor no longer feels the vibrancy of this contemporary polis (I say contemporary polis because what was created during Occupy was not only a space for conversation and action, but the whole of human living &ndash; that is, alternative medicinal resources, safety, food, education, etc, which is obviously dramatically contrasted from the Greek polis). How does one construct a similar space of freedom when space is continually, relentlessly, ‘pounced on,’ as you put it, either stifled entirely or simply subsumed by the activist industrial complex? Perhaps more importantly to me, how does one construct such a space without leaving people behind &ndash; not inclusive in the sense of political representation, but one that incorporates friends, family, those against and with whom I constitute myself? Those who perhaps exist on a different political or social terrain than myself, but on whom my freedom is nonetheless contingent? Like my mother, for instance, a woman whose freedom I value as much as mine own, and yet who has vastly different ideas about life-living? My relationship with you, of course, is of a different matter entirely, as a love that is absolutely committed to revolutionary life &ndash; indeed, a love that has become one of the defining characteristics of it!</p>

<p>BS: Right, I think all of that is understandable and I’ve thought some of those things myself. But my fear is that in trying to share our own deeply cherished feelings, positions and visions with others who don’t share them but who might if only we could communicate them&mdash;my fear is that it might practically require such an attenuation of them that it effectively amounts to a betrayal of them. Their authentically lived qualities&mdash;the exuberance and joyously fearless overzealousness I mentioned before&mdash;always gets lost when “politicizing” others becomes the goal of some specific activity rather than the necessary social effect of exhibiting a life as emancipated as possible. In other words, it could be that in the attenuation of energies required even in the simple, specific activity of “sitting down to have a conversation” with one’s little brother or whoever it might be, we are already basically volunteering to omit precisely what is most irresistible and most convincing about our perspective! Namely, that it makes us stand and jump, run in the streets, yell at cops, demand higher wages, demand respect, act out against institutions infinitely more powerful than us, travel, write, cry, all happily, publicly, proudly. It’s precisely these things we fail to do when we go out of our way to organize the depoliticized or educate friends and family. We give them everything boring, unconvincing, and dismissable (“OK Justin, we get it, you’re the youthful idealist in the family, but nothing is ever going to change!” rather than what is irresistible and undeniable (“Uh, what country is Justin in? Ever since that Occupy stuff I haven’t seen or heard from him in years, but he’s always writing crazy shit on the internet… He’s in love, too, it seems? He doesn’t seem to work much or care about anything I care about, he never even pays his bills or debts! Hmm, maybe things are changing…”). In other words, I feel the same things you’ve communicated, but I actually think the best way to care about others is to have as little respect for the status quo as possible, even the status quo that exists inside of them. To love the status quo inside of someone is simply to hate them, sweetly. The best way I can love someone, and refuse to leave them behind, is to live as forwardly, radically, and defiantly as possible. To show them and anyone else who&rsquo;s paying any attention what can be won from fighting for a new subjectivity, something that I think is very much on the table for us, precisely because a radical political subjectivity hasn’t been widely on display or widely available for decades in this country. And finally, I think the difference between the original explosion of the Occupy movement and its sort of post-orgiastic “organizing” agenda currently is precisely this difference: that at first, it was exciting precisely because it heralded an emancipation of everyday life, but as soon as it degenerates back into the status quo of behaviors and practices available and unattractive for years, of course it has lost potency. I suppose it&rsquo;s precisely coming out of this experience that to me, now, the path forward is the selfish-sounding but I think politically and ethically defensible commitment to emancipating myself from the status quo intensely as possible, in order to legitimately become political force rather than trying to organize its absence.</p>

<p>TBFOOM: I think my question, though, is not concerned at all with diverging from a revolutionary life, which by this point both of us clearly and resolutely aspire to and for. However, such a potent decision must content with the absolute fact that such a life does not, purposefully does not, defiantly does not, fit into life itself. It is at once a rejection from life as we know it and the absolute affirmation of life, a new life, a world-building affirmation. And those that cannot bear to reject this life instead sacrifice themselves to it. Sacrifice, in fact, seems to dominate the activist ethos and the activist’s self-image. It strikes me as quite Christian in origin, inherited from martyr narratives. Coincidentally enough, “burning out” is a phrase used to describe the logical outcome of the activist’s sacrifice, which strikes me as superbly reminiscent of a martyr’s burning at the stake, but that is beside the point. It seems clear that the question is not one should prevent burnout, but rather, what is it about the current paradigm of activism that is lending itself to this idea of sacrifice? I would argue that the difficulty of committing to a revolutionary life can be found in its outright rejection of self-sacrifice, and why conversations concerning political activism always return to the boring binary between revolution and reform, both of which ultimately return to the concept of sacrifice: with reformism, that sacrifice takes place in the form of an agreement between the subjects in the state, wherein both agree or consent to the others’ demands. With revolution, that sacrifice is ideally or in theory more short-lived &ndash; and is made in exchange for the outcome of the revolution itself, whether that be equality, the distribution of wealth, death to the aristocracy, etc &ndash; but nevertheless still presents itself as an inevitable component of such. This is where anarchist theory really comes in handy, in that the most basic action to which subjects are called is to live an autonomous and self-sovereign life, a will-full life.</p>

<p>BS: Yeah, it&rsquo;s seems a sort of really insidiously conservative, ideological trap that to do organizing work seems to require the betrayal of precisely the lived reality of one&rsquo;s own desires&mdash;the meetings!&mdash;a betrayal of the sovereign, omnidirectional intransigence that radicalism implies. There is a sort of prohibition on what the radically emancipated fulfillment of one&rsquo;s desires actually looks like, precisely what could be perhaps the most revolutionary and sort of contagious activity, all in the name of trying to empower people who often suffer first and foremost from the forced depoliticization of their desire! It makes sense that contemporary capitalism will tolerate activist organizations so long as they prohibit their members from pursuing or spreading their own committed emancipation! &ldquo;Organizing,&rdquo; the very term, presupposes that the people to be organized are in fact political subjects. But what if the problem is precisely that we&rsquo;ve become so depoliticized that, on some level, we&rsquo;re not even political subjects? If this is the case, then most of what is called activism or organizing is not only going to be consistently and disappointingly unaffective, but it will also be&mdash;convenient for the status quo&mdash;actively repressive of the only activity privilege is good for, namely, unprofitable or we might say antiprofitable expenditures toward the creation of anticapitalist values, i.e. countercultures. And as if this is not convenient enough for the status quo, this particular distribution of priorities currently so common to Serious Radical Activists is reinforced even more by an often knee-jerk and tactically uncritical way of thinking and speaking about privilege. Specifically, we sort of police each other, in our shared disrespect for unfair privileges, into living and behaving conservatively rather than revealing and exhibiting precisely that to which it is such a travesty for us to have disproportionate access! Because we are aware of the injustice of our own privileges, we’ve developed an immobilizing neurosis around these privileges rather than using them to bite the hand the fed them to us. When we modestly “resist” our privileges, we think we are being educated, discipline radicals, but really we’re covering up the crimes of a capitalist distribution. We ought to use our privileges openly and provocatively, living freely and immodestly, irresistibly and politically, not only because we deserve freedom as much as anyone, but exactly in order to politicize a desire for them among those who ought to be up-in-arms for having been deprived them!</p>

<p>TBFOOM: I agree that one cannot simply hope to negate one’s privileges, as they are built on material borders, injustices, and inequalities, but instead one must try to enliven them to their own destruction, so to speak. Along those lines, in questioning the political capacity of the contemporary subject, I am reminded of much of the radical and critical theory written in the past 50 years or so, particularly Judith Butler&rsquo;s work, which sets out to do exactly that: to problematize the subject. I do not think it’s a coincidence that theory is commonly conceived of as, if not the complement to praxis, it’s apolitical antithesis! The oft-exaggerated binary between theory and practice goes hand-in-hand with the outright aggression towards academics, philosophers, and more generally thinkers, which has been increasing over the past 60 or 70 years. What’s happening is a widespread and systematic repression of thinking itself. Yes, thinking, what a seemingly silly concept but one that is dangerously real nonetheless. Not only can we no longer trust in the existence of a subject equipped for politics, we can no longer taking for granted that there is a politics towards which subjects can turn to at all. There needs first to be the possibility of politics to occur. This is why I find that much political philosophy is no longer useful, despite it’s long tradition that began, arguably, with Plato. The question that needs to be asked now is not what one’s utopian model of democracy looks like, and then setting about to cast subjects towards this model, but instead questioning the very possibility of politics &ndash; and a political subject &ndash; entirely.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Windowpain]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/08/20/29858546699/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-20T19:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/08/20/29858546699</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With <a href="http://thebreadfromonesownmouth.tumblr.com">The Bread From One&rsquo;s Own Mouth</a>.</p>

<p>*</p>

<p>Once upon a time, there was a young woman named Jane Henrietta. She was a very angry young child, never listening to any kind of authority figure who crossed her path. One morning, she woke up and said “Fuck this shit, I’m going to go smash some windows.” On her way to the window store, she ran into 15 girls on bicycles. A girl gang. Jane Henrietta had no idea what to do. At first Jane Henrietta felt scared and she felt sort of full with hatred but then she also felt full of love and wanted to be in the girl gang. She realized that the hatred she had for the young women was due only to herself not being in the gang. So she thought she might be welcomed into the gang if she went to the window store and was sufficiently provocative and radical in her destruction of the windows.</p>

<p>“Hey you,” said one of the girls, the biggest one of all. “You have to be a feminist if you want to run with us.” Jane Henrietta didn’t know what a “feminist” was. She had only seen them on TV, huge bear-chested women, burning men alive on stakes. The idea sort of appealed to Jane Henrietta, and she agreed.</p>

<p>And so Jane Henrietta proceeded to the window store. When Jane Henrietta arrived at the window store where she originally planned to destroy windows, she realized that it might make more sense in the intermission to be a practically effective feminist, getting a job at the window store instead of breaking things. So she went to the counter, and she requested an application. She then left the store and on her way home she ran into the gang of young women on bikes. One of the girls who saw her exiting the window store with a job application shouted epithets at her, something to do with politics or something like “capitalism;” Jane was scared and confused.</p>

<p>Little did the girls in the gang know, Jane Henrietta only picked up the job application to murder the store manager, a large burly man who had no values, no morals, and certainly no politics. Jane Henrietta got the job at the window store. And she began to concoct a plan, a very simple one indeed: at the end of her next shift, she would sprinkle a fine poison into the store manager’s coffee, which he had at the end of every day. This poison was so rare, it only existed in the depths of West Virginia. Jane Henrietta, having grown up there, knew exactly where to get it. In fact…she had a lifetime supply.</p>

<p>Jane had heard whispers around the store that a new technology for window production was about to be adopted by management. The rumors were that all of the employees could lose their jobs due to the superior production power of the window technology, but Jane Henrietta wasn’t afraid. She was not afraid of the window technology not because she thought she could do a better job or she could make windows faster or because she felt productively or economically superior to the window technology, but because she didn’t give a shit about the job and she didn’t really care if you did a good job or not, she didn’t really care how many windows she produced.</p>

<p>The new technology prove to be perfect for her plan. Sheer perfection. It produced windows in such a way that if a person were to fall into the machine…they would never be seen again. On her first training shift, her burly, sweaty boss was showing her around the new equipment. “This is how you do it, sweetie,” he said. “You just stick this here and stick that there and then you got a window.” Jane Henrietta despised him. She despised the way he called her sweetie, with sweat glistening on his upper lip. At the end of the shift, she turned and said, “Mr. Manager? Can you come over here?” He came over, his back to the open machinery and she knew this was her chance. She pushed him into the machinery, and as his body was flying backwards Jane Henrietta screamed “Anti-capitalism!!!!!!” As his body was slowly sucked away by the dominant hegemonic machineries of globalization and Western patriarchy, Jane Henrietta knew she did her job. The next day, she asked for a raise.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[local weather philadelphia]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/04/27/21940232210/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-27T19:27:59-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/04/27/21940232210</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>General Strike Google Bomb for Occupy Philly</p>

<p>Link: <a href="http://www.facebook.com/events/384999524851887">local weather philadelphia</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Full text of my interview with Temple News on the walkout and Occupy Philly]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2011/10/18/11633158771/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-18T20:22:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2011/10/18/11633158771</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>**Temple <a href="News:**">News:**</a> First, I need your year and major/exactly what you do at Temple.</p>

<p><strong>Justin Murphy:</strong> I am a PhD student in the Department of Political Science. I am in my fourth year as a graduate student. I study International Relations and my research focuses on how mass media conditions states' responses to international politics. I&rsquo;m also a TA.</p>

<p>**Temple <a href="News:%C2%A0**Now,">News:%C2%A0**Now,</a> how did you find out about the walkout?</p>

<p><strong>Justin Murphy:</strong> I work with a contingent of Temple students actively involved in the occupation at City Hall, or &ldquo;Occupy Philly.&rdquo; We have tried to keep in contact with one another to help organize relations between the occupation and the TU community. The idea of a walkout occurred to several of us independently, it being rather obvious and natural at the current juncture. Temple missed the recent effort of a nationwide walkout, so it was obvious that we should just move forward with one as soon as it would be feasible. Walkouts are happening everywhere.</p>

<p>**Temple <a href="News:**">News:**</a> What is the point of a walkout in general, and specifically this walkout?</p>

<p><strong>Justin Murphy:</strong> Simply put, the purpose of a walkout is to protest a particular institution by literally walking out of it! It is a collective withdrawal of the human participation that is the only living truth of an institution, as a demonstration that the institution is there to serve humans, not vice versa; as a reminder to those in power that, in the final analysis, it is the participants of an institution who will decide its destiny. At our current juncture, the college walkouts occurring everywhere are rather polyvalent. They aren&rsquo;t simply a protest against the increasingly dire prospects of college students, against the obviously obscene conjunction of budget cuts, tuition hikes, unemployment, and soaring student debt. The college walkouts we are seeing presently, including the one planned at Temple this Friday, link the political struggle of students to the political struggle of the 99% of people who are beginning similarly to pour into the streets out of a sense of disenfranchisement. It&rsquo;s interesting that we are sort of spontaneously rediscovering the logic of the general strike, which we don&rsquo;t have a strong tradition of in the U.S. That is, we are realizing for ourselves that the interests of college students in this country dovetail with the interests of all poor and working people everywhere; that if students are going to win the political recognition they deserve, they are going to do it arm-in-arm with the rest of the 99% also &ldquo;walking out&rdquo; of wherever they are and &ldquo;walking into&rdquo; a general public refusal of the status quo. That is why we, as in many similar walkouts happening presently, will walk out of Temple and right into the occupation of City Hall.</p>

<p>**Temple <a href="News:**">News:**</a> Do you have personal reasons for attending?</p>

<p><strong>Justin Murphy:</strong> No, I don&rsquo;t have personal reasons for attending. The fundamental truth revealed by walkouts and occupations is that all our sob stories we call &ldquo;personal problems,&rdquo; are nothing of that order! They are political problems, plain and simple: shared, widespread, the outcome of decisions made by people with power. Of course, I have typically oppressive student debt and will probably not get a job, but no personal reasons for attending. That said, of course I will attend.</p>

<p>**Temple <a href="News:**">News:**</a> Do you feel like many Temple students are in support of OccupyPhiladelphia, or do they not know/don&rsquo;t support the Occupation?</p>

<p><strong>Justin Murphy:</strong> Extrapolating from polls and what we know about predictors of public opinion, I think we can be pretty sure that at least somewhere near half of students on campus know about the Occupy movement, and of those students a solid majority of them probably have positive views. It&rsquo;s impossible to guess how many know specifically that there is an occupation&mdash;and a pretty strong one!&mdash;right down Broad Street, although most students I speak with have at least heard about it. But the reasoning for the extrapolation is simple. Polls of the country as a whole show there are more people with positive views of the Occupy movement than people with negative views. And across the country as a whole, about half of people know about it in the first place. Now, it&rsquo;d be silly to guess numbers, but we know that college students in urban centers tend to be more liberal than the median citizen. How exposed to and informed about the Occupy movement they are compared to the median&mdash;that is not very clear to me. In any event, we shouldn&rsquo;t be too concerned with who currently knows about the movement and what they currently think about it, because there are thousands of people, this very minute, actively teaching and welcoming others into this broad-based project. That&rsquo;s the point, to make people know about it and help them see why we should all support each other against a very small elite. When we march, one of the popular chants is &ldquo;We are the 99 percent!&rdquo; and it&rsquo;s not for nothing that we often throw in &ldquo;And so are you!&rdquo; while pointing at people on the sidewalk.</p>

<p>**Temple <a href="News:**">News:**</a> How do you feel about the Republican protest in front of Senator<br/>
Toomey&rsquo;s office that occurred the other day?</p>

<p><strong>Justin Murphy:</strong> If I feel anything about that, and I probably don&rsquo;t, I almost feel pity for these conservatives who always seem to end up on the wrong side of history.</p>

<p>**Temple <a href="News:**">News:**</a> Anything else you&rsquo;d like to add?</p>

<p><strong>Justin Murphy:</strong> We should caution against naive overexcitement regarding what is only a fledgling movement, but we should also not be afraid to affirm that when we walk from the Bell Tower to City Hall this Friday we will be walking into what is probably the single best opportunity our generation has ever had to be pivotal participants in American political history.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
