<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: life | Justin Murphy]]></title>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-12T23:09:31+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unsent letter to a former friend (a DJ)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2011/08/30/3018373241/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-30T22:15:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2011/08/30/3018373241</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You&rsquo;ve already become a cop! You&rsquo;re a DJ. Bars are temp agencies that hire short-term cops to repress the revolutionary desire of any potential counterculture by blasting recycled bourgeois nostalgia into everyone&rsquo;s ears all night. Just to keep people drunk and complacent for the petty profits of idiotic philistines who have nothing to offer us other than petty pedestals for accumulating petty cash, social capital, and sexual partners. I think you should quit your job as a cop and become an artist, as I believe you once were; publicly disavow every currently existing institution in the name of truth, freedom, and a better society; and then help us do away with all of this idiocy and start from scratch. If you agree with this I will respect you. If you dismiss this, then I will be forced to conclude that you are a spineless collaborator with no ideas, convictions, or anything else worth expressing. If you respond, then I trust we will have a fruitful dialogue about the culture you and I share. Needless to say, I do not acknowledge your right to make statements on Facebook free of any responsibility to account for them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[100% of my telecommunication will now be through the internet]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2011/02/02/3073952396/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-02T21:38:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2011/02/02/3073952396</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, I paid $20 to Skype for a personal phone number good for three months. Incoming calls are free (as far as I can tell) and $14 more got me credits for making calls, which are only 2.3 cents/minute. Say I speak for 5 minutes per day, which is more than I typically do, that means $14 gets me almost 5 months. I am breaking my cell phone contract ($110) rather than pay $50/month for the next nine months until my contract is over. <strong>Friends</strong>: <strong>You will find my new phone number on my Facebook page. It comes with voicemail, too. If you ever really need me, I&rsquo;d suggest you first email or message me on Facebook because I am always on both of those.</strong></p>

<p>I am doing this for several reasons:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Saving money. I hate bills and I hate cell phone companies. At $50/month that is about $600/year. At $20 every three months, and $14 every 5, that will be less than $150/year. I will save 600 &ndash; 150 = $450/year.</p></li>
<li><p>Cell phones are stupid machines. If you have a smart phone, it might not be as stupid as most but it is still stupid. They have a penchant for jumping into toilets, distracting you from more interesting things, ringing during class/meetings/conversations, breaking, and being stolen. I despise all of these things and I&rsquo;m looking forward to putting them behind me.</p></li>
<li><p>Cell phones are oppressive. To me, ignoring calls is rude and if someone calls me while I&rsquo;m not necessarily immediately busy, I owe it to him or her to pick up. Cell phones stay in your pocket all the time and they offer you no acceptable reason for not talking on the phone if you are able. In maximizing your accessibility in a sense you maximize your freedom of movement, but paradoxically you make yourself beholden to anyone calling you at any time and thus you limit your freedom (unless you ignore calls or turn your phone off, options I never found attractive.)</p></li>
</ul>


<p><em>Abolition of Phone.</em> Decision. February 2, 2011.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
