<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: life | Justin Murphy]]></title>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-12T23:24:49+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Untitled fragment]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/09/28/32424415965/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-28T00:59:18+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/09/28/32424415965</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I haven’t had fun in a whole year because I have been a serious man, an ambitious young academic who is serious. I have been putting my ducks in a row. But the ducks are getting ill. I’m getting off the duck bus, fucking idiot I am. Unless they scatter immediately I will kill the ducks unless they kill me. Every bus is a duck bus if you ask me, and you are asking me. I just ate a $3 vegan burger and now I’m at an Afghani place smoking a hookah, reading Agamben, and drawing idiotic diagrams on my iPad. There is a crisis in higher education. I am the crisis. I feel good and nice and quite right about being a crisis.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Untitled fragment]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/09/27/32401241879/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-27T18:33:36+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/09/27/32401241879</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Too hastily I ask if I can have some of her bisque and of course she says yes but I immediately feel terrible and apologize for being so quick. She says no and that it’s perfectly fine and that she feels bad for ever having not offered me anything ever, a stalemate of absolute humility being perhaps the only possible outcome of revolutionary commitments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Untitled fragment]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/09/25/32225613970/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-25T00:17:59+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/09/25/32225613970</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don&rsquo;t see why it&rsquo;s reasonable for people to look down on how we live, I mean, I think their nice apartments are truly sad and disgusting but I don&rsquo;t look down on them. I just don&rsquo;t care about them so I don&rsquo;t go to their houses and yea I laugh at them but if I don&rsquo;t look down on them then surely they have no right to look down on us.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Untitled fragment]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/09/23/32128929969/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-23T17:13:52+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/09/23/32128929969</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s Sunday now. I haven’t left, of course not. Now that I know I absolutely cannot live here anymore, I might as well just stay.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Untitled fragment]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/09/23/32127366757/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-23T16:49:41+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2012/09/23/32127366757</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Friday we need to leave behind this shithole.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
