<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: social science | Justin Murphy]]></title>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/categories/social-science/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-01T12:37:38+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dynamic map of murdered journalists, 1992-2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2014/08/01/dynamic-map-of-journalist-killings/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-01T18:24:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2014/08/01/dynamic-map-of-journalist-killings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe width='100%' height='700' frameborder='0' src='http://jmrphy.github.io//jmrphy.cartodb.com/viz/324a04fe-1a35-11e4-8f79-0e73339ffa50/embed_map?title=true&description=true&search=false&shareable=true&cartodb_logo=true&layer_selector=false&legends=false&scrollwheel=true&fullscreen=true&sublayer_options=1&sql=SELECT%20*%20FROM%20cleaned_data_table%20WHERE%20type_of_death%20IN%20(%27Murder%27)%20AND%20type_of_death%20IS%20NOT%20NULL&zoom=2&center_lat=37.85750715625203&center_lon=18.28125' allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>The original raw data can be <a href="http://www.cpj.org/killed/cpj-database.xls">downloaded here</a> from the Comittee to Protect Journalists and the lightly cleaned data used in this map can be found <a href="https://jmrphy.cartodb.com/tables/cpj_data/public/table">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some slides on 'Democracy' as propaganda for capitalism]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2014/07/12/propaganda-democracy-capitalism/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-12T15:30:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2014/07/12/propaganda-democracy-capitalism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Resisting the conventional wisdom that propaganda is mostly associated with authoritarian governments, these slides sketch how the liberal, capitalist government of the United States at the time of World War I exploited the concept of &ldquo;Democracy&rdquo; in what would become perhaps the most remarkable propaganda achievement in modern history. Includes photos, videos, historical data from Google Books, and a discussion of some recent research suprisingly consistent with this argument.</p>

<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/jmrphy/slideshelf" width="760px" height="570px" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:none;" allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A theory of ethically-biased technological change (toward an empirical test of the Frankfurt School)]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2014/06/21/a-theory-of-ethically-biased-technological-change-toward-an-empirical-test-of-the-frankfurt-school/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-21T14:58:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2014/06/21/a-theory-of-ethically-biased-technological-change-toward-an-empirical-test-of-the-frankfurt-school</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h5>The Puzzle</h5>

<p>There is a widespread consensus in the economics literature that the rise of information technology over the past several decades has been a “skill-biased technological change.” A skill-biased technological change increases the productivity of skilled workers more than it improves the productivity of unskilled workers, therefore increasing the demand for skilled workers relative to unskilled workers. This increased demand for skilled workers, ceteris paribus, <a href="http://www.dictionaryofeconomics.com/article?id=pde2008_S000493">increases their income relative to unskilled workers</a>. It is widely agreed that this is a key explanation for at least some of the rapid increase in income inequality since the 1980s.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> One key observation consistent with this theory is that it is only after the appearance of micro-computers that income inequality begins to rise in the early 1980s.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> A second key observation is that more educated workers are more likely to use a computer on the job<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Despite this growing interest in the economic implications of technological change, social scientists have failed to take seriously a surprisingly similar line of thought advanced most notably in twentieth-century German philosophy. Heidegger and, later, the Frankfurt School theorists developed critical theories of technology which argued, in different ways, that technological changes shape ethical attitudes toward the world. In particular, a specific line of thought revolves around the relationship between technological development and instrumental rationality, or in other words formal analytical rationality which renounces consideration of substantive goals and concerns itself only with calculating the optimal means toward given ends.</p>

<p>For Heidegger, from a phenomenological perspective, technology represents a &ldquo;clearing&rdquo; of Being which generates a relation to the world in which nature and other humans are merely &ldquo;standing-reserve&rdquo; waiting to be exploited as means to whatever ends. For Adorno, Horkheimer, and especially Marcuse, modern technological advancements were &ldquo;organizing and perpetuating (or changing) social relationships, a manifestation of prevalent thought and behavior patterns, an instrument for control and domination.”<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup></p>

<p>While positivist social scientists have long perceived these types of claims from continential social theory to be hopelessly speculative and empirically intractable, this is puzzling given that the core claim emerging from this particular current in the critical theory of technology is relatively straightforward: technological development increases the prevalence of instrumentalism among other possible ethical attitudes toward the world. Moreover, the theory of skill-biased technological change is a powerful heuristic for modeling this argument given that it is a well-established model of how technology can generate unequal distributions of power without any reference to Marxian bugaboos which have likely caused more confusion than clarity by now.<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup></p>

<p>However, it is perhaps more fair to observe that critical theorists indeed sometimes lack what contemporary social scientists would call “mechanisms,&ldquo; or specifiable and testable triggers which effectively do the work of some variable <em>X</em> supposedly causing some variable <em>Y</em>. While this particular critique of technological development is not delivered with any particular "mechanism&rdquo; which would be intelligible to many empirical social scientists working today, critical theory does supply many useful hints in this direction. Moreover, the basic argument is surprisingly consistent with well-known economic models, however disparate might be the vocabularies, thus permitting the elaboration of a critical theory of technological change empirically testable and consistent with a rational-choice framework.</p>

<h5>A Theory</h5>

<p>To better specify the mechanism whereby technological change may plausibly generate a greater prevalence of instrumental ethics, I propose a theory of <em>ethically-biased</em> technological change. I argue that certain technological changes can increase the income paid to certain ethical orientations relative to others. As in the theory of skill-biased technological change, certain technological changes increase the productivity of certain ethical orientations relative to others, increasing their relative demand, and therefore increasing their relative income. This increase in relative income represents a premium paid to those with the ethical resources required by the new technology, just as skill-biased technological change generates a premium paid to those with the technical resources required by the new technology.<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup></p>

<p>More specifically, a technological change which increases productivity but transgresses <em>any particular ethical value</em> will increase the productivity of individuals with the weakest commitment to that ethical value relative to those more firmly committed to that ethical value, thus increasing demand for them relative to the more ethical individuals, and thereby increasing their relative income. Ethically transgressive technological innovations increase the productivity of the least ethical because ethical compunctions are effectively a psychological tax on a worker. It is hard to take a job, and then demoralizing to work it, to the degree one feels ethical compunction for doing so. While an employer would have to pay very high wages to attract highly ethical workers to an ethically transgressive job, the wages they have to pay to attract relatively unethical workers will tend to be lower. The firmer one&rsquo;s ethical commitment, the greater is the tax one pays to work an ethically transgressive job, the less worthwhile the wage, and the less likely is one to take the job; the weaker one&rsquo;s ethical commitment, the lower is the tax, the more worthwhile is the wage, and the more likely one is to take the job. The overall implication is that technological change rewards individuals with weak ethical convictions relative to individuals with strong ethical convictions, and therefore exerts a direct, material pressure on the evolution of ethics within society.</p>

<p>There are three key, testable implications we would expect to observe if this model indeed captures important aspects of the historical record. First, during times of ethically transgressive technological innovation, the first workers will be individuals who before the technological innovation were already less ethically scrupulous on the relevant ethical dimension. Second, workers of the new technology will be paid a premium which would be, in principle, distinct from any skill premium, although of course these can be correlated. Third, if we add the assumption of modern capitalist institutions, wherein wage workers have no common land and no immediate means of production, then the price of integrity for committedly ethical individuals literally becomes death. This last implication means that, if technological change is ethically biased as I hypothesize, the steady-state to which it must tend in the long-run is the absolute evacuation of integrity from all participants in the labor market. Note that this can come about through two different causal pathways: ethical individuals can learn to sacrifice their integrity to compete with the unethical and survive, <em>and/or</em> ethical individuals can literally die off while unethical individuals thrive and replace them (evolutionary change). It should be noted explicitly that while observations 1 and 2 show how ethically-biased technological change reward certain ethical orientations differently and unequally,</p>

<p>Anecdotally, a general acquaintenace with the contours of modern history seems to suggest some striking evidence for this model of ethically-biased technology change. Consider, for instance, that while a certain amount of philosophical liberalism was no doubt necessary for the industrial revolution to emerge, and this perhaps explains why it began in England, it seems equally undeniable that the industrial revolution in turn <em>generated</em> an extraordinary instrumental turn and valorization of self-interest wherever it went. It will obviously require more work to test this expectation more rigorously, but it seems highly probable.</p>

<h5>Conclusion</h5>

<p>In summary, building from insights of the Frankfurt School, I provide a specific, empirically testable mechanism which accounts for the large-scale historical variations in ethical outlook they described to the dismissal of the mainstream social scientists of the time. Working heuristically from rational-choice economic theory, my stylized theoretical model is consistent with but more general than the rational-choice framework because the model here in some sense explains what rational-choice models merely assume (the prevalance of instrumentally rational dispositions).</p>

<p>If correct, the long-run, world-historical implication of this model could not be more staggering for understanding the ethical experience of living through modern, let alone contemporary, capitalism: if this model is correct, then it would mean that today we have inherited a world in which ethical integrity has been subjected to a roughly 300-500 year forced evacuation by labor market institutions.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>See Card, David, and John E DiNardo. 2002. “Skill Biased Technological Change and Rising Wage Inequality: Some Problems and Puzzles” and Guvenen, Fatih, and Burhanettin Kuruscu. 2010. “A Quantitative Analysis of the Evolution of the U.S. Wage Distribution, 1970–2000.” NBER Macroeconomics Annual 24(1): 227–76.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Katz, Lawrence F. 2002. “Technological Change, Computerization, and the Wage Structure.” In Understanding the Digital Economy Data, Tools, and Research, Cambridge: MIT Press.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Autor, David H, Lawrence F Katz, and Alan B Krueger. 1997. “Computing Inequality: Have Computers Changed the Labor Market?”<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>Marcuse, H. 1941. “Some Social Implications of Modern Technology.” Studies in Philosophy and Social Science, Vol. IX.<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:5">
<p>I have in mind such perennial bad habits as lazily but self-certainly referring to Capital as a conspiratorial agent, an argument which has never boded very well for Marxism.<a href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:6">
<p>Indeed, the analogy between skill-biased and ethically-biased technological change is all the more apt if we, with Foucault, conceptualize the practice of ethos as itself a kind of technical game; if ethical resources are themselves understood as technologies of the self. Key examples in this context are those most bourgeois of ethical resources: the various techniques of repressing ethical compunctions and moral anxieties, and the various techniques of guilt management consequently required by this ethos. In this register, ethically-biased technological change would be essentially identical to skill-biased technological with the exception that the &ldquo;skills&rdquo; in question are the skills of self-management rather than economic production. The reason we must avoid this reductionism at the outset is that it would beg the most important question, namely, the question regarding <em>how</em> exactly did the contemporary human become, quite peculiar in the long-run of world history, so instrumentalist that the only activities remaining in contemporary life are exploiting and suffering exploitation?<a href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On the early social science of the media]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2014/02/18/the-early-social-science-of-the-media/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-18T18:56:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2014/02/18/the-early-social-science-of-the-media</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From the 1920s until the end of World War II, the conventional wisdom was that the role of mass
media in modern society was, and ought to be, an instrument of propaganda for the optimal
functioning of the state (@Bernays:2004vo; @lippmann1932public). With the rise of information theory, which would become a basis for modern computing (@Shannon:2013iy; @gleick2011information), in the post-war period there was a flowering of social-scientific efforts to link the propaganda role of media to the burgeoning framework of information theory [@wiener1965cybernetics; @Deutsch:1953ww; @Deutsch:1966ux; @McLuhan:1994tf; @Ellul:1965uf].<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Norbert Wiener was arguably chief among the towering intellectual figures of the midcentury attempting to understand society with the new tools of information theory. Wiener named the new science &ldquo;cybernetics,&rdquo; a term which gained some limited currency at the time but has since fallen into oblivion. Cybernetics was, essentially, an information theory of society: institutions, organizations, and even social systems more generally are machines comparable to mechanic devices. What they all have in common is that their existence is sustained by mechanisms which effectively send signals and respond to signals. The mechanism in an automobile engine which prevents it from overheating is a mechanism which responds to the signal of too much heat, just as the mechanism of elections is supposed to prevent politicians from pursuing unpopular policies. Information theory would allow us to understand political power and social control as essentially, in their most basic units, dynamics of communication.</p>

<p>For Wiener, then, communication and control were the same thing, and he argued passionately that humanity was on the brink of a new age where communication and control would define society: &ldquo;The thought of every age is reflected in its technique&hellip; If the seventeenth and early eighteenth centuries are the age of clocks, and the later eighteenth and nineteenth centuries constitute the age of steam engines, the present time is the age of communication and control.&rdquo;</p>

<p>But Wiener also wrote passionately and ominously that the American state and small elite groups posed an extraordinary threat in this new age of communication and control. Starting in World War II and continuing throughout the Cold War, the US state was aggressively bringing science under its aegis. This is well-known and well-documented, but it is especially interesting that it is also reflected in the lives and thought of many of the very towering intellectual figures who were at the forefront of the new sciences. Wiener, for instance, believed firmly in the independent scientist and avoided institutional affiliations, although he did choose to help the war effort in anti-aircraft research. &ldquo;Without any doubt,&rdquo; he wrote, &ldquo;we possess the world&rsquo;s most highly developed technique of combining the efforts of large numbers of scientists and large quantities of money toward the realization of a single project.&rdquo; [@Wiener:1989ud, 126].<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>Today, the incipient social-scientific theories of thinkers such as Wiener and McLuhan appear remarkably cynical: given the longstanding conventional wisdom of elites that the media were mere tools of propaganda, the
emergence of legitimately scientific models of information quite naturally led social theorists to
conceptualize the media as instruments of social control. Thus, these early efforts are laden with
surprisingly sinister vocabularies, the most recurring themes revolving around the control,
monitoring, and shaping of mass publics.</p>

<p>These early social scientists of the media, most of whom were writing within democratic states, had
surprisingly little to say about the media having anything to do with the empowerment of the masses. This is puzzling given that, today, scholars and schoolchildren alike are most immediately inclined
to think of the media as a watchdog over government, the main purpose of which is to ensure popular
sovereignty through the free flow of information. Today, even those social scientists most critical
of media effects are exceptions which prove the rule, as they typically frame their findings as
raising questions about the medias well-known function as government watchdog.</p>

<p>If the earliest and most influential social-scientific models of the media were so cynical, then
why, when and, how did contemporary social scientists develop such a sanguine view of the media? I
do not pretend to offer any definitive answer to such questions, but we ought to float some short
and provisional answers to these questions.</p>

<p>Wiener understood the system-level of ideas and communication politics, but he was surprisingly naive to think his ethical arguments could win the day. According to his very outlook, such ideas were like &ldquo;negative feedback&rdquo; mechanisms which were purely imaginery: the nervous system he described had to discard that ethical information like our bodies discard germs. For, his ethical critique called into question the very nature of state-and-market-centered political system in the information age.</p>

<p>The extraordinary negative pressures faced by people such as Wiener and Oppenheimer and Einstein when they chose to speak out, is perhaps evidence of the political system&rsquo;s nervous system neutralizing threats. Oppenheimer&rsquo;s villainization by the state as a &ldquo;security threat&rdquo; and the humiliating trial in front of the House Un-American committee was itself an act of power and control through communication&mdash;the public was being told these people and their ethical ideas were bad, i.e. their behavior was being shaped away from such ethical principles. Wiener&rsquo;s publishers (embodying market forces), put pressure on him to tone down the political sharpness of his perspective,observable in the difference between the first and second editions of <em>The Human Use of Human Beings</em>.</p>

<p>But where did our benign democratic notions of the media come from, when for several decades the
conventional wisdom on the role of media was expressly anti-democratic and the very nature of
information was now becoming understood scientifically? This intersection in intellectual history
would seem to predict a future in which the various media would become all the more powerful tools
for small national elites to control and manipulate mass publics, the vision largely shared by so
many incipient post-war social scientists. But yet, the notion of propaganda recedes from the social
sciences from its high point around 1950, while the study of information continues increasing and
the social scientific study of media begins in earnest.</p>

<p>In some sense, these social-scientific currents which are only just beginning to theorize the mass
media with an emphasis on propaganda and information control are absorbed by government and the
private sector. It appears as if this incipient social-scientific perspective is adopted and <em>put
into practice</em> by various branches of the state, as in the rise of “counterinsurgency” abroad (Carruthers) and
government “public relations” at home, or otherwise the private commercial development of
communications engineering and “operations management.” As the new sciences of information control
are put into practice by the state and the private sector, it is at this time that the curiously
mild-mannered attitude toward the media is elevated into a baseline for political science research
(Lazarsfeld 1944; Berelson 1954; Campbell et al. 1960).<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> This baseline conventional
wisdom of “limited effects” from media would no doubt be challenged within political science, but it
nonetheless has remained dominant (Katz; Bartels 2008). That research funding distributed by the
U.S. government and the private sector played a prominent role in the mainstreaming and
institutionalization of the Columbia and Michigan models of political science research approaches,
at the very same time that information theory is being rapidly mobilized in actual state and
corporate operations and logistics, further tempts one to the hypothesis that perhaps the greatest
achievement of state and corporate media control was to have ensured that social scientists would
never quite succeed in understanding or demonstrating the media’s function in social control.</p>

<p>This is why the present detour through intellectual history is not merely a review of the literature; rather, this sociological review of the literature is itself suggestive
empirical evidence, however circumstantial, regarding a crucial transformation in our thinking and
practices of media politics. I have traced in the record of the social sciences the transformation
of media-as-propaganda to media-as-transparency to outline a general gap in the literature which
this volume contributes to filling, but also to present some provisional evidence, very close to
home, of precisely how media-as-propaganda may shape certain institutional political outcomes in
ways which have hardly been noticed. Indeed, if the media are most importantly propaganda tools
then, to the very degree they are politically effective, we would expect them to go unnoticed by
institutional social science. Indeed, even the exceptions suggest evidence for this rule, for the
most popular intellectual inheritors of the media-as-propaganda tradition today remain marginal to
dominant mainstream social science.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup></p>

<p>@Horkheimer:2009te, @adorno2001culture, and @Debord:1967vn.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>To say nothing of concurrent and parallel movements in radical, continental theory. See<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Oppenheimer, a crucial figure in the American development of an atomic bomb, would later speak out against the hydrogen bomb and was aggressively maligned as a &ldquo;security threat&rdquo; by the US government and in the mass media. Einstein, as well, was mocked for his critical attitude toward developments in the state&rsquo;s relationship to science. All of this is to point out that the most towering intellectual figures of this time were beginning to converge on the belief that the institutional dynamics of science were unconscionable.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>The Columbia group around Lazarsfeld, from the beginning, was really only interested in what was already a highly narrow and market-oriented type of behavioral variation. Bartels notes how they only turned to electoral behavior when they could not find grantvmoney to study consumer behavior (Rossi 1959, 15-16, as cited in     Bartels 2008). The point for our purposes is that these pioneering studies which would become baselines for the modern study of political behavior rose to prominence with a view of the media that already abstracted away from the more “sinister” media effects predicted by the group discussed above. Thus, by the 1954 <em>Voting: A Study of Opinion Formation in a Presidential Campaign, </em>the Columbia group finds little evidence for the role of parties and media in presidential campaigns. The later Michigan group, whose election studies would become an increasingly institutionalized backbone of American political science research, also had a view of the media which is puzzlingly inane and conservative read alongside work of roughly the same period by someone such as Karl Deutsch. Of course, I do not here take issue with the validity of these early findings as far as they go; my point is only to flag that these foundational studies in American political science adopted an approach which  generated strikingly inane findings on the political effects of media, especially when read alongside those who were grappling with the more general historical functions of media as institutions of social control.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>For instance, see @Herman:1988ta [@mcchesney2000rich; @luhmann2000reality]<a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A diagram of stratification]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/12/19/dg-stratifcation/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-19T06:53:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/12/19/dg-stratifcation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Below is a sketch of what Deleuze and Guattari describe as &ldquo;the pincer&rdquo; or &ldquo;double articulation&rdquo; of stratification.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<iframe src="http://wl.figshare.com/articles/881284/embed?show_title=0" width="650" height="424" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<p></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Deleuze, Gilles, and Félix Guattari. 1987. A Thousand Plateaus. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press. pp. 40-41.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
