<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: theory | Justin Murphy]]></title>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/categories/theory/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-23T22:35:22+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Justin Murphy]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A diagram of stratification]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/12/19/dg-stratifcation/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-19T06:53:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/12/19/dg-stratifcation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Below is a sketch of what Deleuze and Guattari describe as &ldquo;the pincer&rdquo; or &ldquo;double articulation&rdquo; of stratification.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<iframe src="http://wl.figshare.com/articles/881284/embed?show_title=0" width="650" height="424" frameborder="0"></iframe>


<p></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Deleuze, Gilles, and Félix Guattari. 1987. A Thousand Plateaus. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press. pp. 40-41.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Remodeling revolutionary agency]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/11/17/remodeling-revolutionary-agency/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-17T14:25:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/11/17/remodeling-revolutionary-agency</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When thinking about revolutionary agency, I move away from the traditional Marxian concept of the “proletariat,” a particular class which is most able to generate revolutionary resistance, in favor of a more general conception of whosever happens to fall through the cracks of capitalist subjectivation.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> I am interested in those whose thoughts, behaviors, and projects, <em>for whatever reason</em>, remain relatively undisciplined by the normalizing and neutralizing tendencies inherent in contemporary society. Is someone’s life very consistent with what the status quo expects of them, or is it very inconsistent. What proportion of someone’s thoughts and behaviors are <em>systematic</em> (predictable) and what proportion are in the statistical error term?</p>

<p>This would be consistent with, but more general than, the classical conception. Immiseration of the “workers” as in the Marxian eschatology would become only a special case of such falling through the cracks. Capitalism grinds the workers to the bottom of its barrel and the revolutionary mechanism in the Marxian view is essentially that, eventually, the workers are pushed through the barrel itself, they see the system from its outside (class consciousness), and therefore are finally free to smash the barrel. But metaphors for the “system” are just metaphors, and however we wish to model the system, there’s no reason why there shouldn’t be many conceivable pathways where individuals could find themselves (intentionally or randomly) having dodged the social conditioning which normalizes individuals into identification with the system. This would explain why and how intellectuals are disproportionately inclined to revolutionary conversion: they fall through the cracks by a totally different path, via the leisure of education, study, and creative intellectual work. But the essential logic which makes workers radical in the Marxian view could thus be unified with the same logic that makes intellectuals revolutionary. And then it would be a matter of identifying through theoretical and empirical research the necessary and sufficient conditions for individuals to escape the grid which so thoroughly shapes most individuals.</p>

<p>Capitalist subjectivation requires a layered process of ideological conditioning; the typical lifespan of a human being in the modern world is a complete archeology of layered ideological conditioning processes that would be dangerously obvious if they were not so effective: the family, where life itself begins as emotional and physical indentured servitude and continues as a process of paying back the father and mother until death; the school, where the cost of food for the social intellect is not just cultivating a taste for obedience to arbitrary authority, but contributing to its legitimacy insofar as the students’ presence constitutes that legitimacy; the workplace, where the price paid for survival outside of the family is just more uncritical submission to whatever institution which takes its place; and finally the re-production of the family itself, which is not actually a successful egress from this inherited chain of uninterrupted submissions that constitute everyday life (however much modern weddings pretend it is), it is actually just passing the buck to the next generation. Having children is merely a debt-swap in which the creditor (society) allows the indentured servant (the young adult) to escape its unpaid and unpayable debt on the condition that it produce a new person who will pay it with interest (the child). The stress, self-sacrifice, and perpetual ethical castration of raising a child today is akin to an exorbitant transaction fee for this debt-swap.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> Yea, OK, we’ll let you pass the debt on to a new person but don’t think you get freedom instantly: if you don’t pay the transaction fee that saps whatever desire might remain in you, then you will be unbearably stigmatized and ostracized as a “bad parent.” Notice that, for better or worse, the most famoulsy radical and effective intellectuals have historically been awful parents, effectively defaulting on this debt altogether.</p>

<p>To measure this concept of proletariat, we would highlight Marx’s main variable of material degradation but also intellectual and spiritual degradation, without necessarily privileging one or the other. Thus, a general formula would understand all individuals as characterized by three variable terms <em>work</em>, <em>ideology</em>, <em>capital</em> and different values under which an individual breaks from identification with the system. Thus a worker’s interest in the system is increasing in ideology and income but decreasing in work:</p>

<p> <em>u = ideology + income &ndash; work</em>,</p>

<p>The traditional Marxian theory of the individual-level revolutionary mechanism is that workers are invested in the system by ideology but the hold of ideology breaks as their labor is increasingly alienating while their income is decreasing. According to Marx, a worker becomes revolutionary when work increases and income decreases enough to <em>outweigh</em> the investments from ideology.</p>

<p>But Marx and so many of his followers never really took seriously the revolutionary positions of bourgeois intellectuals. What this reconceptualization suggests, though, is that the revolutionary defection of bourgeois intellectuals is according to the same essential conception of human beings as the theory of worker defection, only from different movements of the same variables. The defecting bourgeois intellectual receives relatively high income for relatively little work but dis-identifies with the system through decreasing ideological investment. This is simply because true education is the depletion of ideology. This also explains why as anyone’s true education increases, status quo institutions either increase their income, decrease their work, and/or dilute their ability to think and speak freely.</p>

<p>Of course, in reality, a multitude of other, additional institutional investments enter into the equation, such as family investments or racial, gendered, or nationalist investments. All of these institutional investments provide individuals with perceived utility from the system and therefore increase their attachment to the system, and decrease the probability of a revolutionary break. And theoretical and empirical research would have to pursue as an open question the degree to which these different investments account for the inertia of the status quo, and the conditions under which they decrease or increase their hold on individuals.</p>

<p>As for strategy, two thoughts suggest themselves. The first is to search for and find all those who for any reason have fallen through the cracks and to organize around the simple criterion of minimal investment in the status quo.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> The second is that statistical probabilities are essentially scientific maps for how not to think and behave. Statistics allow us to map with extreme precision the paths of resistance. This is because statistical distributions of thought and behavior across the status quo are exact measurements of what the system desires. Thus, I would make the case that the inversion of empirical statistical likelihoods is revolutionary political ethics. Randomness, along the lines of vulgar faux-Situationism or faux-Dada is not sufficient, for capitalism has an extraordinarily high tolerance for randomness. What is necessary is to produce systematically unlikely social outcomes. Notions of “affirmative action” and even more radical variants on that theme are correct to move in this direction, but they typically fail to take seriously that producing unlikely outcomes is far more difficult a challenge than switching some seats at status quo tables. It requires that we have a far more sophisticated theoretical and empirically defensible model of how macro-structures actually respond to low-level individual or group behavior, and it requires that we orchestrate our individual and group behavior according to what are likely far more complicated and sophisticated strategic requirements.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>This Marxian schema of the proletariat still looms behind radical identity politics today in that a special revolutionary agency is now simply associated with various different groups other than the Marxian worker. Even where the concept of intersectionality is highlighted, implicitly or explicitly there is very often the notion that certain intersections of identity uniquely prime certain groups to certain aspects of revolutionary struggle.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>For instance, it&rsquo;s EITHER feed one’s children disgustingly shitty food in solidarity with the masses or naturalize them into hideously bourgeois food privilege, or intellectualized self-loathing privilege, OR&hellip;<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>As a side note, it’s interesting how the internet at once enables this organization and has so quickly supplied its own institutional brakes, as radicals find themselves on the internet but they’re only allowed to find themselves so long as their theoretical and communicative frameworks are adequately consistent with the status quo. See my piece on media choice, the internet, and what has happened to leftist communication.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A concept of political validity in quantitative social science]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/11/03/a-concept-of-political-validity-in-quantitative-social-science/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-03T17:12:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/11/03/a-concept-of-political-validity-in-quantitative-social-science</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let us call <em>bourgeois data</em> any research data the collection of which is funded by groups invested in the status quo. Bourgeois data, which is to say nearly all the quantitative data used by social scientists, suffer from a specific type of bias for which most methodologists show very little concern, despite the extraordinary analytical attention they devote to the question of bias in social-scientific inference more generally. Methodologists are likely unconcerned about the possibility of <em>institutional</em> biases in data collection because they have precisely the same institutional investments as the funders of data collection projects. Methodologists will consider &ldquo;external validity&rdquo; (whether the data reflects what we think it reflects in the world) and &ldquo;internal validity&rdquo; (the logical coherence of inferences), but rarely do they consider what we might call <em>political validity</em>, which we might provisionally define as the scientific legitimacy of the basic worldview, determined by a researcher’s institutional environment, with which scientific inferences are verbally constructed. In other words, we must take seriously the question of whether the institutional environment which sponsors data-collection and research activity more generally is itself non-random and non-trivial. I suspect that for too long this question has been delegated to “critical” theorists in a disingenuous gesture which gives them just enough attention so that positivist social scientists can say their discipline already has people “working on” this issue, but not so much attention that positivists have to make any serious adjustments in how we actually think, write, or speak about the political implications of our research agendas.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, bourgeois data are almost by definition generated by a non-random, non-trivial social process which biases at the very least its <em>terms</em>, if not necessarily the internal or external validity of conclusions drawn from it. By beginning with a vocabulary drawn from a status quo which is from a social-scientific perspective perfectly arbitrary, it ends with conclusions the <em>meaning of which</em> are equally arbitrary, no matter how internally or external valid those conclusions might be. More to the point, the non-random, non-trivial process which shapes a status quo into one vocabulary rather than another is, of course, power. This is why critical theory&rsquo;s demand for reflexivity in social science is not empty posturing, as so many positivist social scientists dismissively believe. Rather, that demand points to a bona fide problem of scientific inference which is not merely humanistic critique from cultural studies departments. To put the issue in the words of positivist social science: the problem is that the words we use to draw conclusions from empirical patterns are never &ldquo;controlled for.&rdquo; We need theoretical work which will, in a methodologically rigorous fashion, subject the naive vocabularies of contemporary social science to a verification process where arbitrary power-driven linguistic determinations are &ldquo;controlled for&rdquo; and replaced in those theoretical edifices we devise to “house” the empirical patterns we discover.</p>

<p>(Social scientists, it must be admitted, have a child-like trust of the politicians and institutions from which they inherit their vocabularies, perhaps because like children they live from the good graces of these parents.)</p>

<p>Most contemporary datasets respond to some research demand that is considered valuable from the perspective of the status quo; it will be motivated by hypotheses the confirmation and rejection of which are consistent with the status quo, for no other reason than all of the actors involved prefer the status quo to a radical overhaul. One doesn’t need to even be a Marxist to believe this, perfectly mainstream rational-choice theories as well as sociological institutionalism confirm this point easily. Because we know these simple truths about institutions but can’t be bothered to take them very seriously in our own work—because the committment to truth, to unbiased inference, would actually demand an explicitly revolutionary politics for which social science does not have the courage today, quantiative social scientists in particular are like finance columnists who evaluate businesses they own stock in without disclosing this fact to readers.</p>

<p>Fortunately, for those of us who take seriously the revolutionary political agenda implied by the necessity of the scientific method, it is not at all the case that we are simply awash with hopelessly and uselessly prejudiced data. Bourgeois data cannot help but accidentally shed light on aspects of the social system it never had any interest in and would have preferred to omit. And it is these aspects to which we must devote our attention if we are to glean from biased data the stories which are most important for correcting the data’s institutional biases. I will call <em>epiphanic data</em> those datasets which emerge from transforming, subsetting, modeling, and otherwise manipulating bourgeois data in order to glean from it radical, anti-institutional insights. It might be objected that if the institutions which sponsor data collection so contaminate data with political bias, then what allows us to think we can glean non-biased conclusions from it? In that voice which positivists use to insinuate that critical theorists are merely conspiracy theorists with paranoiac worldviews: “Why is it not the case that this data is doomed to reproduce the status quo, if the data-collecting instituions are so politically perverse?” There are a few reasons why even the most bourgeois data can be used for anti-bourgeis, epiphanic social science.</p>

<p>The drive for short-term profit incentivizes institutions and individuals to collect dangerously more data than is ideal for the perpetuation of the status quo, at the risk of revealing contradictions which indict the system as a whole. Those groups funding data collection in one area are often unaware and, in any event, politically unconcerned with data collected in another area. Of course, they are politically aware of issues such as general conflicts of bureaucratic “turf” but certainly not in the long-term, revolutionary political dimensions under consideration here. Bourgeois data collection is complacent also because the division of academic labor is so developed and intensely enforced that status quo institutions don’t really have to worry about anyone discovering relationships <em>across many interdisciplinary datasets</em>, even though such datasets are widely and freely available. Bourgeois institutions have been emboldened by a severe undersupply of revolutionaries in quantitative social science. This has permitted data-collectiong institutions a great deal of complacency on this point. A sudden exogenous increase in radical social scientists could quickly seize on bourgeois data and extract from it extremely damning indictments of the status quo, which from a technical perspective would be almost childishly simple but have never yet been performed because the institutional biases are such that these findings are not rewarded. At the same time, phenomena such as racism, colonialism and patriarchy have, for a very long time, artifically depressed literacy, education, and civil rights to specific groups, suppressing demand for a really true, popular social science which would dispel the most vicious falsities and generate more legitimate equilibria. So long as the less privileged groups could not effectivley demand true social science, bourgeois institutions felt safe to collect data to their cold heart’s content.</p>

<p>But today, decolonization, civil rights movements, feminist movements, various democratic uprisings, and the rise of mass education as well as the internet, have all lead to a huge increase in the aggregate demand for precisely this kind of social science. Witness the rise of the “data visualizer”, that not-quite-data-scientist internet persona who specializes in fashionable data-intensive infographics for mass distribution on the web. Such a persona is merely an inane example of how millions of people around the world would be increasingly amenable to a popular, emancipatory social science.</p>

<p>In summary, for those who wish to read between the lines of bourgeois data, there always exists epiphanic data in the simple will to read it differently, a parallax data which promises a wide world of revolutionary intellectual exploration. Unfortunately, this world of data is currently available only to those few of us who have been given the unequally distributed privileges required to mine it <em>and</em> a sufficiently youthful spirit to still <em>want to</em>. But a mass defection of radical young social scientists from currently privileged research agendas toward anti-institutional perspectives would open a large range of research which need not be technically sophisticated to quickly produce huge increases in both the overall truth quotient of social science and its overall effectiveness in radical egalitarian political change.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[There are more than enough hours in the day]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/09/15/there-are-more-than-enough-hours-in-the-day/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-15T16:46:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/09/15/there-are-more-than-enough-hours-in-the-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The popular refrain that &ldquo;there aren&rsquo;t enough hours in the day&rdquo; is an interesting departure from the long and storied political and rhetorical battle to <em>objectively</em> decrease the hours of the working day. It is an extraordinary gauge of our political pacification that when so many people have such a hard time meeting a pervasive social and economic expectation, we would sooner <em>ask for an extension</em> of the expectation than its abolition.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ego and revolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/08/31/ego-and-revolution/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-31T20:42:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jmrphy.github.io/blog/2013/08/31/ego-and-revolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My ego often wrestles with itself: Obviously I want to avoid arrogance and self absorption and selfishness, but the project of revolution almost presupposes delusions of grandeur and extraordinary self-confidence (if only a confidence in the collectives of which one is a constituent). Capitalist individualism is highly egoistic but ironically it keeps egos small and frail under a herd mentality inclusive of exploitation and alienation. I would much prefer the opposite contradiction of wildly inflated egos demanding and creating revolutionary egalitarianism. Indeed, in such a truly egoistic society such as ours, a powerful and disruptive political project to truly force egalitarian movement might require not the altruistic ethos of shrunken egos but a proliferation of individuals sufficiently egoistic to see themselves as truly and immediately capable of changing the world.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
